<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
    <titleInfo>
        <title>Household and Family Trends in Europe: from Convergence to Divergence</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <abstract>The International Year of the Family 1994 together with the World Population Conference have drawn greater attention to the changing family. On the level of the European Union interest in the family was intensified, as the first steps taken towards the creation of a European household and family statistics and the strengthening of the European Observatory on National Family Policies (EONFP) show. In addition, other international organisations, such as the Council of Europe or the United Nations Economic Commission for Europe (ECE), have intensified their activities in the field of population and family research. In this context the question may be posed how household and family structures in Europe evolve. Not only for the European Union but also for sociological research in general the question of divergence or convergence of national household and family structures and of national demographic developments is of great importance.</abstract>
    <name>
        <namePart>Rothenbacher, Franz</namePart>
    </name>
    <location>
        <url>http://www.mzes.uni-mannheim.de/eurodata/newsletter/no1/househol.html</url>
    </location>
    <originInfo>
        <publisher>EURODATA Research Archive. Mannheim Centre for European Social Research (MZES)</publisher>
        <dateCreated encoding="w3cdtf">1995</dateCreated>
    </originInfo>
    <physicalDescription>
        <internetMediaType>text/html</internetMediaType>
    </physicalDescription>
    <relatedItem type="otherFormat">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>EURODATA Newsletter No.1</title>
        </titleInfo>
    </relatedItem>
    <classification authority="IZSOZ">10303</classification>
    <classification authority="IZSOZ">10209</classification>
    <subject authority="IZSOZ">
        <topic>Europa</topic>
    </subject>
    <subject authority="IZSOZ">
        <topic>Familiensoziologie</topic>
    </subject>
    <subject authority="IZSOZ">
        <topic>Familienstand</topic>
    </subject>
    <subject authority="IZSOZ">
        <topic>Familienstruktur</topic>
    </subject>
    <subject authority="IZSOZ">
        <topic>internationaler Vergleich</topic>
    </subject>
</mods>