<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
    <titleInfo>
        <title>U.S. Perspectives on the position and role of Germany and Japan in international and regional structures. The 1950s and the Present</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <abstract>Rather than focusing on the relative power of Germany and Japan within the international system, my attention is directed towards U.S. perspectives on the position and role of Germany and Japan in regional and international structures as points of reference with a view of analysing the transformation of Germany's and Japan's foreign relations in conjunction with changes in the global economy and regional security concerns. The differences between firstly Germany and Japan, secondly the regional context of German and Japanese policies, and thirdly Germany and Japan as international actors are too important and the German-Japanese relationships too underdeveloped (in spite of the spurts in the early 1980s and since 1993) to allow a direct comparison of Germany's and Japan's positions and roles in International Relations. The comparison between U.S. perspectives on Japan and "Germany integrated into Europe" is more manageable and conducive to an assessment of changes:&lt;br/&gt;  - the U.S. is a determining factor in Europe's/Pacific Asia's affairs,&lt;br/&gt;  - Germany/Japan regards the U.S. as a pillar of its foreign policy,&lt;br/&gt;  - the U.S. considers (for the time being) Germany's/Japan's position and role essential to what the U.S. can accomplish regionally and internationally.&lt;br/&gt;  The weight of these "factors" ensures that the comparison of U.S. perspectives on Germany and Japan is a reliable guide to the Interpretation of the foreign policy positions and roles of the Federal Republic of Germany (FRG) and Japan in regional and international structures.</abstract>
    <name>
        <namePart>Schmidt, Gustav</namePart>
    </name>
    <location>
        <url>http://www.ruhr-uni-bochum.de/lehrstuhl-ip/Ostasien.pdf</url>
    </location>
    <originInfo>
        <dateCreated encoding="w3cdtf">1999</dateCreated>
    </originInfo>
    <physicalDescription>
        <internetMediaType>application/pdf</internetMediaType>
    </physicalDescription>
    <relatedItem type="otherFormat">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>Bochumer Jahrbuch zur Ostasienforschung, Bd. 23 (1999), S. 359-372.</title>
        </titleInfo>
    </relatedItem>
    <classification authority="IZSOZ">10505</classification>
    <subject authority="IZSOZ">
        <topic>Außenpolitik</topic>
    </subject>
    <subject authority="IZSOZ">
        <topic>Bundesrepublik Deutschland</topic>
    </subject>
    <subject authority="IZSOZ">
        <topic>Einfluss</topic>
    </subject>
    <subject authority="IZSOZ">
        <topic>Geopolitik</topic>
    </subject>
    <subject authority="IZSOZ">
        <topic>Japan</topic>
    </subject>
    <subject authority="IZSOZ">
        <topic>USA</topic>
    </subject>
    <subject authority="IZSOZ">
        <topic>politische Beziehungen</topic>
    </subject>
</mods>