<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
    <titleInfo>
        <title>The European population 1850-1945: A Historical Data Handbook</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <abstract>This contribution describes the project which is to publish a historical data handbook on the European population in 21 European countries, covering the time period of the first demographic transition, the years 1850-1945. All eighteen Western European nations are included plus the three Eastern European countries Czechoslovakia, Hungary and Poland. The handbook covers such topics as population development; the population structure by sex, age and marital status; the regional population structure; annual vital statistics developments in the fields of population growth and migration, fertility and legitimacy, infant mortality and life expectancy, nuptiality and divortiality. Furthermore, household and family data have been collected systematically using the population censuses as a basis. The book comprises several introductory comparative chapters and 21 national chapters for each country. Extensive documentation of available data and sources concludes the volume.</abstract>
    <name>
        <namePart>Rothenbacher, Franz</namePart>
    </name>
    <location>
        <url>http://www.mzes.uni-mannheim.de/eurodata/newsletter/no11/feature.html</url>
    </location>
    <originInfo>
        <publisher>EURODATA Research Archive. Mannheim Centre for European Social Research (MZES)</publisher>
        <dateCreated encoding="w3cdtf">2000</dateCreated>
    </originInfo>
    <physicalDescription>
        <internetMediaType>text/html</internetMediaType>
    </physicalDescription>
    <relatedItem type="otherFormat">
        <titleInfo>
            <title>EURODATA Newsletter No.11</title>
        </titleInfo>
    </relatedItem>
    <classification authority="IZSOZ">10303</classification>
    <classification authority="IZSOZ">10209</classification>
    <subject authority="IZSOZ">
        <topic>Bevölkerungsentwicklung</topic>
    </subject>
    <subject authority="IZSOZ">
        <topic>Demographie</topic>
    </subject>
    <subject authority="IZSOZ">
        <topic>Rezension</topic>
    </subject>
    <subject authority="IZSOZ">
        <topic>historisch</topic>
    </subject>
    <subject authority="IZSOZ">
        <topic>internationaler Vergleich</topic>
    </subject>
</mods>