<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<book>
    <bookinfo>
        <graphic fileref="logo.jpg"/>
        <productname>XSLT Processor</productname>
        <title>GSoC 2008 : XSLT Processor</title>
        <author>
            <firstname>Leela</firstname>
            <surname>Manoranjan</surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address format="linespecific">
                    <email>ManoRanjan.Balanagu@gmail.com</email>
                </address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </bookinfo>
    <ci:include xmlns:ci="http://apache.org/cocoon/include/1.0" src="sidebar.xml"/>
    <chapter>
        <title>XSLT Processor - Statement of Work</title>
        <para>Author/Student: <b>Leela Manoranjan</b><br/>
        Mentor: Pierrick Brihaye</para>
        <section>            
            <title>XSLT Processor (GSOC 2008)</title>
            <para>Hi Everybody,</para>
            <para>I would like to introduce myself and give an overview for the Google Summer of code, 2008 
            Accepted project XSLT Processor (<a href="http://code.google.com/soc/2008/exist/about.html">
            http://code.google.com/soc/2008/exist/about.html</a>).</para>
            <para>I am postgraduagte student, attending Masters in Software Systes from DLPD, Birla Institute of 
            Technology, Pilani, India. I have 4 years of working experience in Software development using the J2EE 
            technologies. Currently I am employed with Cordys R&amp;D and am involved in developing of BPMS suite.</para>
            <para>This is my first project with eXist and also with open source and feely honoured to be part of 
            open source code development, and have understand is both a challenge and commitment, I believe will 
            keep the commitment for long time.</para>
            <para>In this summer project, I will be working to implement XSLT Processor for the eXist Database.</para>
            <para>Shortly: eXist open source XML Database has in built support for XQuery and XPath parsing. Currently, 
            eXist supports transformation of XML's with the use of external XSLT processor, which is 
            configurable to operate with multiple processors. However, as I believe, the XSLT processor, 
            is dependent on both the XQuery and XPath, and implementing XSLT Processor will make eXist 
            compatible with XML Standards.</para>
            <para>Thanks for reading. Will be communicating more as I to work with my mentor ( Pierrick Brihaye).</para>             
        </section>
        
        
    </chapter>
</book>

