<book xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"><bookinfo><graphic fileref="../../../resources/images/empty.GIF"/><productname>Tamboti</productname><title>What is Tamboti?</title><date>December 2010</date><author><firstname>Dulip</firstname><surname>Withanage</surname><affiliation><address format="linespecific"><email>withanage@asia-europe.uni-heidelberg.de</email></address></affiliation></author><author><firstname>Jens Østergaard</firstname><surname>Petersen</surname><affiliation><address format="linespecific"><email>petersen@asia-europe.uni-heidelberg.de</email></address></affiliation></author></bookinfo><xi:include href="sidebar.xml"/><chapter><title>What is Tamboti?</title><section><title>Background</title><para/></section><section><title>Features</title><para/></section><section><title>Outline of the Tamboti Help System</title><para/><section><title>Walk-through</title><para>
                    Tamboti, the new metadata framework, has two main functions. One is to make it possible to search for metadata records and one is to make it possible to create new metadata records and edit existing ones. 
                </para><para>
                    To provide a framework that allows many users to work on the database at the same time, a very flexible user system has been introduced. This allows each user to keep records private, to share records with one or more groups of one's own choice, and to open records with to everybody.
                </para><para>
                    The motto for Tamboti is flexibility - the flexibility that has been demanded both in matters of metadata description and in matters of control over who can access one's records. One should not be needlessly restricted in what one wishes to describe by an over-simplified input schema and one should not forced to share one's input unless one chooses to do so.
                </para><para>
                    Such flexibility comes at a price, for it obviously requires you to make choices, choices that in some circumstances may seem overly cumbersome. A lot can still be done to only display this complexity when it is required: in the present version, we recognise that the interface is over-complex in places.
                </para><para>
                    The format of the metadata records is the so-called MODS format, a standard maintained by the US Library of Congress called "MODS" for Metadata Object Description Schema. This standard allows one to catalogue many different kinds of material, not just books and articles, but web sites, photos, maps, computer files - and so on. It allows one to catalogue in great detail, but it also allows fairly simple cataloguing. It allows one to relate one record (say, an entry for a book) to another entry (say an entry for a movie) and it allows one to make notes that one can "type" freely. You don't have to make acquaintance with this format, but basically all it does is to surround each type of information with a set of tags, like <title>Midsummer Night's Dream</title>.
                </para><para>
                    When you access Tamboti without logging in, you are able to search in the material that is open to everybody. When you log in, you can additionally search in material that is open to you alone and to groups to which you belong. Even when you log in, you will not see all material in the database, since there will be other users who keep some of their records private. The part that you wish to keep to yourself cannot be seen by anybody else, unless you choose to allow this. When searches are performed, only the material that is open to a certain user is being retrieved: the rest of the database could just as well be non-existent. Needless to say, the parts that outsiders cannot see cannot be edited by them.
                </para><para>
                    If you click on Folder View - the grey column on the right with the hierarchical indents at the top - it will flip to a vertical position. What you see in Folder View before you log in and after you log in differs in several respects. 
                </para><para>
                    Before you log in, you will only see three buttons below the grey bar. These are for expanding and collapsing the hierarchy of folders that the database consists of - and for reloading the list of folders, should any new folder have been added in the meantime. 
                </para><para>
                    Below that you will see the name of the base folder "mods". All records in Tamboti are collected in this folder and its subfolders. In front of the folder icon, there is a plus sign; if you click on it, the folder opens up - and the plus turns into a minus which allows you to close the folder again. You may know this interface from Windows Explorer and elsewhere. 
                </para><para>
                    If you click on the first button at the top, all folders are opened fully, where all folders close up if you click the second. The third button, the one for reloading the folder view, is only needed if you work for a long time on the database and new folders have been created by others since you logged in - these you will only have access to if you reload the Folder View.
                </para><para>
                    When you click on a folder or a folder name, you will see that the "path" leading to the folder from the base folder, "mods", separated by slashes, in the manner of "/mods/publications". Clicking on a folder in this way is how you decide where to perform a search. If you search for something, it will be searched for inside the material in the path you have chosen. You can only choose one path to search in at a time. If you choose "/mods" as your search path, a search will search through all material available to you in the database.
                </para><para>
                    If you wish to find all material available in a certain path, leave the search term empty and click "Search."
                </para><para>
                    Searching in itself should be fairly obvious. The options are more or less the same as in any library catalogue. In a separate section of this tutorial you can read about the search options at your disposal.
                </para><para>
                    If you search find a specific term in the records in the path you have selected or make an "empty search" to retrieve all records in the path you have selected, you will be presented with a hit-list if more than one record is retrieved. If one a single record satisfies your search criteria, a detail view of this record will be shown. If several records are found and you click one of them in the hit-list, the detail view for the record in question will be shown. 
                </para><para>
                    On this detail view, you can see in which folder the record is located, under "Folder Name."
                </para><para>
                    On this detail view there are also some buttons, buttons which reflect what you can do. If you have not logged in, this is not much: you can add the record to a list of records the database remembers for you, a list which you can later export. You can also access the XML view of the record in question, that is the "raw" XML view of the MODS record, with all information enclosed by tags. While this view is very informative, it will take some time to decipher by reading it. 
                </para><para>
                    The detail view shows most of the contents of the records, arranged in two columns, but some of the information may not be displayed, because it is too complex or too prolix or because it lacks relevance to most users. The XML view shows the unabridged view of a record. If you have saved a number of records and export them, the export format will also be raw XML, but applications like EndNote and Zotero can import this format (in Citavi, this import function is still under development). This means that you can work with the records you find in Tamboti in ordinary desktop applications, such as you favourite word processor.
                </para><para>
                    When you log in, changes occur both in the buttons above and in the folders below.
                </para><para>
                    In order to log in to the Tamboti framework, use your Cluster username and password. When you click on the "Login" sign in the upper right corner, a pop-up window will appear. Enter your username in the following format: USERNAME@ad.uni-heidelberg.de. Note that, for the time being, you will have to add "@ad.uni-heidelberg.de" to your username. As password, enter the password you use to access Cluster resources. Your password is not stored in the database, but authenticated against the central university Active Directory.
                </para><para>
                    After logging in, you will see that the username you are logged in under in the upper right corner, with an option to log out again. Please note that you are automatically logged out after ?? minutes of inactivity.
                </para><para>
                    After you have logged in, the folders that are accessible to you have changed. First of all, you have a Home folder. If you click on your Home folder, you will see that the path is not /mods/Home, but "/mods/" followed by your full username.  
                </para><para>
                    The Home folder is represented in bold typeface. This means that you have rights to write to this folder, this is, that you can save records in it. If other users allow you to write to their folders, they will also appear in bold in the Folder View when you log in. All the other folders, that is, all the folder with a light greyed-out appearance, are folders you can read only. As explained above, there are many folders that you simply cannot see, folders that belong to other users that have not been made viewable by everyone by the users themselves or that have not been shared by the users with a group that you are a member of. - More about sharing folder below.
                </para><para>
                    By default, Tamboti comes with a number of sample records that illustrate different kinds of records. These you can treat as your own: at regular intervals the "Samples" folder is restored to its original state, so you can do no (permanent) harm here. They are mainly of use when learning how to use the editor; more about this later.
                </para><para>
                    If you click on your Home folder, you will see that a number of new buttons occur in the line above the list of folders.
                </para><para>
                    One new button allows you to create a folder inside the folder that you have selected. If you select your Home folder and click this button, a dialogue pops up, in which you can give a name to this folder.
                </para><para>
                    Another button allows you to move a folder to someplace else "within your command."
                </para><para>
                    Yet another button allows you to delete a folder that belongs to you.
                </para><para>
                    More complicated options are presented by the new button: Manage Folder Sharing. The options here will be discussed separately.
                </para><para>
                    The last button is in many ways the most important one: Create Stand-Alone Resource (more about "Stand-Alone" below). If you click this button, you will leave the Tamboti search interface and be taken to the Tamboti editor in which you can enter information for a record. You will first be presented with a dialogue in which are are asked to choose which kind of record you wish to enter and which language is used in the resource (and which language you intend to use when cataloguing). More about this later.
                </para><para>
                    The search interface and editor are linked in more ways than this. If you are already in the editor or dialogue box now, you can click Cancel to return to the search interface. Now try locating a record that you can edit. 
                </para><para>
                    Tamboti comes with a folder full of sample records of different kinds. These you can edit (and delete and move, though there is probably no good reason to do so): at regular intervals the folder is restored to its original state, so all changes done here will be undone.
                </para><para>
                    If you click on the Samples folder and perform a search with no search term, your will find all of the sample records. If you click on one of them, you will find that you now have more options than you had with the records that did not belong to you. The records you did not own you could only save in a list and view as XML, but when you have logged in and are looking at a record that you are allowed to change, you will see a set of new buttons.
                </para><para>
                    First of all, you have now the option to Edit Resource, that is, to open the record inside the editor - to correct mistakes, make additions, add notes and abstracts and so on. 
                </para><para>
                    Just as you have the option to delete a folder you have created, any file you can edit, you can delete as well.
                </para><para>
                    Just as you have the option to move a folder you own to some other place own control, you can move any file you can edit, for instance, to a folder within your own Home folder for finished records, to a folder used for having records checked by someone or to a folder that is common to your group.
                </para><para>
                    When you started out in a folder you had write access to, you were able to "Create Stand-Alone Record", now you are able to "Create Related Record" - what is the difference?
                </para><para>
                    The difference is that whereas some resources are published on their own, others occur inside others. A standard book is a good example of a stand-alone resource, whereas an article is a good example of a related resource: it obviously occurs inside a periodical. The idea behind making this distinction in the database is that many entries will be "Related" in this way and that it does not make sense for many persons to input the same data for a periodical - or for one and the same person to input the same data over and over again. The same goes for anthologies: many contributions to a single anthology may be catalogued. Also, if the information regarding periodicals and anthologies are centralised in this way, the entries can be improved and fitted with extra information more easily, and the inconsistencies of the decentralised approach can be avoided.
                </para><para>
                    Since - from some point of view - one might view every resource as part of something else, this approach could of course be carried to extremes. The "Create Related Record" is primarily to be used with periodicals and anthologies. Many books occur in series, but the information regarding the series is often hard to find and often not part of the standard citation for a book, so this information can be added to the entry for the book - later on, a librairan may come along and sort these references out and create a centralised structure out of many references to the same series, but this is not the task of the ordinary user.
                </para><para>
                    What this means in concrete terms is this: if you are cataloguing a book (or some other resource which does not obviously occur as part of some other publication), use "Create Stand-Alone Record". If you are catalguing an article or a contribution to an anthology, then first search to see if the anthology is already catalgouged. If it is, then use "Create Related Record" in the record for the periodical or anthology: your "child" record will then automatically be linked with the "parent" record. If you are the first to catalogue an article in a certain periodical or the first to catalogue an contribution to a certain anthology, then catelogue the periodical or anthology first: when you have done so, use "Create Related Record" from there.
                </para><para>
                    Staff will take care to search out records of periodicals and anthologies and will prioritise the quality of these records, so you can limit yourself to entering the basics in such cases.
                </para><para>
                    This record will eventually be saved inside the folder that was selected when you clicked the button (but now you know that you can delete it and move it somewhere else if you want to).
                </para></section><section><title>Search Functions</title><para/></section><section><title>Editor</title><para/></section>
            <!--xi:include href="security-manager.xml"/--></section></chapter></book>