<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<book>
    <bookinfo>
        <graphic fileref="logo.jpg"/>
        <productname>Open Source Native XML Database</productname>
        <title>GSoC 2007 : XQJ Driver for eXist</title>
        <author>
            <firstname>Cherif</firstname>
            <surname>YAYA</surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address format="linespecific">
                    <email>chef.ya@gmail.com</email>
                </address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </bookinfo>
    <ci:include xmlns:ci="http://apache.org/cocoon/include/1.0" src="sidebar.xml"/>
    <chapter>
        <title>XQuery API for Java Project - Statement of Works</title>
        <para>Author/Student: <b>Cherif YAYA</b><br/>
        Mentor: Adam Retter</para>
        <section>
            <title>Project Description</title>
            <para>The goal of this project is to implement a driver that enables developers to easily access the eXist XQuery engine from a Java application. The implementation will follow version 1.0 of the XQuery API for Java which attempts to provide a common way for Java developers to interact with XQuery engines. Over the years, XML has become the predominant data interchange format and eXist provides developers with an easy and powerful way to manage, store and query their XML datasets. An XQJ driver for eXist will be a very valuable addition.</para>
            
            <para>An early draft of the XQJ API standard is available as JSR (Java Specification Request) 225 at the <ulink url="http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=225">Java Community Process Website</ulink>. This draft outilines the interfaces and functionality that an XQJ driver implementation has to meet.</para>
       </section>
       <section>
       		<title>Proposed Solution</title>
            <para>An eXist Database can essentially be deployed in one of two ways: either as an embedded library that runs in the JVM of the client application or as a standalone server possibly located on a remote host. A different XQJ driver is therefore needed for each of these use cases.</para>
            <para>To implement the local connection driver, eXist core classes will be used through the Internal eXist API. Different instances of the eXist engine can be managed with the <ulink url="http://exist-db.org/api/org/exist/storage/package-frame.html">org.exist.storage</ulink> package. Additionnaly the package <ulink url="http://exist-db.org/api/org/exist/collections/package-frame.html">org.exist.collections</ulink> provide all needed functionnality to access the database collections and the DBBroker class offers a convenient method to execute queries (getXqueryService() method).</para>
            <para>To implement the remote connection driver, the REST API already implemented in eXist will be used. I wrote some demo code that gives an example of how the driver might be used, this code is available at <ulink url="http://cherif.ycsoft.org/soc/xqj/">http://cherif.ycsoft.org/soc/xqj/</ulink> . It currently uses the XML:DB API offered by eXist, however, the goal is to replace the XML:DB API by the XQJ implementation.</para>
       </section>
       <section>
       		<title>Implementation Schedule</title>     
            <para>Work on this project will be undertaken using a test-driven development methodology, following this schedule: 
                <ul>
                    <li>Weeks 1-2 of June: Implementation of the local connection driver with JUnit test classes for each use case</li>
                    <li>Weeks 3-4 of June: Testing of the local connection driver</li>
                    <li>Deliverable: Fully tested local connection driver</li>
                    <li>Weeks 1-2 of July: Implementation of the remote connection driver with JUnit test classes for each use case</li>
                    <li>Weeks 3-4 of July: Testing of the remote driver</li>
                    <li>Deliverable: Fully tested remote connection driver</li>
                    <li>Weeks 1-2 of August: Documentation writing for both drivers</li>
                    
                </ul>
            </para>			
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Deliverables</title>            
			<para>
                <unorderedlist>
                    <listitem>A Local Connection Driver to be used when accessing an embedded eXist database</listitem>
                    <listitem>JUnit test cases for the Local Connection Driver</listitem>
                    <listitem>A Remote Connection Driver to be used for remote standalone eXist databases</listitem>
                    <listitem>JUnit test cases for the Remote Connection Driver</listitem>
                    <listitem>Documentation and Examples</listitem>
                </unorderedlist>
                
            </para>
            
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Student Profile</title>
            <para>My name is Cherif YAYA and I have been selected to participate in the <ulink url="http://code.google.com/soc">Google Summer of Code</ulink> 2007 for the eXist Open Source Native XML Database Project. I will be working on an XQuery API for Java Driver for eXist, under the supervision of my mentor Adam Retter.</para>
            <para>I am a junior Computer Sciences student at the <ulink url="http://www.utc.fr">University of Technology of Compiegne</ulink> in France. I first became interested in programming whilst in high school when I discovered that my old vTech Genius 9000 had a BASIC interpretor. Since then, I have learned various programming languages : C/C++, Python, Java, C#, PHP... In my spare time, my favourite occupations are programming and discovering new Operating Systems. I love tweaking my computer. There's always something that can be automated to make your life as a computer user much easier, so I focus on developing solutions to the various problems I face as a computer addict. I have released several end user applications and most of them are available on my website : <ulink url="http://www.ycsoft.org">http://www.ycsoft.org</ulink></para>
            
            
            <para>Since September 2006, I have been doing an exchange program at the <ulink url="http://www.upenn.edu">University of Pennsylvania</ulink> in the USA. I have had the opportunity to take multiple courses which have introduced me to XML and related technologies: XQuery, XSLT, Web Services... I expect to apply these skills whilst working on the XQJ driver and hopt to learn a lot about the state of the art in XML processing.</para>
            
            
            <para>I first heard of the Google Summer of Code one year ago when I applied for the 2006 edition. Unfortunately, I was not accepted, so I spent the whole year in preparation for this years event and I am very pleased to have been accepted to work on the eXist XQJ driver project. I sincerely hope to make a positive contribution to the eXist initiative.</para>
            
        </section>
        
        
    </chapter>
</book>

