<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <graphic fileref="logo.jpg"/>
    <productname>Open Source Native XML Database</productname>
    <title>Google Summer of Code 2007</title>
    <author>
      <firstname>Wolfgang M.</firstname>
      <surname>Meier</surname>
    </author>
  </bookinfo>

  <ci:include xmlns:ci="http://apache.org/cocoon/include/1.0" src="sidebar.xml"/>

  <chapter>
    <title>Google Summer of Code 2007</title>
    
        <para>eXist is participating in the Google Summer of Code 2007. Applications have been
        evaluated by both eXist and Google and <emphasis>two</emphasis> projects have now been accepted, details are below.
        Our original project ideas sumitted to Google are still listed below for informational purposes,
        each of these could still be used for a small personal/academic project, if you are interested
        please contact us.</para>
        <para>For all questions concerning the Summmer of Code,
        contact our GSoC administrators <ulink url="mailto:existadmin@gmail.com">eXistAdmin@gmail.com</ulink>, send an email to the
        exist-open <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=17691">mailing list</ulink>
        or meet us in <ulink url="http://irc.exist-db.org/">IRC</ulink>. For short questions, IRC
        is the preferred medium.</para>
    
    <section>
    	<title>Timeline</title>
    	<itemizedlist>
   	    	<listitem><del>5th - 12th March - eXist applies to Google Summer of Code</del></listitem>
	    	<listitem><del>14th - 26th March - Student Applications</del></listitem>
	    	<listitem><del>26th March - 10th April - Appraisal and evaluation of student applications</del></listitem>
	    	<listitem><del>11th April - Succesfull student applications announced</del></listitem>
	    	<listitem><del>11th April - 27th May - Students learn about eXist community and project</del></listitem>
	    	<listitem>28th May - Students begin coding</listitem>
	    	<listitem>9th July - Students upload work in progress / Mentors start mid-term evaluation</listitem>
	    	<listitem>16th July - Mentors finish mid-term evaluation</listitem>
	    	<listitem>20th August - Students finish coding and start evaluation / Mentors start final evalutaion</listitem>
	    	<listitem>31st August - Students and Mentors finish final evaluation</listitem>
    	</itemizedlist>
    </section>
    
    <section>
	    <title>Accepted Projects</title>
	    <section>
	    	<title><ulink url="http://code.google.com/soc/exist/appinfo.html?csaid=57CE1501A899507C">XQuery API for Java</ulink></title>
	    	<para>
	    		<orderedlist>
                	<listitem>Student: Cherif YAYA</listitem>
     	       		<listitem>Mentor: Adam Retter</listitem>
     	       		<listitem><ulink url="soc-xqj.xml">Statement of Work</ulink></listitem>
                </orderedlist>
	    	</para>
	    </section>
	    <section>
	    	<title><ulink url="http://code.google.com/soc/exist/appinfo.html?csaid=69EADF1DA6525E5B">eXist extension to fulltext search</ulink></title>
	    	<para>
	    		<orderedlist>
		           	<listitem>Student: Akhil Kumar Meshram</listitem>
	    	   		<listitem>Mentor: Pierrick Brihaye</listitem>
     	       		<listitem><ulink url="soc-ft.xml">Statement of Work</ulink></listitem>	    	   		
    	   		</orderedlist>
    	   		<note><para>Akhil disappeared just after mid-term evaluation, leaving some regressions in
    	   		the parser's code and a very incomplete work on the modularized fulltext index which was 
    	   		breaking backward compatibility.</para>
    	   		<para>Pierrick has fixed the incompatibility stuff in september/october and we hope to integrate
    	   		Akhil's FT grammar part, which looks OK, into the new redesigned parser (under Leif-Jöran's responsability).</para></note> 
       		</para>
	    </section>
    </section>
                
    <section>
      <title>Suggested Project Ideas</title>

      <section>
	<title>Implement JSR 225: XQuery API for Java <emphasis>(Accepted)</emphasis></title>

	<para>The XQuery API for Java (XQJ) attempts to provide a common API
	for access to XML databases, very similar to the JDBC API for relational
	databases. Though it is still an early draft, the XQJ is already available for a
	number of XQuery enabled systems, including <ulink href="http://saxon.sf.net">saxon</ulink>.
	</para>

	<para>eXist currently uses the XML:DB API as its main Java interface. However, the
	XML:DB initiative, which proposed the specification, has been dead since quite some time
	and the API is no longer maintained. Compared to the XML:DB, the XQuery API for Java limits
	itself to a single job: executing XQuery expressions and integrating the results into the calling
	Java program. From a developer's perspective, the XQJ is much simpler to learn and
	understand. On the other hand, it does not cover subjects like data manipulation or database
	administration. However, eXist provides a large number of XQuery extension functions to acomplish
	these tasks, so the lack of functionality in the API is compensated.</para>

	<para>Since eXist can be used as an embedded library as well as a server process, two drivers will
	be needed for the XQJ: one that directly connects to the embedded database and another one that
	communicates with a remote DB.</para>

	<para><emphasis>Resources:</emphasis></para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><ulink url="http://jcp.org/aboutJava/communityprocess/edr/jsr225/">JSR 225</ulink></para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><ulink url="http://www.saxonica.com/documentation/using-xquery/xqj.html">XQJ in
	    the saxon XSLT/XQuery engine</ulink></para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><ulink url="http://www.datadirect.com/developer/xquery/topics/xqj_tutorial/index.ssp">Tutorial
	    using DataDirect's query engine</ulink></para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Remote Debugging Interface</title>

	<para>XQuery programs can get quite complex (scripts with more than 1000 lines are not uncommon), especially
	if they use a lot of modules. However, debugging the code is currently a tedious, time-consuming job due to the lack
	of tool support. While some commercial XML editors do already include XQuery debuggers (e.g. Oxygen), eXist lacks an appropriate
	debugging API to interface with them.</para>

	<para>A remote debugging API should be implemented on top of the eXist server. This should at least include the
	ability to stop XQuery execution at predefined breakpoints, inspect the current query context and switch into single-step
	execution. A basic command-line or graphical debugging interface should be shipped with eXist. The Oxygen team
	already expressed their interest to support eXist from their commercial XQuery debugger.</para>

	<para><emphasis>Resources:</emphasis></para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>see the debugging API in <ulink url="saxon.sf.net">saxon</ulink></para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>XQuery debugger in <ulink url="http://www.oxygenxml.com/xquery_debugger.html">Oxygen</ulink> (commercial product)</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Extend and Improve eXist's Full-Text Search Extensions <emphasis>(Accepted)</emphasis></title>

	<para>eXist always featured a set of special functions and operators to support full-text search, i.e. queries on
	tokens and phrases rather than substrings. However, the available functions just help to select a distinct text or
	attribute node in the document. Unlike traditional full-text systems, eXist does not rank the text match
	in comparison to other matches. Dedicated systems like Apache's Lucene assign a score to each match, which - in simple words -
	expresses the assumed "quality" of the match with respect to the user's query.</para>

	<para>The algorithms used in document-oriented full-text retrieval system can not be directly applied to an
	XML query engine though. For the document-oriented system, the context of a query is usually always the same: the entire 
	document (or a pre-defined "field"). In XQuery, the context is ever changing: there's basically no limit to the complexity of the query. The user can restrict
	his search to arbitrary nodes in the document or even combinations of nodes.</para>

	<para>The various existing approaches and algorithms thus need to be adopted to an XML context and properly integrated
	into the  XQuery environment. We think this is still a new and very interesting area of research. The W3C has
	already published first drafts for an "XQuery 1.0 and XPath 2.0 Full-Text" extension to XQuery, describing a syntax for
	full-text queries. Though these drafts are still subject to controverse discussions, they should be a guideline for the features
	to be implemented in eXist.</para>

	<para><emphasis>Resources:</emphasis></para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/xquery-full-text/">XQuery 1.0 and XPath 2.0 Full-Text</ulink>. W3C Working Draft.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Current <ulink url="http://localhost:8080/exist/xquery.xml#ext">full-text search extensions</ulink> in eXist.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Implement Full ACID Transaction Support</title>

	<para>Transaction support in eXist is currently limited to the functionality needed for crash recovery. Though eXist
	maintains transactions internally, they are currently not exposed to applications. Also, read operations are
	not transactional right now. In order to allow full user-controlled ACID transactions, some missing functionality
	needs to be implemented:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Concurrency control: eXist currently implements locking on the level of documents and collections. For
	    better transaction support, we need a more fine-grained concurrency control within the core B+-tree and an improved
	    lock management to detect or avoid deadlock situations.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>While eXist does already support full redo/undo operations during crash recovery, it does not provide a
	    rollback facility at runtime. Users can not explicitely abort and roll back a transaction (that's why we don't
	    expose transactions to the user at all). Performing a rollback on the core db files would be easily possible, but
	    we also need to take care of any indexes defined on the data.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Implement an XSLT 2.0 Processor</title>

	<para>eXist aims to be compliant with XQuery 2.0 specifications. It would be interesting that the "sister" recommendation, XSLT 2.0, should be implemented as well,
	thus allowing XSLT 2.0 processing on (eventually huge) persistent documents. Most of the code is already here since both recommendations are built on-top of XPath 2.0. </para>
	<para>However, this is still to be implemented:</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Clean separation of XPath 2.0 and XQuery 1.0 code. 
	    Exist used to have a dedicated package for XPath in the past: it somehow has to be revived and the XQuery 1.0 specific classes have to be moved to a dedicated package. 
	    Functions, including experimental grouping ones (which have to be improved with regard to performance) have to be moved as well.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Write a dedicated XSLT 2.0 frontend to the existing XQuery 1.0 parser that would be used to build the expression tree.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Attention should be drawn to performance concerns. Recent code is definitely more friendly to the programmer with regard to performance. Implementing an XSLT 2.0 processor could help in bringing even more improvements in this area.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	
	<para><emphasis>Resources:</emphasis></para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt20/">XSL Transformations (XSLT) Version 2.0</ulink>. W3C Recommendation.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><ulink url="http://monet.nag.co.uk/xq2xml//xsltest-20061026.zip">XQ2XML: XML syntaxes for XQuery</ulink>. A test suite by David Carlisle that provides an XSLT 2.0 syntax for some of the <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/XML/Query/test-suite/">XQuery test suite</ulink> tests.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Distributed Search</title>

	<para>Implement a federated search service over distributed eXist databases. There are various reasons why users may
	have more than one database instance deployed, for example, to distribute load or to keep sensitive data in its own
	data store. Another important area of application would be in the context of grid computing.</para>

	<para>Unfortunately, there's no simple way to combine results from distributed data stores in a single XQuery. eXist's
	query engine can only operate on local resources. It can retrieve data from external locations, but only to store them into a
	local, temporary resource, which is then used for querying. A distributed search facility would allow eXist to directly forward parts of an expression to a remote database
	instance. The XQuery specification already provides the necessary framework: the collection() and doc() functions
	both accept arbitrary URIs, so collections as well as resources can be at external locations.</para>

	<para>The main challenge will be to properly merge intermediate results from different database instances and track references
	to remote node sequences throughout the query.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Process control and management service</title>

	<para>Implement a process control and management service à la the top and ps tools. There are various uses for a process control and management service, keeping track of running processes in the current DB instance, showing cache and memory statistics, be able to cancel or set different processing permissions on the fly for each query process, etc.</para>

	<para>The fundamentals for this could be JMX with the current cache and memory statistics and the QueryWatchDog which at the moment only restricts queries in number of created temmporary nodes and in the total time allowed for processing it, while not allowing any interactive management.</para>
	<para><emphasis>Resources:</emphasis></para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	  <para><ulink url="http://jcp.org/aboutJava/communityprocess/final/jsr003/index3.html">JSR 003</ulink></para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><ulink url="http://java.sun.com/javase/technologies/core/mntr-mgmt/javamanagement/">JMX resources</ulink></para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </section>

        <section>
          <title>Add index-support for order-by, distinct-values and aggregate functions</title>

            <para>Sorting a set of nodes is a frequent operation in many XQuery applications. The "order by" clause in XQuery is
            very powerful and allows the definition of an arbitrary number of ordering specificiations to be applied on the tuple stream
            returned by a FLWOR expression.</para>

            <para>However, ordering is quite expensive: for each tuple in the return sequence we have to evaluate all ordering expressions once
                and atomize the result, i.e. transform it into an atomic sequence. Atomization requires access to the actual node stored
                in the db, thus generating a huge amount of IO. As a result, "order by" expressions should always be applied with care. Query execution times will increase linearily with
                the size of the return sequence.</para>

            <para>To improve this, eXist should at least provide indexed access to the atomized values needed for the ordering.
                Unfortunately, the existing index structures can not be directly used: the range index maps atomized node values to
                a sequence of node ids, while order by would need to order node ids by their node value. So either the existing range
                index has to be extended to support value lookups by node id or a new index structure has to be implemented.</para>

            <para>Other XQuery operations could benefit from such an index as well: this includes the aggregate functions min, max
            and sum, as well as distinct-values.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Mentors</title>
        
        <para>The following people are available as mentors. Once your project has been accepted,
        you will be assigned one or two mentors to support you.</para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Adam Retter (GSoC Administrator)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Pierrick Brihaye</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Leif-Jöran Olsson</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Dannes Wessels</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Wolfgang Meier</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
	            <para>Kurt Cagle</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
     </section>
  </chapter>
</book>