<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="changes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!-- Author: Wolfgang Meier "meier@ifs.tu-darmstadt.de" -->
<changes title="History of Changes">
	<release version="0.9.2">
		<topic category="New Features">
			<action name="XUpdate Support">
				eXist now has full support for XUpdate. The XUpdate 
				specification allows to update fragments of a 
				document or an entire collection.
			</action>
			<action name="Additions to XPath">
				The XPath engine has been partially rewritten. It now supports XPath axis specifiers like
				ancestor-or-self, following-sibling etc.. The processing of predicate expressions has been
				reworked to be more conformant to the specification. Some things are still 
				missing from the full XPath spec, but they will be implemented for the 1.0 release.
			</action>
		</topic>
		<topic category="General Improvements">
			<action name="Unicode support">
				Much effort has been invested to ensure that East Asian 
				character codesets are correctly processed by the database
				as well as the query engine. While the database core has 
				been UTF-8 clean before, deficiencies have been found in
				several supporting libraries, including the XML-RPC library 
				and GNU Readline. The included XML-RPC library has been 
				patched to fix a transport encoding bug. All components have 
				been extensively tested to work with other character encodings 
				than ISO-8859-1. The database is now truely usable for 
				applications using non-european languages.
			</action>	
			<action name="SOAP interface">
				eXist's SOAP services have been enhanced to support authentication and user sessions. The
				provided SOAP methods have been reworked.
			</action>
			<action name="Database synchronization">
				Various bug fixes to address synchronization issues have been
				applied. A new sync thread periodically flushes unwritten
				database pages to disk. The shutdown procedure has been
				modified to avoid database corruption errors caused by
				dirty shutdowns.
			</action>
			<action name="Enhanced Client">
				The included Java client now has an optional, graphical 
				user interface, offering dialogs for user management,
				file uploads, restore and backup.
			</action>
            <action name="Storing large files through XMLRPC">
                Instead of sending files as one large chunk to a remote
                server, the XMLDB implementation now splits big files into
                smaller pieces and uploads them separately to the server. This
                way, out-of-memory errors on the server are avoided.
            </action>
		</topic>
        <topic category="Misc Bug fixes">
            <action name="Large text nodes">
                The database had problems to store text nodes whose content was
                larger then the database page size (4K). Such nodes are now stored
                as overflow nodes.
            </action>
            <action name="XPath bugs">
                Numerous bugs have been fixed in the XPath engine. In particular, 
                the handling of wildcard expressions like *, node(), text() has been
                improved. The processing of predicate expressions has been modified
                to support reverse axis specifiers inside the predicate.
            </action>
        </topic>
	</release>
	<release version="0.9.1">
		<topic category="New Features">
			<action name="Highlighting of Search Terms in Query Results">
				When displaying	query results, the query engine can now be
				configured to mark the exact matching search terms in the text. The
				highlighting is exact, i.e. only those sections, which have actually
				triggered a final match will be highlighted. In the case of text
				nodes, the matching term is surrounded by a &lt;exist:match&gt;
				element. For attribute values, two pipe symbols (||) are used
				as a mark.
			</action>
			<action name="Access to Index Information">
				Element and term occurrences for a collection can now be directly
				retrieved from the index. For this, a new extension service 
				(IndexQueryService) is provided by the XMLDB driver. The service can
				be used, for example, to provide users a list of searchable index
				terms.
			</action>
			<action name="Backup/Restore">
				There's a new client to backup and restore database contents. The backup
				mechanism dumps database contents to a hierarchy of directories, reflecting
				the collection structure. Information on owners and permissions is also
				correctly preserved. Backup/restore is based on the XMLDB and will also
				work over the network.
			</action>
			<action name="Database Startup">
				Since batch and shell scripts proved to be a constant source of trouble,
				the database and the clients can now be started through a singe jar-file,
				which tries to determine correct settings for the classpath, exist.home
				and other parameters. The jar-file is an adopted version of the file shipped
				with Jetty.
			</action>
		</topic>
		<topic category="Speed Improvements">
			<action name="Indexing Data Volumes &gt; 200MB">
				When indexing data volumes &gt; 200MB, the database frequently produced 
				various exceptions, resulting in corrupted data files (see section "Bug 
				Fixes" below). In particular, using the RPC based XMLDB driver to index
				large volumes was not recommended. To fix this, the database core has
				again been substantially changed: in particular, overall memory consumption
				has been heavily reduced, the paging and btree code has been cleaned up
				to avoid a number of redundant object allocations (mostly byte arrays),
				the indexer creates less string and char arrays, and the Java collections 
				library (trove) has been replaced by a faster implementation (fastUtil),
				which is more predictable concerning memory consumption.
			</action>
			<action name="Querying a Large Number of Files">
				Querying ten-thousands of files in the database proved to be extremely slow.
				Most of the time is spent for loading collection metadata, including document
				names, document identifiers, or user permissions. The storage space required
				for collection metadata has thus been heavily reduced: in particular, parts 
				of the metadata have been moved from collections.dbx to dom.dbx. This data
				is only rarley needed during query execution. Also, the security manager now
				assignes numeric user and group ids, which consume less storage space when 
				stored with the document object. As a result, loading collection metadata 
				on query startup is much faster now. Additionally, there's a new cache for
				collection metadata.
			</action>
			<action name="XMLRPC Communication">
				The RPC based XMLDB driver has been fixed to avoid several unnecessary 
				requests to the database. Also, the Apache XMLRPC library used to reserve
				large amounts of memory during the transport of large files, which slowed down
				the subsequent processing of smaller files. The included XMLRPC library has 
				been patched to fix this.
			</action>
		</topic>
		<topic category="Bug Fixes">
			<action name="EOFExceptions">
				Version 0.9 reproducably triggered EOFExceptions, caused by an overflow
				in the internal list of free pages, which is maintained for each data 
				file. Also, deleted pages were not correctly marked as free, resulting
				in constantly growing data files.
			</action>
			<action name="OutOfMemory Errors">
				When indexing more than some 100 megabytes, the database run into 
				OutOfMemory errors, mainly caused by memory leaks in the page buffering
				mechanism.
			</action>
			<action name="Data Corruption">
				Errors in the linking of data pages caused data files to get corrupted
				("tid ... not found" messages in the log-file).
			</action>
			<action name="Concurrency">
				Fixed several concurrency issues, which resulted in data corruption if
				more than one thread tried to index larger data volumes at the same time.
			</action>
			<action name="Updating Documents">
				On document updates, the old document got removed even if the new document
				was invalid and failed to parse. Fixed. A document is now only updated if
				the new document is valid.
			</action>
			<action name="Multi-Collection Queries">
				In version 0.8.1, the query engine supported a multiple collection arguments 
				to the collection() function, allowing to search through arbitrary, collections
				at the same time. This feature got lost in 0.9 and has now been reintroduced.
			</action>
			<action name="XMLResource.setContentAsDOM">
				The XMLResource.setContentAsDOM() method now works correctly. The indexer
				will directly access the DOM tree.
			</action>
			<action name="XMLDBException">
				The XMLDB driver has been changed to include the causing exception into every
				XMLDBException it throws. This makes it possible to explore the cause of an
				exception.
			</action>
			<action name="Resolving External Entities">
				So far, catalog files did not work with relative file names in
				system ids, because the SAX parser reports absolute system ids.
				The indexer now intercepts calls to the resolver to replace
				absolute file names with relative ones before forwarding them
				to the entity resolver.
			</action>
			<action name="Indexing Scheme">
				Fixed a bug in the indexer: in some rare cases, an empty text
				node occurring between elements could lead to a wrong
				assignment of identifiers.
			</action>
			<action name="Selective Indexing">
				The selective inclusion/exclusion of specified document-parts
				from the fulltext-indexing did not work properly. Fixed.
			</action>
		</topic>
	</release>
    <release version="0.9">
        <topic category="New Features">
            <action name="User Authentication and Access Control">
                Beginning with version 0.9, the database engine supports basic
                user authentication and access control. Access control loosely
                resembles Unix conventions, so Unix users should be familiar
                with this. Access control is disabled unless a password is set for the
                superuser.
            </action>
            <action name="XInclude">
                eXist now implements basic support for XInclude on the server. XInclude
                elements are expanded during the serialization of the document, i.e. whenever
                a document is retrieved from the database. We don't support the whole XInclude
                standard. The database currently recognizes simple document inclusions, 
                shorthand pointers and the xpointer() scheme. However, the XPointer extensions 
                to XPath are not implemented yet.
            </action>
        </topic>
		<topic category="General Improvements">
			<action name="Indexing Speed and Scalability"> The native storage backend
				has again seen a substantial redesign: It is now possible to store more
				than just a few megabytes or files into a single collection. The indexing
				process scales nearly linear as long as page buffers are sufficiently large.
				Internally, the management of overflow pages has changed: Since eXist manages
				all indexes by collection, index entries can get very large and have to be split
				over a number of overflow pages. When adding new data to a large index 
				value, the data is now simply appended to the existing chain of overflow pages. 
				Thus only the first and the last page in the chain have to remain in memory. 
				This results in a considerable performance gain, much lower memory consumption 
				and increased scalability.
			</action>
			<action name="Index Size"> Indexes for elements, attributes and text tokens
				are now based on a combination of variable byte and delta coding to store 
				the index data. The index data basically consists of a list of int and long
				values, so using variable byte coding yields good compression rates. Additionally,
				the persistent DOM's internal B+-tree is much smaller now: The B+-tree maps
				unique node identifiers to the node's storage address in the data section. So far,
				all nodes have been added to the B+-tree. However, most XPath expressions use
				short-cuts to access nodes directly, so the B+-tree is only required for some
				less time-critical operations (like the serialization of query results). I thus
				decided to keep only top-level elements in the DOM index. Attributes and text
				nodes are always excluded. These nodes are retrieved by looking up the nearest
				available ancestor. As a result, the DOM file is much smaller now. The accumulated
				size of all index files may in some cases be even less than the original raw data
				source size. For highly structured data, the expansion factor will be around
				1.5 to 2.</action>
			<action name="Page Buffering">The LRU page buffers 
				used so far have been replaced by a clock implementation, which yields
				better page prediction rates. A priority is assigned to each page to
				keep often used pages in the buffer, e.g. inner B+-tree nodes.</action>
			<action name="Locking">
				Finally, Java synchronization has been replaced by our own locking mechanism.
				This allows locks to time out: If a thread has acquired a read 
				lock and blocks for more than a given period of time, the lock manager will
				remove the lock and pass it to another waiting thread.
			</action>
			<action name="Documentation">
			    Lots of new documentation: There's a new performance howto, a document explaining
			    the different deployment options and a security howto.
			</action>
		</topic>
        <topic category="API Changes">
			<action name="XMLResource.setContent"> If a File object is passed
				to XMLResource.setContent(Object) when running in embedded mode, the
				file is directly passed on to the indexer. Otherwise the
				object is converted to String. Being able to pass a file is an 
				important feature when parsing large documents since the file's 
				content is not loaded into memory. The file object is directly 
				passed on to the indexer.</action>
			<action name="XMLResource.setContentAsSAX"> Fixed methods setContentAsSAX
				and getContentAsSAX in the XMLResource class. </action>
			<action name="DatabaseInstanceManager"> Added a new service to the
				XML:DB API called DatabaseInstanceManager. This service contains
				a single method shutdown() used to shut down the database instance
				currently connected to the driver. You have to be a member of group
				"dba" to use this method or an exception will be thrown.</action>
            <action name="Configure Multiple Backends"> It is now possible to
                use multiple database instances from the XML:DB API. Each
                instance may have its own configuration file and XML:DB driver. </action>
            <action name="Query results"> eXist usually creates a container
                element around attribute and text nodes in the query result set
                returned through the XML:DB API. For example, a text node is
                returned (by XMLResource.getContent()) as
                &lt;exist:text>content&lt;/exist:text>. The container element is
                required for additional information like source-document or
                internal node-id. However, this makes it hard to use the query
                result directly in the code (one always has to remove the
                container element). Thus, class XPathQueryService does now
                accept a property &quot;create-container-elements&quot;. When
                set to false, query results obtained through the service will
                not be wrapped into a container element. Instead, for attribute
				as well as text-nodes, the node's string value is returned. </action>
        </topic>
        <topic category="Indexer">
            <action name="Indexer Configuration"> Added an &lt;exclude> element
                to the index section of the config file to make it possible to
                exclude portions of the source XML file from fulltext indexing. </action>
            <action name="Indexing Attributes"> So far, fulltext searches did
                not work correctly on attribute values. This has been fixed.
                Attribute values are added to the fulltext index if the
                &quot;attributes&quot; option has been set to &quot;true&quot;
                in the &lt;index> section of the configuration file. Default is
				&quot;true&quot;. </action>
			<action name="XMLRPC Interface"> The XMLRPC Server now reuses created
				Parser objects. It does no longer need to set up a new parser
				for every file. This saves a lot of time and results in a considerable
				increase in indexing performance when parsing large collections.
			</action>
        </topic>
        <topic category="XPath Engine">
            <action name="Querying for the Root Node"> The descendant-or-self
                axis did not work when querying for the root node. For example,
                /PLAY did work while //PLAY did not. Fixed. </action>
            <action name="Node Set Processing"> Fixed a number of problems
                related to the processing of intermediate node sets during XPath
                evaluation. The XPath engine produced wrong results in some rare
                cases, for example, entire documents were missing in the result
                set, though there should have been hits. </action>
            <action name="Simple Wildcards"> The &amp;= and |= operators and the
                near()-function now support simple, shell-like wildcards
                (*,?,[...]) in specified keywords. This is easier than using the
                full-blown regular expression syntax, which is still provided
                through the match(), match-all() and match-any() functions. The
                simple wildcards are translated to full regular expressions by
                the underlying regexp library (jakarta ORO). </action>
            <action name="id() added"> Added the missing id()-function to the
                XPath parser. The function is index-based. </action>
			<action name="Querying Attributes"> Finally fixed the XPath parser
				to handle queries for any attribute (e.g. //div[@*='intro']) 
				correctly.
			</action>
			<action name="Any element queries"> Queries like //*[dc:title &amp;= 'computer']
				should work now.
			</action>
        </topic>
        <topic category="Bug-fixes">
            <action name="XMLResource.getId()"> XMLResource.getId() now returns
                the identifier of the current node, not that of the document it
                is contained in. </action>
            <action name="Read-only mode"> eXist again runs from a read-only
                filesystem. This had been broken in 0.8. The server tried to
				save some files, though no changes have been made to them.
				The database will switch to read-only mode if any of the database
				files is not writable. A PermissionDeniedException will be thrown
				internally on write requests.</action>
			<action name="Document Update"> When replacing a document through the 
				XML:DB API, the document seemed to have no content on the client 
				side until the client got restarted. Fixed. </action>
            <action name="XML-RPC"> Method getDocumentListing() used to return
                all documents in a collection (including sub-collections).
                Fixed. </action>
            <action name="Relational backend"> When using the relational
                backend, documents were parsed and indexed but not correctly
                stored. Fixed. </action>
            <action name="Interactive command-line client"> Client throws an
                exception if one tries to cd into a non-existing collection.
                Fixed. </action>
        </topic>
    </release>
    <release version="0.8">
        <topic category="Bug fixes">
            <action name="Memory usage"> A severe bug in the page buffering code
                of the native XML data store led to uncontrolled memory
                consumption when indexing larger documents. Freed pages have not
                been correctly garbage collected. After fixing the bug, memory
                consumption is much lower: for example, indexing a 12MB file
                with only 32MB of main memory for the JVM should work. A new
                option in the configuration file controls the amount of free
                memory which should be available in the JVM. If free memory
                drops below the specified minimum, eXist will try to flush all
                caches to disk. </action>
            <action name="XMLRPC"> Several bugs related to the XMLRPC interface
                have been fixed. The Perl examples should work now. </action>
            <action name="Namespace handling"> Version 0.7.1 stored all
                namespace declarations with the document object. This is not
                what one would expect. In 0.8, namespace declarations are stored
                for each element node. </action>
        </topic>
        <topic category="Updates">
            <action name="Cocoon"> Updated the included Cocoon to version 2.0.3. </action>
            <action name="Documentation"> Updated documentation to reflect
                version 0.8 </action>
        </topic>
        <topic category="General improvements">
            <action name="SOAP"> Added methods to store or remove documents /
                collections to the SOAP interface. </action>
        </topic>
    </release>
    <release version="0.8beta">
        <topic category="New features">
            <action name="Deployment"> eXist may now run either as a stand-alone
                server process, embedded into an application or in connection
                with a servlet-engine. If it runs in a servlet-context, all
                database files will reside in the web-application's /WEB-INF
                directory. </action>
            <action name="XML:DB API"> There are now two implementations of the
                XML:DB API available: The first talks to a remote database
                engine using XML-RPC calls. The second has direct access to a
                local database instance. This allows to embed eXist into a
                stand-alone application without running an additional
                server-process. The DatabaseManager-class will choose the
                correct implementation based on the XML:DB collection-URI you
                pass to it.</action>
            <action name="Integration with Cocoon"> Resources stored in Cocoon
                may be directly referenced in Cocoon's site map using the
                xmldb:// pseudo-protocol. If eXist is configured to run in the
                same web-application context, Cocoon has direct access to the
                database engine using the local XML:DB API driver. A new XSP
                logic sheet (xmldb.xsl) based on the XML:DB API is available. </action>
            <action name="SOAP interface"> A SOAP based web-service interface
                has been added to browse and query the database. This is still
                experimental. </action>
            <action name="WebDAV support"> Added the Xincon WebDAV
                implementation to the distribution to support access by WebDAV
                enabled file managers (Windows Explorer, cadaver ...) and
                applications (XMLSpy). WebDAV allows you to browse, add, remove
                or rename files and collections stored in eXist using your
                favourite file manager (if it supports the protocol). The Xincon
                module is still alpha so don't expect everything to work. Since
                the module had been written for Xindice, I had to make some
                small changes to the code.</action>
        </topic>
        <topic category="General improvements">
            <action name="Indexing speed"> The B+-Tree implementation and the
                page buffering mechanisms have been optimized to improve
                indexing performance. On my machine indexing a file will be up
                to two times faster than before. However, there's still more
                optimization potential for future releases.</action>
            <action name="String tokenizer"> The string tokenizer used to break
                up text into index terms has been replaced. The old tokenizer
                simply split text at every non-letter character. For example, a
                floating point number 7.10 would be split into 7 and 10. The new
                tokenizer class handles such cases correctly. Dates, floating
                point, various types of serial numbers (e.g. Q/14A, 35-16-7),
                acronyms and the like are now indexed as a single term making it
                easier to find. </action>
            <action name="New functions for regular expressions"> Due to the
                changed tokenization, it is no longer possible for the query
                engine to detect if keyword arguments to &amp;= and |= are
                regular expressions or not. To solve this, two new functions
                have been added: match-any(path, 'regexp keyword', 'regexp
                keyword' ...) and match-all(path, 'regexp keyword', 'regexp
                keyword' ...). </action>
            <action name="Compatibility with Apache's Xindice"> The XML:DB API
                implementation has been changed to be compatible with Xindice's
                implementation. Applications written for Xindice should now work
                with eXist. Most important, the database root collection is now
                called '/db'. </action>
        </topic>
        <topic name="Other changes">
            <action name="Server shutdown"> The server now tries to flush all
                unsaved buffers to disk if the Java VM gets killed or is shut
                down. In previous versions, killing the server led to corrupted
                data files. </action>
        </topic>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7.1">
        <topic category="New features">
            <action name="Regular expression support">Added regular expression
                support for search patterns. New function: match().</action>
            <action name="Near queries">Added a near()-function to search for
                phrases of text. Near uses the fulltext-index. Contrary to the
                other fulltext-operators near requires search terms to occur in
                the right sequence and near to each other. The functions
                measures the distance between two search terms by counting the
                words in between them. A maximum distance of 1 is assumed by default.</action>
            <action name="Clients">A new interactive command line client has
                been included. The client is completely based on the XML:DB API.</action>
        </topic>
        <topic category="Bug fixes">
            <action name="Namespaces">Some namespace-related bugs (null-prefixes
                in eXist's output) have been fixed.</action>
            <action name="Native backend">Due to bad page headers, database
                files got damaged sometimes during updates/removal.</action>
            <action name="XPath">XPath expressions including the document's root
                element did not work correctly, e.g. document(*)/PLAY did not
                yield any results.</action>
        </topic>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7">
        <topic category="General improvements">
            <action name="Space usage">Reallocation of free space in data pages
                has been improved. In previous versions, clean ups slowed the
                server down. Pages with free space are now kept in an ordered
                list and reused to avoid underfull pages. This reduces the
                overall size of data files. Overflow pages (used if an index
                entry exceeds the size of a single page) are compressed with
                gzip. An XML file in eXist will now occupy approx. twice the
                disk space of the original source file for DOM nodes and indexes.</action>
        </topic>
        <topic category="New features">
            <action name="XSL support">eXist's XML serializer now applies XSL
                stylesheets to a document. The HTTP server recognizes the
                xml-stylesheet processing instruction inside a document.
                Alternatively, a _xsl parameter will be evaluated in
                GET-requests. Stylesheets are read from eXist if the href is not
                an URL. Documents referenced in xsl-include or xsl-import are
                loaded from eXist as well.</action>
            <action name="XSP logicsheet">An XSP taglib (logicsheet) has been
                added to make writing XSP pages easier. The logicsheet
                communicates with the server using XML-RPC. See process.xsp in jakarta-tomcat-4.0.1/webapps/exist.</action>
            <action name="XML-RPC API">The XML-RPC interface now saves query
                result sets on the server until a timeout is reached. This makes
                it possible to process a query, display a first part of the
                results to the user and later retrieve the rest without
                executing the query again.</action>
            <action name="Collections">Added method to remove complete
                collections. This is much faster than removing every single document</action>
            <action name="Read-only file systems">It is now possible to run
                eXist on a read-only file system, e.g. from a cdrom. All methods
                which imply a modification of the current database will throw an IOException.</action>
            <action name="Case-sensitivity">A new switch has been added to the
                configuration file which allows to switch of case-sensitivity
                for string comparisons. This applies to the xpath equality,
                greate than, less than operators etc. and to the contains(),
                starts-with() etc. functions.</action>
        </topic>
        <topic category="Bug fixes/Compatibility">
            <action name="JDK1.4">eXist will now run with JDK 1.4. JDK 1.4beta
                contains Crimson, which complained about unknown SAX features.
                This has been fixed and Crimson is now accepted as SAX parser.</action>
            <action name="Serializer">A number of bugs in the serializer code
                produced invalid XML.</action>
            <action name="Relational backend">A bug has been fixed in the
                relational backend: In some cases, old document versions have
                been displayed to the user after a document has been updated.
                The server had to be restarted to view the updated document.</action>
        </topic>
        <topic category="Other changes">
            <action name="Collection()-function">The collection()-function now
                accepts an optional boolean argument, indicating whether
                documents found in sub-collections of the named collection
                should be included into the document-set. For example,
                collection('foo', false) will run the xpath-query against all
                documents in collection 'foo' but not against documents in
                sub-collection foo/baz.</action>
            <action name="Package names">eXist source code has been moved to
                org.exist to follow Java coding conventions. Files have been
                grouped into sub-packages. This makes it easier to browse
                through the code.</action>
            <action name="Tomcat, Cocoon">The included version of tomcat has
                been updated to 4.0.1 (Catalina). Cocoon has been updated to 2.0
                final. The helma.xmlrpc library has been replaced by it's
                successor, org.apache.xmlrpc.</action>
        </topic>
    </release>
    <release version="0.7beta2">
        <topic category="General improvements">
            <action name="Concurrency">The native Java backend is now safe for
                concurrent write access by multiple threads.</action>
            <action name="Indexing performance">The performance breakdown which
                occured with previous versions of the native storage backend
                when indexing many small files has been fixed. The indexing
                process scales much better now with small files and queries
                perform very well. To achieve this, the indexing structure had
                to be changed. Please note that the indexes are now organized on
                a collection basis. If there are too many files in one
                collection, it is recommended to split them up into subcollections.</action>
            <action name="Retrieval performance">Because documents are now
                stored inside a Collection-object, loading of document
                descriptions at the start of every query is about 10 times
                faster. On my machine, loading 5000 document descriptions took
                about 5-7 sec. with version 0.6, resulting in a considerable
                delay before query start. This is now reduced to 500ms..</action>
            <action name="Attributes">Attribute values are now included in the
                fulltext index. An attribute value may be queried with &amp;=
                and |= operators.</action>
            <action name="Space usage">The number of bytes used to store a node
                in the main dom file has been heavily reduced.</action>
        </topic>
        <topic category="Other Changes">
            <action name="Dropped index">The index used for string comparisons
                (=,&lt;,>) has been removed. Building this index is expensive.
                You may use the &amp;= and |= operators instead.
                =,&lt;,>,contains() etc. do a full table scan. Because of the
                reduced dom storage size, full table scans are much faster now.</action>
        </topic>
        <topic category="New Features">
            <action name="Entity Resolver">Norman Walsh's resolver classes are
                used in the parser to read XML Catalog files and resolve entities.</action>
        </topic>
        <topic category="Bug fixes/Compatibility">
            <action name="Default namespaces">Default namespaces (xmlns=) do no
                longer produce NullPointerExceptions.</action>
            <action name="Prefixes">xml-prefixes are handled correctly (e.g.
                xml:lang=&quot;...&quot;). </action>
        </topic>
    </release>
</changes>
