<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                      "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
    <bookinfo>
        <graphic fileref="logo.jpg"/>
        <productname>Open Source Native XML Database</productname>
        <title>eXist-db Developer Manifesto</title>
        <date>March 2010</date>
        <author>
            <firstname>Adam</firstname>
            <surname>Retter</surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address format="linespecific">
                    <email>adam at exist-db.org</email>
                </address>
            </affiliation></author>
    </bookinfo>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="sidebar.xml"/>
    <chapter id="ch01">
        <title>eXist-db Developer Manifesto</title>
        <para>This document lays out guidelines for developers that are either committing directly
            to the eXist-db code base via. the projects subversion repository or developing
            externally for later incorporation into eXist-db.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Communication</title>
            <para>Communication between developers and within Open Source projects can be a hard
                thing to achieve effectively, but to ensure the success of the project and
                contributions, we must all strive to improve on communicating our intentions.</para>
            <para>Public and open discussion of all new features and changes to existing features
                MUST always be undertaken. eXist-db is a community project and the community must be
                invited to provide input and feedback on development. Development discussion should
                take place through the <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=17691"
                    >eXist-db Development mailing list</ulink>.</para>
            <para>If conflicts of interest occur during discussion, they must be resolved before any
                code changes are made. Conflicts may be resolved by one of the senior core
                developers, who have been contributing to eXist for a long time and have a good
                overview of the project. Right now this includes: Wolfgang Meier, Leif-Jöran Olsson,
                Adam Retter and Dannes Wessels.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Maintainability</title>
            <para>All code accepted to the project must be maintainable otherwise there is the
                possibility that it will grow stale and without maintainers will be removed from the
                code base.</para>
            <para>To ensure a happy future for the code base each contributor has a responsibility
                to ensure:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>New code and bug-fixes <emphasis>must</emphasis> be accompanied by
                        JUnit/XQuery/XSpec test cases. This helps us understand intention and avoid
                        regressions.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Code should be appropriately commented (including javadoc/xqdoc) so that
                        intention is understood. Industry standard code formatting rules should be
                        followed. This helps us read and understand contributions.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Code must be appropriately with the developers name and current email
                        address. This helps us contact contributors/maintainers should issues
                        arrive.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Consider the maintainability of new features, will you maintain and
                        support them over years? If not, who will and how do you communicate what is
                        required?</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Developing</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Follow Industry Standard coding conventions.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>eXist-db is now developed atop Sun Java 6, so make use of Java 6 features
                        for cleaner, safer and more efficient code.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>New Features <emphasis>must</emphasis> be generic and applicable to an
                        audience of more than one or two. Consider whether the eXist-db community
                        would see this as a valuable feature; You should have already discussed this
                        via the eXist-db Development mailing list! If a feature is just for you
                        and/or your customer, it may have no place in the eXist-db main code
                        base.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Major new features or risky changes must be developed in their own branch.
                        Once they have been tested (should include some user testing) they may then
                        be integrated back into the main code base.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Follow a RISC like approach to developing new functions. It is better to
                        have a single function that is flexible than multiple function signatures
                        for the same function. Likewise, do not replace two functions by offering
                        one new super function. Functions should act like simple building blocks
                        that can be combined together.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The use of Static Analysis tools is highly recommended, these bring value
                        by reducing risk, and are even valuable to the most highly skilled
                        developers. Such tools include <ulink
                            url="http://checkstyle.sourceforge.net">Checkstyle</ulink> and <ulink
                            url="http://findbugs.sourceforge.net">FindBugs</ulink>.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Before Committing</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>TEST, TEST and TEST again!</emphasis></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Execute the JUnit test suite to ensure that there are no regressions, if
                        there are regressions then do not commit!</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Execute the XQTS test suite to ensure that there are no regressions, if
                        there are regressions then do not commit!</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If you are working in an area of performance, there is also a Benchmark
                        test suite that you should run to ensure performance.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>When effecting major changes, make sure all the demo applications which
                        ship with eXist-db are still working as expected. Testing of the main user
                        interfaces including Java WebStart client and WebDAV helps to avoid
                        surprises at release time.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Documentation, whilst often overlooked this is critical to getting users
                        to accept and test any new feature. If you add features without
                        documentation they are worthless to the community.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Atomicity! Please consider how you group your commits together. A feature
                        should be contributed as an atomic commit, this enables co-developers to
                        easily follow and test the feature. During development if you need to clean
                        existing code up, please commit this at the time labelled as 'cleaning up',
                        this makes your final commit much more concise.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Very large commits. If possible, without breaking existing functionality,
                        it can be useful to break very large commits up into a few smaller atomic
                        commits spanning a couple of days. This allows other users to test and help
                        identify any parts of your code which might introduce issues.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Commit tagging, helps us to generate lists of what has changed been
                        releases. Please prefix your commit messages with an appropriate tag:</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>[bugfix]</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>[lib-change]</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>[feature]</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>[ignore]</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>[format-change]</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>[documentation]</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>[documentation-fix]</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>[performance]</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Finally</title>
            <para>Open Source projects are not a democracy, although they are not far from that.
                Breaking, unknown and untested commits cause a lot of pain and lost hours to your
                fellow developers.</para>
            <para>Whilst we of course wish to encourage and nurture contributions to the project,
                these have to happen in a manner that everyone involved in the project can cope
                with. However, as an absolute last measure, if developers frequently fail to adhere
                to the Manifesto then Commit access to the eXist-db repository could be revoked by
                the core developers.</para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
