<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<!-- $Id: scheduler.xml 9661 2009-08-05 19:48:39Z ixitar $ -->
<book>
    <bookinfo subject=""><graphic fileref="logo.jpg"/>
        <productname>Open Source Native XML Database</productname>
        <title>Developer's Guide</title>
        <subject>Log4J Logging Guide</subject>
        <date>September 2009</date>
        <author>
            <firstname>Loren</firstname>
            <surname>Cahlander</surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address format="linespecific">
                    <email>loren at syntactica.com</email>
                </address>
            </affiliation></author></bookinfo>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="sidebar.xml"/>
    <chapter>
        <title>Log4J Logging Guide</title>
        <section>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <para>Logging may seem like a rather unimportant part of our application. After all, it
                consumes resources – taking programmer time, increasing class file size (both on
                disk and in memory), and consuming CPU cycles to execute – all while doing nothing
                to provide end-user capability, e.g. configuration and document management. In
                reality, however, logging is an important part of any substantial body of software
                and is absolutely critical in enterprise software. </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>R&amp;D often needs some debug or trace output mode to help give greater
                    insights into how mechanisms are operating in various situations. </listitem>
                <listitem>Occurrences of problems or potential problems need to be recorded for
                    examination by site administrators. </listitem>
                <listitem>Given that R&amp;D cannot watch the software from a debugger constantly
                    while it is running in a customer environment, we need a means of capturing what
                    is going on at various levels in the software to facilitate troubleshooting.
                    Lack of appropriate log data can make attempts to identify and address customer
                    problems ineffective or even completely infeasible. </listitem>
                <listitem>Customers want to be able to record and monitor trends in the operation of
                    their software. </listitem>
                <listitem>Appropriate transaction logs are an important tool in performance tuning.
                    Also, customers often want some general idea as to what the software is up to. </listitem>
                <listitem>Customers need to record various data for security reasons, e.g. to
                    produce an access log of who accessed the system. </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>What’s been lacking in our logging?</title>
            <para>Customers have been complaining about our logging for quite some time – and there
                are some good reasons for this.</para>
            <para>As should be clear by now, there are many different motivations and audiences for
                logging. Some log data is interesting primarily for analysis of access and/or
                performance. Other data is critical for examination of system health. Still other
                data is just informative – and some of this is really only meaningful to developers.
                To date, XXXXXXXXX has generally made it very hard to filter out the data of
                interest. XXXXXXXXX also has not consistently and clearly distinguished between
                important error messages, informational messages of possible customer interest, and
                debugging messages.</para>
            <para>A big issue with the use of XXXXXXXXX logs in troubleshooting has been the fact
                that XXXXXXXXX has required a restart for changes to log configuration (e.g.
                enabling a type of logging or changing its verbosity) to take effect. Customers are
                often extremely reluctant to restart their production servers, so we often get
                customer rancor, resistance, and delays in obtaining the log data critical to
                effective troubleshooting.</para>
            <para>The overall flexibility of XXXXXXXXX logging has left much to be desired. Certain
                data always goes to separate files whereas other data cannot be separated into its
                own files. There is no reliable, cross-platform means for reducing a log file’s size
                without a restart. The format of the log entries themselves cannot be specified by
                the administrator. Overall, XXXXXXXXX’s logging does not provide the myriad of
                features, big and small, that other logging systems provide today.</para>
            <para>Finally, XXXXXXXXX’s logging is showing signs of its grass-roots growth. There are
                many disparate xx.properties which control logging done in a number of different ad
                hoc fashions. Info*Engine introduces its own logging controlled in a different
                fashion and overall behaving differently. It is hard for a site administrator to get
                a big, useful picture of XXXXXXXXX’s logging.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>What to do about it?</title>
            <para>For 8.0 some classes are using Apache’s log4j (http://logging.apache.org/log4j/).
                Log4j is the most powerful Java-based logging library available today and is used by
                most of the application servers on the market.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>What does log4j give us?</title>
            <para>Log4j is based on several core concepts:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>Each log event is issued by a hierarchically named “logger”, e.g.
                    “xx.method.server.httpgw”.</listitem>
                <listitem depth="2">These hierarchical names may or may not correspond to Java class
                    names.</listitem>
                <listitem depth="2">All log events have an associated severity level (trace, debug,
                    info, warn, error, or fatal). </listitem>
                <listitem depth="2">To issue a log event programmers just acquire a logger by name
                    and specify a log message and its severity level (and optionally a Throwable
                    where applicable). </listitem>
                <listitem depth="2">Decisions as to whether a given log event is output, how and
                    where it is output, what additional data (e.g. timestamps) are included beyond
                    the log message, etc, are generally not made by the programmer – instead they
                    are controlled by an administrator via a log4j configuration file. </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Based on these core concepts, log4j provides a powerful set of
                functionalities.</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Many “appender” choice</para>
                    <para>Each log event may be output to zero or more “appenders,” which are
                        essentially generalized output pipes. Log4j output can be sent to the
                        System.out/err, files, JDBC, JMS, syslog, the Windows event log, SMTP,
                        TCP/IP sockets, telnet, and more – all at the site administrator’s
                        discretion. File output includes various options for log rolling, e.g. daily
                        creation of new log files, segmenting when a given file size is reached, and
                        externally controlled log rotation. These appenders can be run synchronously
                        to the threads generating log events or as separate asynchronous
                        queues.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Flexible “layout” options</para>
                    <para>With each appender one can specify a “layout” for formatting the log
                        message. The administrator may choose from HTML, XML, and various plain text
                        formats – including the flexible PatternLayout which allows selection of
                        data to include (e.g. timestamps, originating thread, logger name, etc) and
                        exactly how to include it.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Hierarchical logger configuration</para>
                    <para>Administrators can easily configure log event cutoff levels and appenders
                        for entire branches of the hierarchical logger tree, i.e. for a whole set of
                        related loggers, at once. For instance, by adding a “console” appender
                        targeting System.out to the root logger, all log4j output will go to
                        System.out. One can similarly configure the overall cutoff level as “error”
                        at the root logger level so that only error and fatal messages are output
                        unless otherwise specified. One could then configure the “xx.method” logger
                        to have an “info” level cutoff and an appender to capture all output to a
                        specified file (in addition to System.out). These “xx.method” settings would
                        then affect all loggers whose names begin with “xx.method.” (e.g.
                        “xx.method.server.httpgw”), in addition to the “xx.method” logger
                        itself.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Log viewers</para>
                    <para>Various free and commercial products provide specialized viewing
                        capabilities for log4j logs. Apache provides a very useful log4j log viewer,
                        Chainsaw (http://logging.apache.org/log4j/docs/chainsaw.html).</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>See the log4j website (http://logging.apache.org/log4j/ and in particular
                http://logging.apache.org/log4j/docs/manual.html) for more information. </para>
            <para>It is worth noting that Java 1.4 and higher’s java.util.logging API and concepts
                are very similar to log4j’s, but log4j is much more powerful in a number of critical
                areas. </para>
            <para>In conjunction with our JMX MBeans for log4j, one can also: </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Dynamically examine and reconfigure the log4j configuration for the
                        duration of the process via a JMX console, </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Have all processes using a log4j configuration file periodically check its
                        modification date and automatically re-load it upon any change , and </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Force an immediate reload from a configuration file via a JMX
                        console.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Overall use of log4j provides an immense leap forward in XXXXXXXXX logging
                functionality and flexibility. Specifically, by using log4j we can address each of
                the shortcomings previously noted in our existing logging.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>How can I use log4j in new code?</title>
            <para>Using log4j from XXXXXXXXX code is quite easy.</para>
            <para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Acquire a logger. import org.apache.log4j.Logger; … private Logger
                            logger = Logger.getLogger("xx.method.server.httpgw");</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>This is a somewhat time-consuming operation and should be done
                                in constructors of relatively long-lived objects or in static
                                initializers . </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Many classes can separately acquire a logger using the same
                                    logger name. They will all end up with their own reference to
                                    the same shared logger object.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Use the logger: logger.info( "Something I really wanted to say"
                            );</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>info() is just one of Logger’s methods for issuing log4j log
                                events. It implicitly assigns the event a severity level of “info”
                                and does not specify a Throwable. Logger methods for issuing log
                                events include:</listitem>
                            <programlisting format="linespecific" language="java"><![CDATA[
public void trace(Object message); 
public void trace(Object message, Throwable t); 
public void debug(Object message); 
public void debug (Object message, Throwable t); 
public void info(Object message); 
public void info(Object message, Throwable t); 
public void warn(Object message); 
public void warn(Object message, Throwable t); 
public void error(Object message); 
public void error(Object message, Throwable t); 
public void fatal(Object message); 
public void fatal(Object message, Throwable t); ]]></programlisting>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Note that in each case the “message” is an Object, not a
                                    String. If (and only if) log4j decides to output the given log
                                    event (based on the configuration), it will render this object
                                    as a String. By default this is essentially via
                                    toString().</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </para>
            <para>It’s as simple as that. You just emit log events with appropriate log levels to
                appropriately named loggers. The log4j configuration determines which appenders (if
                any) should output/record the event and how this should be done. </para>
            <para>For more information on “Do’s and Don’t” see that section. For more information on
                how to configure log4j output see the “Configuring log4j?” section. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>How can I convert existing logging code to use log4j?</title>
            <para>Conversion of existing logging code to use log4j can be simply viewed as replacing
                System.out.println() calls, etc, with use of the log4j API. There are, however, a
                few special considerations worth noting.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Dealing with Legacy Properties</title>
                <para>In the conversion process the behavior of some existing properties will
                    generally be affected. </para>
                <para>In cases this may mean simply removing the existing properties. For instance,
                    properties specifying specific output files can generally be removed as
                    customers can now siphon log4j output to specific files at their discretion via
                    log4j’s configuration files. </para>
                <para>On the other hand, it may be useful in cases to preserve well known log
                    enabling properties to reduce confusion amongst those used to these properties.
                    In such cases it is suggested that the property be ignored unless it is set to
                    enable the given log – in which case it will ensure the given log4j logger’s log
                    level is verbose enough to cause the existing messages to be output. For
                    instance, one might have something like </para>
                <programlisting format="linespecific" language="java"><![CDATA[
   private static final boolean VERBOSE_SERVER;
   static
   {
     XXProperties properties = XXProperties.getLocalProperties();
     VERBOSE_SERVER = properties.getProperty("xx.method.verboseServer", false);
   }
   …
   if ( VERBOSE_SERVER )
     System.out.println( "some message" );
     ]]></programlisting>
                <para>in the existing code. The static portions above can be left as is and the
                    remainder changed to:</para>
                <programlisting format="linespecific" language="java"><![CDATA[
   import org.apache.log4j.Level;
   import org.apache.log4j.Logger;

   // place VERBOSE_SERVER declaration and static block from above here
   private static final Logger  serverLogger =
                                     Logger.getLogger( "xx.method.server" );
   static
   {
     if ( VERBOSE_SERVER )
       serverLogger.setLevel( Level.ALL );
   }
   …
   serverLogger.debug( "some message" );
   ]]></programlisting>
                <para>This example assumes that output from the given log4j logger should be
                    completely enabled, i.e. for all log levels, when the existing property is set.
                    One can also use logic like:</para>
                <programlisting format="linespecific" language="java"><![CDATA[
   if ( VERBOSE_SERVER )
     if ( !serverLogger.isDebugEnabled() )
       serverLogger.setLevel( Level.DEBUG );
       ]]></programlisting>
                <para>to cause the existing property to enable output from the given log4j logger up
                    through only a certain severity level, debug in this example. </para>
                <para>To be clear, this approach to preserving existing “enabling” properties only
                    keeps them working more or less as they were. The intended minimum log verbosity
                    is ensured upon initialization and then cannot be reset via the property without
                    a restart. The ability to change the log-level on the fly or make finer-grained
                    log-level adjustments is still only available through log4j configuration. </para>
                <para>When an existing property’s behavior is changed or when log4j configuration is
                    now the more powerful (and thus preferred) approach, this should be noted in the
                    property’s entry in properties.html. Be sure to include the name of new log4j
                    logger in such notes. </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Conditional Computation of Data for Logging</title>
                <para>In cases you will find existing code like:</para>
                <programlisting format="linespecific" language="java"><![CDATA[
   if ( VERBOSE_SERVER )  // static final boolean
   {
     // various computations and assignment
   }
   ]]></programlisting>
                <para>the if block may include System.out.println()’s or the results of the block
                    may be used in later System.out.println()’s. </para>
                <para>In either case, the code is intended to avoid the block of computations and
                    assignments unless their results are to be used. This intent can be satisfied by
                    use of one of log4j’s is*Enabled() methods. For example: </para>
                <programlisting format="linespecific" language="java"><![CDATA[
   if ( serverLogger.isDebugEnabled() )
   {
     // various computations and assignment that will only be used
     // if serverLogger.debug() calls
   }
                ]]></programlisting>
                <para>The log4j Logger class provides a set of methods for this purpose
                    including:</para>
                <programlisting format="linespecific" language="java"><![CDATA[
   public boolean isTraceEnabled();
   public boolean isDebugEnabled();
   public boolean isInfoEnabled();
   public Boolean isEnabledFor(Level);
                ]]></programlisting>
                <para>This technique obviously applies to new log4j usage as well but is noted at
                    this point so as to make conversion of existing logging code more
                    straightforward.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Configuring log4j</title>
            <para>In X-10 several configuration files located in the codebase directory control
                log4j’s behavior: </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>log4j.properties – default configuration file log4j will use if not
                        otherwise specified; used for all other JVMs at this time</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>The full format of these configuration files is described here and a short
                introduction of the basics is given here. Note this is the simpler, but less
                powerful, form of log4j configuration file. An XML-based configuration file format
                also exists and customers will end up supplanting one or more of the properties
                files above with an XML configuration file if they require some of the most advanced
                log4j features. </para>
            <para>These out-of-the-box configuration should generally be kept fairly simple (see
                “Do’s and Don’ts” below), so the main use case for development configuration of
                log4j is to enable a given level of log output from one or more loggers. Without
                such configuration XXXXXXXXX will output only ERROR and FATAL log events
                out-of-the-box – except where the configuration has already been extended to output
                other log events. Therefore you generally must change the configuration to see
                trace, debug, info, or warn log events in the log4j output. </para>
            <para>To turn on a given logging level for all loggers, find the log4j.rootLogger
                property in the appropriate properties file and change the value before the first
                comma (“error” by default) to the desired level. For instance, change </para>
            <programlisting format="linespecific" language="java"><![CDATA[
log4j.rootLogger=error, …
]]></programlisting>
            <para>to</para>
            <programlisting format="linespecific" language="java"><![CDATA[
log4j.rootLogger=debug, …
]]></programlisting>
            <para>Of course this will result in a cacophony of log output, so you’ll generally want
                to adjust the logging level at a more specific level. To do this you can append a
                line to the properties file of following form:</para>
            <programlisting format="linespecific" language="java"><![CDATA[
 log4j.logger.targetLoggerName =desiredLogLevel
 ]]></programlisting>
            <para>For instance, you would add</para>
            <programlisting format="linespecific" language="java"><![CDATA[
log4j.logger.xx.servlet.ServletRequestMonitor.stats=INFO
]]></programlisting>
            <para>to set the “xx.servlet.ServletRequestMonitor.stats” logger’s level to “INFO”. Note
                that doing so also causes all the default log level of all
                xx.servlet.ServletRequestMonitor.stats.* loggers to be set to “INFO”. For example,
                the level of the xx.servlet.ServletRequestMonitor.stats.summary logger would also be
                set to INFO unless the level of this logger is otherwise specified. </para>
            <para>Changes to log4j configuration files may go unnoticed for as long as a few minutes
                as the checks for modifications to these files take place on a periodic basis. To
                force an immediate reload of the log4j configuration file, change the configuration
                file modification check interval, or make temporary changes to the log4j
                configuration without changing the configuration files, one must use our JMX MBeans. </para>
            <para>To use our log4j JMX MBeans: </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Start jconsole. </para>
                    <para>jconsole is located in the Java 5 SDK’s bin directory. You can either
                        double-click on it or run it from the command line. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Select the target JVM. </para>
                    <para>jconsole will list the Java processes running on your machine under your
                        current user which have been configured to allow local JMX connections. This
                        includes servlet engine, method server, and server manager processes in
                        X-10. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Navigate to the Logging node in the MBean tree.</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Select the MBeans tab.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Expand the XXXXXXXXX folder.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>In the servlet engine expand the “WebAppContext” folder and the
                                folder named after your web app.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Select the “Logging” node (which should now be visible).</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Note that it may take a short while after initial start up for all
                                of these tree nodes to load into jconsole.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Perform desired operations and/or modifications.</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>To change the configuration file check interval, change the
                                ConfigurationCheckInterval attribute to the desired number of
                                seconds. [Note that this change will apply only for the duration of
                                the JVM process unless you select the Loader node and its “save”
                                operation.]</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>To force an immediate reload of the configuration file, press the
                                “reconfigure” button on the operations tab.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>To examine other aspects of the configuration and make temporary
                                (for the duration of the JVM process) changes to the logging
                                configuration, press the “registerLoggers” button on the operation
                                tab. Expand the “Logging” tree node and examine/operate upon its
                                children.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Do’s and Don’ts</title>
            <para>General </para>
            <para>Do carefully select appropriate logger names </para>
            <para>Logger names should be somewhat meaningful and should facilitate hierarchical
                configuration by administrators. They should also be namespaced with “xx” or
                “com.xxx” so as to avoid collision with logger names from 3rd-party libraries and
                customizations. For instance, one might (and we do) have “xx.method.server” for
                general logging related to various low-level aspects of the method server and
                “xx.method.server.timing” for logging specifically related to the method timing. One
                can certainly use Java class and package names where these make sense, but an
                understandable and useful hierarchy is the important thing. </para>
            <para>Do document your logger in /XXXXXXXXX/src_web/loggers.html if appropriate </para>
            <para>If your logger is to be sent significant information of potential customer
                interest, then the logger should be documented (by name) in
                /XXXXXXXXX/src_web/loggers.html (which ends up in XXXXXXXXX’s codebase in an
                installation) unless there are special considerations to the contrary. Special
                considerations which would cause one not to document the logger include a likelihood
                that the logger will be removed in the near future or any other scenario wherein we
                do not want to raise customers’ awareness of a given logger. </para>
            <para>Do carefully select appropriate levels for log events One of the big advantages of
                log4j is that each logging event has an associated level and thus an administrator
                can easily filter out log messages by level. This advantage is nullified, however,
                if those outputting log events do not select appropriate log levels when they do so.
                The following table delineates when to use each level. </para>
            <informaltable frame="void" border="1">
                <thead>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Level</th>
                        <th>Usage</th>
                    </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Trace</td>
                        <td>Very low-level debugging “execution is here” debugging / troubleshooting
                            types of events.</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Debug</td>
                        <td>Messages of interest to those debugging or troubleshooting of a greater
                            importance than trace messages; possibly still only meaningful to
                            developers</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Info</td>
                        <td>General informational messages; provide higher level and/or more
                            important information than debug messages; understandable by and/or of
                            interest to non-developers</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Warn</td>
                        <td>Warnings of potential problems</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Error</td>
                        <td>Error conditions</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Fatal</td>
                        <td>Fatal error conditions, i.e. where the product is going to have to shut
                            down, is likely to crash, or something equally severe</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr/>
                </tbody>
            </informaltable>
            <para>Don’t go overboard with the log4j configuration files </para>
            <para>Log4j provides a great deal of ease and flexibility in its configuration. Its log
                viewers also make it easy to merge log data from multiple log4j logs or filter out
                the data of interest from a general purpose log. Given this it makes little sense to
                provide a complex log4j configuration file out-of-the-box. The customer can change
                the configuration to have more or less specific log outputs as dictated by their
                needs and desires. </para>
            <para>Do adjust log levels in log4j configuration files where appropriate </para>
            <para>Currently the out-of-the-box global default for XXXXXXXXX is to only output
                “error” and “fatal” log messages. This is a reasonable default in that it generates
                fairly quiet logs that only alert administrators to issues. There are, however, some
                cases where a given log event is best classified as being only informational (and
                thus is output as level “info”) and yet should be output to logs as an
                out-of-the-box default behavior. Examples include periodic summaries of requests
                serviced by the server over the last time interval and periodic process health
                summaries. In such cases one should add to the out-of-the-box log4j configuration to
                enable info level debug output for the logger in question. </para>
            <para>Don’t include redundant data in log messages </para>
            <para>Administrators can easily configure log4j log output to efficiently include: </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>current time</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>thread name</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>logger name</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>log event level</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Moreover, log4j includes this information in a standard, structured fashion which
                is therefore easily interpreted by log viewers like Chainsaw. </para>
            <para>Inclusion of any of these pieces of information in the log message itself is
                therefore redundant and pointless. </para>
            <para>Do make use of AttributeListWrapper where appropriate </para>
            <para>For some particularly significant logs it is important to give the administrator
                even more control including: <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Allowing them to select which of many possible attributes should be
                            included in a given log message</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Allowing them to specify the order of these attributes</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Allowing them to specify the formatting of these attribute (e.g. comma
                            delimited, with or without attribute names, etc)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
            <para>Examples of such cases include request access and periodic statistics logging. </para>
            <para>We have a re-usable utility for just this purpose,
                xx.jmx.core.AttributeListWrapper. See its existing usages for examples of how to use
                it and the Runtime Management design note for background information. </para>
            <para>Don’t be afraid to use log4j in any tier or JVM </para>
            <para>log4 currently is not included in the client jar set. The only reason for this is
                that currently no clients use log4j. We should not waste time and energy trying to
                avoid log4j logging from the client. If/when we need log4j.jar on the client we
                should simply include it in the client jar set. Java 5’s Pack200 technology reduces
                jars to 25% their original size on average, and log4j.jar is not that big to begin
                with. </para>
            <para>Performance </para>
            <para>The operation of log4j’s Logger class’s logging methods for issuing log events can
                be roughly summed up as: </para>
            <programlisting format="linespecific" language="java"><![CDATA[
public void  log( Level level, Object message )
{
  if ( isEnabledFor( level ) )
  {
    String  string = render( messasge );
    for ( Appender appender : myAppenders )
      appender.output( string );
  }
}
]]></programlisting>
            <para>where:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>render() is simply a toString() call except when ‘message’ is an instance
                        of a Class for which a specialized render has been registered.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>trace(), debug(), info(), warn(), error(), etc, simply call log() with the
                        appropriate ‘level’.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Note that log4j documentation claims that isEnabledFor(), and the
                Logger.is*Enabled() method in general, are extremely fast (and they have some
                benchmark data to back this up). Thus log() should take very little time as well
                unless isEnabledFor() returns ‘true’. </para>
            <para>Given this, a few performance do’s and don’t become clear: </para>
            <para>Don’t reacquire a logger on each usage </para>
            <para>As already noted, the LogR.getLogger() (and underlying Logger.getLogger()) calls
                are relatively expensive. One should thus acquire these objects once per class or
                once instance of a class and re-use them in subsequent logging calls against that
                logger. </para>
            <para>Don’t assume a log’s level cannot change </para>
            <para>One of the big advantages of log4j is that administrators can easily change the
                level setting of any logger at any time. One can easily completely break this by
                following conventions common in existing XXXXXXXXX logging code, e.g.: </para>
            <programlisting format="linespecific" language="java"><![CDATA[
 static boolean  LOG_ENABLED = logger.isInfoEnabled ();
…
public void someMethod()
{
  if ( LOG_ENABLED )
    logger.info( … );
}
]]></programlisting>
            <para>There is no reason such code should ever occur. Logger’s isEnabledFor() and
                is*Enabled() routines are fast enough that we can pay the penalty to call them much
                more frequently in order to obtain the benefits of dynamically configurable logging
                levels. </para>
            <para>Don’t check whether the log level is enabled before every log call </para>
            <para>Do not write code such as: </para>
            <programlisting format="linespecific" language="java"><![CDATA[
if ( logger.isDebugEnabled() )
  logger.debug( "Some constant string" );
  ]]></programlisting>
            <para>Such code results in essentially no savings when isDebugEnabled() is true but
                logger being checked twice to determine if it is debug enabled in the case when
                isDebugEnabled() is true. Besides this it makes the code more verbose and harder to
                read. In such cases one should simple do: </para>
            <programlisting format="linespecific" language="java"><![CDATA[
logger.debug( "Some constant string" );
            ]]></programlisting>
            <para>Do avoid doing additional work for logging unless the logger is enabled </para>
            <para>If last example instead looked like: </para>
            <programlisting format="linespecific" language="java"><![CDATA[
if ( logger.isDebugEnabled() )
  logger.debug( "Object " + object.getDisplayIdentity() + 
                " is being deleted" );
                ]]></programlisting>
            <para>Then the isDebugEnabled() check should be performed. In this case two String
                concatenations and a potentially (somewhat) expensive method call can be saved when
                the logger is not debug enabled – at a cost of only an extra isDebugEnabled() call
                when the logger is debug enabled. See the “Conditional Computation of Data for
                Logging” section above for another example of this pattern. </para>
            <para>On the other hand, this technique should not be used when you are all but certain
                the given logger will be enabled. Usually this applies only to log events being
                emitted with an “error” or “fatal” level designation. In this case saving time for
                the few cases in which someone has actually disabled this level of logging is not
                worth while for the extra time required in the majority of cases. </para>
            <para>Another technique to avoid unnecessary work is to leverage the fact that Logger’s
                take objects, not Strings, as arguments. Thus one might have: </para>
            <programlisting format="linespecific" language="java"><![CDATA[
SomeClass  someObj = new SomeClass(…);
logger.info( someObj );
]]></programlisting>
            <para>Here one will pay the construction of “someObj” in all cases but will only pay for
                someObj.toString() when “logger” is enabled for info-level log events. Thus if very
                little work is done in the constructor and most is done in toString() this avoids
                doing work except when necessary – which is always a good thing.
                AttributeListWrapper (see above) is an example of this technique. </para>
            <para>Do hoist log level checks outside of very tight loops </para>
            <para>For cases where a given log level will usually not be enabled, e.g. for trace and
                debug log messages, one should avoid repeated checks within a tight loop. As an
                example: </para>
            <programlisting format="linespecific" language="java"><![CDATA[
{
  final boolean  traceEnabled = logger.isTraceEnabled();
  for ( int ii = 0; ii < n; ++ii )
  {
    // do some very quick stuff
    if ( traceEnabled )
      logger.trace( ... );
    // do a little more very quick stuff
  }
}
]]></programlisting>
            <para>Trace level logging is rarely enabled and so in this example checking for this
                case ahead of time can save us from repeatedly verifying this in a tight loop. This
                does, however, come at the cost of making it impossible to dynamically enable trace
                logging for this logger in the middle of this loop. Due to this cost this technique
                should only be used for tight loops where the duration of the execution represented
                by the loop (and thus the time during which the logging behavior may lag the
                intended setting) is small.</para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
