<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "docbookx.dtd">-->

<book xmlns:ci="http://apache.org/cocoon/include/1.0">
    
    <bookinfo>
        <graphic fileref="logo.jpg"/>
		<title>Open Source XML Database</title>
        <author> 
          <firstname>Wolfgang M.</firstname>
          <surname>Meier</surname>
          <affiliation>
            <address format="linespecific">
				<email>wolfgang@exist-db.org</email>
            </address>
          </affiliation>
        </author>
    </bookinfo>

    <ci:include src="sidebar.xml"/>
      
    <chapter>
		<title>Support eXist</title>
        
        <section>
            <title>Why support?</title>
            
			<para>eXist started as a spare time project in 2001. Only a small part of my work on eXist
				has been covered by different academic projects in which I have been involved. The rest 
				is spare time. eXist itself is not directly supported by academic funding. It is real 
				free software in the sense that it depends on the commitment of volunteers.</para>
            
			<para>The user community of eXist has been continously growing throughout the past two years.
				Maintaining and developing the software is more and more becoming a full-time job. This is
				only possible as long as my "official" projects allow me to invest enough time into eXist.
				I would be happy if I could finance at least a part of my work time and stay independent
				enough to continue the project, to pay for equipment, internet connections and travel.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>How to support?</title>

			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Contribute to the project</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>First of all, the best way to support eXist is to contribute code, bug-fixes,
							test cases, documentation and the like. If you're not a programmer, there are
							other ways to support the team: e.g. by writing tutorials or howtos,
							or simply by spreading the news about eXist.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Make a Donation</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>Donate any amount you find appropriate using
							<a href="https://www.paypal.com/affil/pal=sbhati%40web.de" target="_blank">PayPal</a>
							or <a href="http://order.kagi.com/cgi-bin/store.cgi?storeID=28U">Kagi</a>. Donations help me as maintainer and main developer of eXist to keep the 
							project alive, to fix
							bugs and implement new features.</para>
						<para>Making a donation also assumes direct, higher priority support by the 
							maintainer of the software.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Sponsor the developments you need</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>I'm willing to offer the implementation of extra features and modifications,
							if my time frame permits it. Just contact 
							<a href="mailto:wolfgang@exist-db.org">me</a> for a possible arrangement.
							The results of such work should go back into eXist.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Other ways</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>If none of the alternatives described is appropriate for you, don't hesitate to
							contact <a href="mailto:wolfgang@exist-db.org">me</a>. 
							We can surely find another arrangement.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Donate using 
						<a href="https://www.paypal.com/affil/pal=sbhati%40web.de" target="_blank">PayPal</a>
						(low fees, but requires registration)
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Donate using <a href="http://order.kagi.com/cgi-bin/store.cgi?storeID=28U">Kagi</a> (no registration)</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
    </chapter>
</book>
        
