<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Author: Wolfgang Meier "meier@ifs.tu-darmstadt.de" -->
<document xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<!-- include header -->
	<xi:include href="header.xml" />
	<xi:include href="sidebar.xml" />

	<xi:include href="http://wiki.exist-db.org/exec/rss?snip=start">
		<xi:fallback></xi:fallback>
	</xi:include>

	<body>
		<section id="overview" title="Overview">

			<p>
				eXist is an Open Source native XML database featuring
				efficient, index-based
				<a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xquery/">XQuery</a>
				processing, automatic indexing, extensions for full-text
				search,
				<a
					href="http://www.smb-tec.com/xmldb/xupdate/index.html">
					XUpdate
				</a>
				support and tight integration with existing XML
				development tools. The database implements the current
				XQuery 1.0 working draft as of November, 2003 (for the
				core syntax, some details already following later
				versions), with the exception of the XML schema related
				features.
			</p>

			<p>
				<a href="xquery.xml">XQuery support</a>
				in eXist makes it possible to write entire web
				applications with just XQuery and XSLT. XQuery files can
				be directly passed to the database, using either the
				XQueryServlet, the XQueryGenerator for Cocoon or the
				REST-style API (see
				<a href="devguide.xml">Developer's Guide</a>
				).
			</p>

			<p>
				Additional features: Java binding, fulltext-search
				functions, modules in XQuery and Java, extension modules
				for HTTP support, database manipulation and XSL
				transformations.
			</p>

			<p>
				To avoid memory-intensive document tree traversals
				during query processing, eXist uses an efficient index
				structure which is based on a numerical indexing scheme
				for identifying XML nodes in the index. The database is
				lightweight, completely written in Java and may be
				easily deployed in a number of ways, running either as a
				stand-alone server process, inside a servlet-engine or
				directly embedded into an application.
			</p>


			<p>
				For a summary of eXist's features please have a look at
				the
				<link href="facts.xml">feature sheet</link>
				.
			</p>

		</section>

		<section id="download" title="Download">
			<p>
				eXist is released to the public under the terms of the
				<link href="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/lesser.html">
					GNU LGPL
				</link>
				license.
			</p>
			<p>
				eXist may be downloaded either as a package containing
				the complete distribution or as a web application
				archive (war-file). Download the war-file if you want to
				install eXist into an existing servlet-engine or write
				your own web application. To get started, we suggest
				downloading the installer or the zip package. Both
				contain a ready-to-run webserver (Jetty).
			</p>
			<p>
				The distribution includes source code and all required
				third party libraries. The current version is 1.0beta2.
				For instructions on starting eXist, read the
				<link href="quickstart.xml">Quick Start Guide</link>
				.
			</p>

			<p>
				<emphasis>
					If you are updating from a previous release, please 
					read the <a href="updating.xml">update notes</a>.
				</emphasis>
			</p>

			<table cellpadding="5" cellspacing="5">
				<tr>
					<th align="left" colspan="2">
						Snapshots
					</th>
				</tr>
				<tr>
				    <td>
				    	<a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/exist/eXist-snapshot-20060313.jar">
				    	eXist-snapshot-20060313.jar
				    	</a>
				   	</td>
				   	<td>
						Installer based on IzPack. Includes source. Run with
						<tt>java -jar eXist-snapshot-XXXXXX.jar</tt>
						.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td colspan="2">
						Development snapshots reflect the current state of development. They are
						released on a regular basis whenever we think the CVS code is in a stable
						state and important new features or bug fixes should be made available to
						the community. The latest snapshot release can always be found on the 
						<a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=17691">
						Sourceforge file release system</a>. Concerning installation, there's no 
						difference to a stable release.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
				    <td colspan="2">
				        Please note that development snapshots are not necessarily less stable than
				        the latest "stable" release. Snapshots often contain important bug fixes 
				        which are not yet available in the stable release. There's also a risk
				        that new bugs or regressions were introduced. However, we try to keep
				        the snapshots as stable as possible. New features, bugs or problems will be
				        announced via the <link href="http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=17691">mailing list
				        </link> and the <link href="http://wiki.exist-db.org">Wiki</link>.
				    </td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<th align="left" colspan="2">Last "official" stable version</th>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<th colspan="2">
						<warning>
			                <title>Health Warning</title>
			                <p>The 1.0 beta2 release is truly ancient now. There were
			                lots of bug fixes and feature enhancements during the past months,
			                so using beta2 cannot be recommended any more. Please download
			                a newer development snapshot. Recent development snapshots can
			                be regarded as stable. A new official "stable" release is in
			                preparation, but as usual, we lack the
			                time to complete the documentation. Any help will be welcome!</p>
			            </warning>
		            </th>
	            </tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<a
							href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/exist/eXist-1.0b2-build-1107.jar">
							eXist-1.0b2-build-1107.jar
						</a>
					</td>
					<td>
						Installer based on IzPack. Highly recommended.
						Includes source. Run with
						<tt>java -jar eXist-1.0b2.jar</tt>
						.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<a
							href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/exist/eXist-1.0b2-build-1107.war">
							eXist-1.0b2-build-1107.war
						</a>
					</td>
					<td>
						Web application archive, ready to be installed
						into an existing servlet-engine like Tomcat or
						Jetty.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<th align="left" colspan="2">Other tools</th>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<a
							href="http://wiki.exist-db.org/space/jEditXQueryPlugin">
							jEdit XQuery Plugin Adapter
						</a>
					</td>
					<td>
						jEdit's XQuery plugin offers a comfortable
						interface to write and test XQueries from within
						jEdit. The plugin provides an adapter
						architecture to access different XQuery engines.
						Using the adapter for eXist, you can execute
						your XQuery directly from within jEdit. Follow
						the link to read more.
					</td>
				</tr>
			</table>
		</section>
		<section title="Community Support" id="mailing">
			<p>The primary medium for asking questions, getting help or posting bug reports
			    or fixes is the project mailing list. To subscribe/unsubscribe
			    visit the mailing lists page on sourceforge.</p>
			    
			<p>
				<link
					href="http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=17691">
					http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=17691
				</link>
			</p>

			<p>
				The <b>list archive</b> can be found on the same page. However, most people
				find <b>Gmane</b> more convenient:</p>
			
			<p>
				<link
					href="http://news.gmane.org/thread.php?group=gmane.text.xml.exist">
					http://news.gmane.org/thread.php?group=gmane.text.xml.exist
				</link>
			</p>

			<p>The project also has an <b>IRC channel</b> <link href="irc://irc.freenode.net/existdb">#existdb</link>
			at irc.freenode.net. The channel is open for general discussions on eXist and related subjects.
			</p>

		</section>
	</body>
</document>
