<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Author: Wolfgang Meier "meier@ifs.tu-darmstadt.de" -->
<document xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <!-- include header -->
    <xi:include href="header.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="sidebar.xml"/>
    <body>
        <section title="News">
            <definitionlist>
                <definition>
                    <term>
                        <b>November 21, 2003</b>
                    </term>
                    <def>
                        <img src="resources/new.gif" border="0"/>XQuery support is progressing fast: I have put 
					up a few <link href="xquery/index.xml">XQuery 
					examples</link>
				to demonstrate some of the new features available in the 
				current development version. XQuery support is still far from 
				being complete, but you can already do a lot of fascinating 
				things.</def>
                </definition>
                <definition>
                    <term>
                        <b>August 11, 2003</b>
                    </term>
                    <def>0.9.2 is out! This is the first official release with support for
						XUpdate. Also, much effort has been invested to ensure
						that East Asian character encodings are correctly processed by the database
						as well as the query engine. Further changes include: important missing 
						parts of the XPath spec have been implemented, more synchronization and
						database corruption bugs have been fixed and interfaces improved.
					</def>
                </definition>
            </definitionlist>
        </section>
        <section id="overview" title="Overview">
            
            <p>eXist is an Open Source native XML database featuring
                efficient, index-based XQuery processing, extensions for full-text
                search, XUpdate support and tight integration with existing
                XML development tools. To avoid memory-intensive document tree
                traversals during query processing, eXist uses an efficient
                index structure which is based on a numerical indexing scheme
                for identifying XML nodes in the index. The database is
                lightweight, completely written in Java and may be easily
                deployed in a number of ways, running either as a stand-alone
                server process, inside a servlet-engine or directly embedded
                into an application.</p>
            
            <p>Beginning with version 1.0, entire web-based applications can be
            written with just XQuery and XSLT. XQuery is not only used as a query
            language, but to implement the whole processing logic of the web
            application. eXist provides several extension modules for the
            required tasks.</p>
            
            <p>The XQuery engine is a complete rewrite and replaces the old
                XPath engine. It implements the current XQuery working draft as
                of November, 2003 with the exception of the XML schema related
                features. Extensions to XPath/XQuery are provided to efficiently
                support document-centric queries, which overcome the inability
                of the standard function library to produce satisfactory results
                when querying larger sections of text.</p>
                
            <p>For a summary of eXist's features please have a look at
                the <link href="facts.xml">feature sheet</link>.</p>

        </section>

        <section title="Online demos">
            <p>Several <b>online demos</b> are available. Please have a look at
                the list of <link href="examples.xml">available examples</link>.</p>
        </section>

        <section id="download" title="Download">
            <p>eXist is released to the public under the terms of the <link href="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/lesser.html">GNU
					LGPL</link> license.</p>
            <p>eXist may be downloaded either as a package containing the
                complete distribution or as a web application archive
                (war-file). Download the war-file if you want to install eXist
				into an existing servlet-engine or write your own web 
				application. To get started, we suggest downloading the 
				installer or the zip package. Both contain a ready-to-run
				webserver (Jetty).</p>
            <p>The distribution includes source code and all required third
                party libraries. The current version is 1.0beta1. For instructions on starting eXist,
                read the <link href="quickstart.xml">Quick Start Guide</link>.</p>
            <table cellpadding="5" cellspacing="5">
                <tr>
                    <th align="left">Stable version</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/exist/eXist-1.0b1-install.jar">eXist-1.0b1-install.jar</a>
                    </td>
                    <td>Installer based on IzPack. Run with <tt>java -jar eXist-1.0b1-install.jar</tt>.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/exist/eXist-1.0b1.tar.gz">eXist-1.0b1.tar.gz</a>
                    </td>
                    <td>Distribution including source code and required
                        third-party libraries. Packed with tar and gzip.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/exist/eXist-1.0b1.zip">eXist-1.0b1.zip</a>
                    </td>
                    <td>Distribution packed with ZIP.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/exist/eXist-1.0b1.war">eXist-1.0b1.war</a>
                    </td>
                    <td>Web application archive, ready to be installed into an
                        existing servlet-engine like Tomcat or Jetty.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <th align="left" colspan="2">Development Snapshots</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td colspan="2">We started to release frequent development 
					snapshots. The snapshots reflect the current state of 
					development. You can find them in the unstable package on 
					the <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=17691">Sourceforge file release system.</a>
                    </td>
                </tr>
            </table>
        </section>
        <section title="Mailing list">
            <p>There's a <link href="http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=17691">mailing
                list</link> on sourceforge. If you are interested in using or
			contributing to eXist, you are encouraged to join the list.</p>
			
            <p>The list is archived at <a href="http://news.gmane.org/thread.php?group=gmane.text.xml.exist">Gmane</a>.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="articles" title="Articles">
            <p>If you would like to know more about the internal workings of eXist, you may
                read the following article:</p>

            <p>
                <i>Wolfgang Meier</i>. <link href="http://exist-db.org/webdb.pdf">eXist: An 
            Open Source Native XML Database</link>. 
            In: Akmal B. Chaudri, Mario Jeckle, Erhard Rahm, Rainer Unland (Eds.): 
            Web, Web-Services, and Database Systems. NODe 2002 Web- and Database-Related 
            Workshops, Erfurt, Germany, October 2002. Springer LNCS Series, 2593.</p>
			
            <p>A chapter about eXist is also contained in the book:</p>
			
            <p>Akmal B. Chaudri, Awais Rashid, Roberto Zicari (Eds.): 
			<link href="http://www.aw.com/catalog/academic/product/1,4096,0201844524,00.html">XML 
			Data Management: Native XML and XML-Enabled Database Systems</link>. 
			ISBN: 0-201-84452-4. Published by Addison Wesley Professional,
			March, 2003.</p>

        </section>
        <section id="links" title="Links">
            <p>Some links to other software packages which build upon or provide access to eXist:</p>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>
                        <link href="http://titanium.dstc.edu.au/xml/xmldbgui/">XMLdbGUI</link>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <p>A Swing-based graphical user-interface to access databases conforming to
							the XML:DB API.</p>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>
                        <link href="http://techweb.rfa.org/staff/bill">Python interface</link>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <p>A thin Python interface to eXist.</p>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>
                        <link href="http://cvs.sourceforge.net/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/exist/exist_php">
					PHP API</link>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <p>PHP class to access eXist using the XMLRPC API.</p>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>
                        <link href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/xml-simpledb">XML-SimpleDB</link>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <p>A perl implementation of the XML:DB API.</p>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
