<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Author: Wolfgang Meier "meier@ifs.tu-darmstadt.de" -->
<document xmlns:ci="http://apache.org/cocoon/include/1.0">
    <!-- include header -->
    <ci:include src="header.xml"/>
    <ci:include src="sidebar.xml"/>
    <body>
        <section title="News">
            <definitionlist>
            	<definition>
            		<term>
            			<b>April 7, 2003</b>
            		</term>
            		<def>0.9.1 released! This is mainly a maintenance release, fixing many
            		bugs found in 0.9, including eof exceptions, out-of-memory errors,
            		and corrupted database files. It also contains further performance
            		optimizations with respect to indexing and querying speed. New features
            		include the highlighting of search terms in query results, simpler
            		database startup, access to index information, new Cocoon examples, 
            		and an IzPack-based installer. For a complete list of changes see 
            		<link href="changes.xml">changes.xml</link>.</def>
            	</definition>
                <definition>
                    <term>
						<b>January 14, 2003</b>
                    </term>
					<def>Version 0.9 is out! This release fixes some of the remaining weak points of eXist,
						namely indexing performance and scalability. Storing more than 
						just a few megabytes into a single database collection is no longer a 
						problem, index files consume less disk space and indexing speed
						improved by an order of magnitude. New features include support
						for user authentication, access control and basic XInclude on
						the server. Version 0.9 also includes a lot of bug-fixes.
					</def>
                </definition>
            </definitionlist>
        </section>
        <section id="overview" title="Overview">
            <p>eXist is an Open Source native XML database featuring efficient, 
            	index-based XPath query processing, extensions for keyword search 
            	and tight integration with existing XML development tools. The database is lightweight,
                completely written in Java and may be easily deployed in a
                number of ways, running either as a stand-alone server process,
                inside a servlet-engine or directly embedded into an application.</p>
            <p>The database is currently best suited for applications dealing
                with small to large collections of XML documents, which are
                occasionally updated. Depending on how the database engine has
                been deployed, eXist offers several interfaces to application
                developers, including HTTP, XML-RPC, SOAP and WebDAV. Java
                developers should have a look at the <link
                    href="http://www.xmldb.org">XML:DB API</link>, which
                provides a common interface to access XML database services.</p>
            <p>eXist integrates well with <link
                    href="http://xml.apache.org/cocoon">Apache's Cocoon</link>,
                allowing developers to create complex web applications entirely
                based on XML and related technologies.</p>
            <p>For more information on eXist's features read the <link
                    href="features.xml">feature overview</link>.</p>
        </section>
        <section title="Online demos">
            <p>Several <b>online demos</b> are available:</p>
            <table border="0" width="100%">
                <tr>
                    <td width="40%">
                        <link href="simple/xquery.xsp">xquery.xsp</link>
                    </td>
                    <td width="60%">Simple query interface to send XPath queries to the server.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td width="40%">
						<link href="xse/squery.xsp?cname=%2Fdb%2Fshakespeare%2Fplays">squery.xsp</link>
                    </td>
                    <td width="60%"> XML search engine, where you don't have to type XPath, with formatting adapted for each collection, highlight of terms of the query, history .</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td width="40%">
                        <link href="xmldb/db/">
                            Cocoon example</link>
                    </td>
                    <td width="60%">A database browser which uses Cocoon's
                        xmldb:// pseudo-protocol and XSL stylesheets.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td width="40%">
                        <link href="library/biblio.xml">Bibliography</link>
                    </td>
                    <td width="60%">This example provides a customized interface
                        to search through a library catalogue.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td width="40%">
                        <link
                            href="xmldb/db/xinclude/xinclude.xml">
                            XInclude Sample Document</link>
                    </td>
                    <td width="60%">This document demonstrates XInclude on the
                        server. Parts of the document are generated dynamically
                        the XInclude processor.</td>
                </tr>
            </table>
        </section>
        <section id="download" title="Download">
            <p>eXist is released to the public under the <link
                    href="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/lesser.html">GNU
                LGPL</link> license.</p>
            <p>eXist may be downloaded either as a zip package containing the
                complete distribution or as a web application archive
                (war-file). Download the war-file if you want to install eXist
                into an existing servlet-engine or write your own web application. 
                To get started, I suggest downloading the zip package, which does
                also contain a ready-to-run webserver (Jetty).</p>
            <p>The distribution includes source code and all required third
                party libraries. Java version 1.4 or above is needed. The distribution has been
                tested on Linux, Solaris and Windows 2000/ME with Suns JDK 1.4
                and IBM JDK 1.4. If you experience any problems on other
                operating systems, please send me a bug report.</p>
            <p>The current version is 0.9. For instructions on starting eXist,
                read the <link href="quickstart.xml">Quick Start Guide</link>.</p>
            <table cellpadding="5" cellspacing="5">
                <tr>
                    <th align="left">Stable version</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/exist/eXist-0.9.1-install.jar">eXist-0.9.1-install.jar</a>
                    </td>
                    <td>Installer based on IzPack. Run with <tt>java -jar eXist-0.9.1-install.jar</tt>.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/exist/eXist-0.9.1.tar.gz">eXist-0.9.1.tar.gz</a>
                    </td>
                    <td>Distribution including source code and required
                        third-party libraries. Packed with tar and gzip.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/exist/eXist-0.9.1.zip">eXist-0.9.1.zip</a>
                    </td>
                    <td>Distribution packed with ZIP.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/exist/eXist-0.9.1.war">eXist-0.9.1.war</a>
                    </td>
                    <td>Web application archive, ready to be installed into an
                        existing servlet-engine like Tomcat or Jetty.</td>
                </tr>
            </table>
            <p>eXist is Open Source and free to everyone. However, you may consider to make a donation
            for the enhancement and further development of the software. Just click the 
            <emphasis>PayPal</emphasis> button below. Making a donation implies extra email-support by the
            maintainer. Donations help to improve the quality of the software and to implement 
            missing features.</p>
            <p>
                <A HREF="https://www.paypal.com/affil/pal=sbhati%40web.de" target="_blank">
                    <IMG ALT="Donations via PayPal!" BORDER="0" SRC="http://images.paypal.com/images/lgo/logo3.gif"/>
                </A>
            </p>
        </section>
        <section title="Mailing list">
            <p>There's also a <link
                    href="http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=17691">mailing
                list</link> on sourceforge. If you are interested in using or
                contributing to eXist, you are encouraged to join the list.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="articles" title="Articles">
            <p>If you would like to know more about the internal workings of eXist, you may
                read the following article:</p>
                
            <p><i>Wolfgang Meier</i>. <link href="http://exist-db.org/webdb.pdf">eXist: An 
            Open Source Native XML Database</link>. 
            In: Akmal B. Chaudri, Mario Jeckle, Erhard Rahm, Rainer Unland (Eds.): 
            Web, Web-Services, and Database Systems. NODe 2002 Web- and Database-Related 
            Workshops, Erfurt, Germany, October 2002. Springer LNCS Series, 2593.</p>
            
			<p>A chapter about eXist is also contained in the book:</p>
			
			<p>Akmal B. Chaudri, Awais Rashid, Roberto Zicari (Eds.): 
			<link href="http://www.aw.com/catalog/academic/product/1,4096,0201844524,00.html">XML 
			Data Management: Native XML and XML-Enabled Database Systems</link>. 
			ISBN: 0-201-84452-4. Published by Addison Wesley Professional,
			March, 2003.</p>
			
        </section>
		<section id="links" title="Links">
			<p>Some links to other software packages which build upon or provide access to eXist:</p>
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><link href="http://titanium.dstc.edu.au/xml/xmldbgui/">XMLdbGUI</link></term>
					<listitem>
						<p>A Swing-based graphical user-interface to access databases conforming to
							the XML:DB API.</p>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><link href="http://techweb.rfa.org/staff/bill">Python interface</link></term>
					<listitem>
						<p>A thin Python interface to eXist.</p>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><link href="http://cvs.sourceforge.net/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/exist/exist_php">
					PHP API</link></term>
					<listitem>
						<p>PHP class to access eXist using the XMLRPC API.</p>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><link href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/xml-simpledb">XML-SimpleDB</link></term>
					<listitem>
						<p>A perl implementation of the XML:DB API.</p>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</section>
					
        <section id="tech" title="Technical Data">
            <table border="0" cellpadding="5" cellspacing="5">
                <tr>
                    <th align="left" colspan="2">
                        <b>System requirements</b>
                    </th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Java:</td>
                    <td>JDK 1.4</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>Tested platforms:</td>
                    <td>Linux (SuSE 7.1, Mandrake 8.2/9.0), Solaris 8, Windows 2000/ME</td>
                </tr>
            </table>
            <table border="0" cellpadding="5" cellspacing="5">
                <tr>
                    <th align="left">
                        <b>Disk space requirements</b>
                    </th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td valign="top">Due to the created indexes, files stored in
                        eXist occupy about 1.2 to 2 times the size of the raw
                        XML source. Highly structured XML files require more
                        space than simple structured documents.</td>
                </tr>
            </table>
            <table border="0" cellpadding="5" cellspacing="5">
                <tr>
                    <th align="left" colspan="2">
                        <b>Limits</b>
                    </th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td valign="top">Max. number of documents:</td>
                    <td>2<sup>31</sup> documents.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td valign="top">Max. number of documents per collection:</td>
                    <td>2<sup>31</sup> documents.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td valign="top">Max. size per document:</td>
                    <td>eXist uses unique object identifiers of type long for
                        every XML node. A document may thus have 2<sup>63</sup>
                        - x single XML-nodes per document, where x = 0 for an
                        ideally well-balanced document tree. To keep x small,
                        eXist does <b>not</b> balance the tree as a whole, but
                        recomputes the ideal tree structure for every single
                        level of the tree's node hierarchy. Thus, the 64bit
                        identifiers are normally more than sufficient to index
                        large documents, because only a few identifiers are
                        wasted for the balancing. The largest document I tried
                        had about 250MB of XML data.</td>
                </tr>
            </table>
        </section>
        <section id="missing" title="Future plans">
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>XUpdate</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <p>We are currently working on XUpdate. It will 
                        definitely be part of the 1.0 release.</p>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>XPath Support</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <p>The XPath implementation still needs some work to be
                            done. A new implementation is on its way.</p>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
