<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <!-- include header -->
    <xi:include href="header.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="sidebar.xml"/>

    <newsblock>
        <div id="quotes">
            <a href="http://www.infoworld.com/reports/01SRtoy06.html">
                <img src="resources/TOY2006s.jpg" border="0"/>
            </a>
            <blockquote>A smooth, even pleasurable introduction to the power of XQuery and XML
                content management</blockquote>
            <div class="source">InfoWorld</div>
        </div>
    </newsblock>

    <body>
        <section id="overview" title="Overview">

            <p>eXist is an Open Source native XML database featuring efficient, index-based <a
                    href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xquery/">XQuery</a> processing, automatic structural
                indexing, extensions for full-text search, <a
                    href="http://xmldb-org.sourceforge.net/xupdate/">XUpdate</a> support, XQuery <a
                    href="update_ext.xml">update extensions</a> (based on an early draft of <a
                    href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xquery-update-10/">XQuery Update Facility 1.0</a>)
                and tight integration with existing XML development tools. The database implements
                most of the current <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xquery/">XQuery 1.0
                recommendation</a>, with exception of the schema import and schema validation
                features defined as optional in the XQuery specification.</p>

            <p>eXist provides a powerful environment for the development of web applications based
                on XQuery and related standards. Entire web applications can be written in XQuery,
                using XSLT, XHTML, CSS and maybe Javascript (for AJAX functionality). XQuery server
                pages can be executed from the filesystem or stored in the database.</p>

            <p> To avoid memory-intensive document tree traversals during query processing, eXist
                uses an efficient structural index structure which is based on a numerical indexing
                scheme for identifying XML nodes in the index.</p>

        </section>


        <section id="download" title="Download">
            <p>eXist-db can be <a href="download.xml">download</a>ed as a izPack installer (as
                    <b>jar</b> and <b>exe</b>), a <b>war</b> webarchive for deployment into a
                servlet container and finally as a <b>Cocoon block</b>. </p>
        </section>

        <section title="Community Support" id="mailing">
            <p>The eXist-db has a large community of users and developers, which is very active. The
                primary medium for asking questions, getting help or posting bug reports or fixes is
                the project mailing list. To subscribe/unsubscribe visit the <a
                    href="http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=17691">mailing lists page</a> on
                sourceforge.</p>


            <p>Previous messages posted on the are archived on <a
                    href="http://www.nabble.com/eXist-f4072.html">nabble.com</a> and <link
                    href="http://news.gmane.org/thread.php?group=gmane.text.xml.exist"
                >gmane.org</link> provides a <link href="news://news.gmane.org/gmane.text.xml.exist"
                    > NNTP</link> interface. </p>

            <p>The project has an chat box <b>#existdb</b> which is accessible via IRC on <link
                    href="irc://irc.freenode.net/existdb">irc.freenode.net</link> and via an AJAX
                based <link href="http://irc.exist-db.org">web interface</link>. The channel is open
                for general discussions on eXist and related subjects.</p>

            <p>All eXist-db sources are freely available via a SourceForge <link
                    href="http://sourceforge.net/svn/?group_id=17691">subversion</link> repository.
                The <a href="http://www.ohloh.net/projects/252?p=eXist">source code</a> is made
                    <link
                    href="http://www.koders.com/info.aspx?c=ProjectInfo&amp;pid=VUM641QG5USW5EHRSLWDSDVM6G"
                    >browsable</link> and is continuously <link
                    href="http://fisheye3.cenqua.com/browse/exist/">monitored</link> and <link
                    href="http://parabuild.viewtier.com:8080/parabuild/index.htm?cid=de9f&amp;view=detailed&amp;buildid=321"
                    >built</link>.</p>



        </section>

        <section id="license" title="License">
            <p> eXist is released to the public under the terms of the <link
                    href="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/lesser.html"> GNU LGPL </link> license.</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
