<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<!-- modified jens_petersen 2010-05-20 -->
<book>
    <bookinfo>
        <graphic fileref="logo.jpg"/>
        <productname>Open Source Native XML Database</productname>
        <title>Quick Start</title>
        <date>March 2010</date>
        <author>
            <firstname>Wolfgang M.</firstname>
            <surname>Meier</surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address format="linespecific"><email>wolfgang at exist-db.org</email></address>
            </affiliation></author>
    </bookinfo>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="sidebar.xml"/>
    <chapter>
        <title>Quick Start</title>
        <section id="objectives">
            <title>Objectives</title>
            <para>
                This guide describes the easiest way to install and begin using the eXist-db Open Source Native XML Database.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id="requirements">
            <title>Requirements</title>
            <para>
                eXist can be installed on newer versions of Linux, Windows and Mac OS X. In order to run the eXist installer, it is necessary to have
                the <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/javase/downloads/widget/jdk6.jsp">Java Development Kit (JDK)</ulink> installed on your operating system.
                The JDK is pre-installed on Mac OS X through 10.6; for instructions on how to install JDK on Windows, see this <ulink
                    url="http://java.about.com/od/gettingstarted/ss/installjdk.htm">guide</ulink>; for instructions on how to install JDK on Linux, see this
                    <ulink url="http://www.wikihow.com/Install-Java-on-Linux">guide</ulink>.
            </para>
            <para>
                In order to be able to install and start up eXist on Mac OS X and Linux, you need to know the basics of how to use your operating system's terminal (Applications/Utilities/Terminal.app on Mac OS X). On Windows, knowing how to use the command
            prompt is not required for installing eXist.
            </para>
            <para>Some knowledge of XML and XQuery is required in order to start using eXist to query XML documents. The <ulink
                    url="http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/XQuery">XQuery Wikibook</ulink> is a useful resource for learning how to use XQuery with eXist; it
                also contains references to other resources for learning XQuery. </para>
        </section>
        <section id="installation">
            <title>Installing eXist</title>
            <para>Download the <ulink url="download.xml">latest stable release</ulink> of eXist. The installer is a
                    <filename>.jar</filename> (Java Archive) file which automatically determines the correct system settings (i.e. paths and environment
                variables) for eXist. On Windows and Linux, the installer can also create convenient desktop shortcuts for starting eXist.</para>
            <para>Once the download has completed, launch the eXist installer by doing
                one of the following:</para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Windows and Mac users: Double-click on the installer file: <filename> eXist-setup-[version]-revXXXXX.jar</filename></para>                    
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Linux users: Entering the following command in a Unix shell using the <command>-jar</command> option:</para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
            <synopsis format="linespecific">java -jar eXist-setup-[version]-revXXXXX.jar</synopsis>
            <para>Windows and Mac users can also use this procedure, entering the same command in Windows command prompt or in a Unix shell.</para>
            <para>After the installer is launched, follow the prompts to complete the installation. </para>
            <para>During installation, you are asked to supply a password for the eXist administrator account (the "admin" password). You are strongly encouraged to set the admin password on all installations of eXist, even those without internet access; otherwise the eXist
            security manager will be disabled. The admin password asked for during the install procedure is not the admin password of your operating system, but the password to be used for the eXist admin account.</para>
            <para>eXist, through Jetty, by default uses port 8080. There may be other services on your system using this port. To see whether this is the case, enter <ulink url="http://localhost:8080/">http://localhost:8080/</ulink> in your browser. If another service occupies this port, you cannot start up eXist unless you shut down the service in question or make eXist use another port. To make eXist use another port, open the file <filename moreinfo="none">/tools/jetty/etc/jetty.xml</filename> inside your eXist installation in a text or XML editor and change the value "8080" in</para>
            
            <synopsis format="linespecific">&lt;Set name=&quot;port&quot;&gt;&lt;SystemProperty name=&quot;jetty.port&quot; default=&quot;8080&quot;/&gt;&lt;/Set&gt;</synopsis>
            <para>to a port that is not used, e.g. "8899":</para>
            <synopsis format="linespecific">&lt;Set name=&quot;port&quot;&gt;&lt;SystemProperty name=&quot;jetty.port&quot; default=&quot;8899&quot;/&gt;&lt;/Set&gt;</synopsis>
            <para>eXist uses port 8443 for confidential communication. Another service may also be using this port.  To make eXist use another port, open the file <filename moreinfo="none">/tools/jetty/etc/jetty.xml</filename> and change the value "8443" in</para>
            <synopsis format="linespecific">&lt;Set name=&quot;confidentialPort&quot;&gt;8443&lt;/Set&gt;</synopsis>
            <para>and</para>
            <synopsis format="linespecific">&lt;Set name=&quot;Port&quot;&gt;8443&lt;/Set&gt;</synopsis>
            <para>to a port that is not used, e.g. "8444".</para>
            <!-- Installation on a headless system does not belong in a quick start. Jens Petersen. 
            <note>
                <para>The eXist installer requires a graphical desktop in order to launch. However, If you wish to install eXist on a headless system, use the
                        <command>-p</command> parameter when following <emphasis>Option Two</emphasis> above. This will automatically start the installation.
                    Option <command>-p</command> expects a single parameter: the path to the directory where you would like to install eXist. For
                    example:</para>
                <synopsis>java -jar eXist-{version}.jar -p /usr/local/exist</synopsis>
            </note>
-->
        </section>
        <section id="launching">
            <title>Launching eXist</title>
            <para>You should now be ready to launch eXist. If you use Linux or Windows and have allowed the installer to create desktop shortcuts, double-click on the <emphasis>eXist
                    Database Startup</emphasis> icon on your desktop, or select this item from the Start menu.
            </para>
            <para>The installer will not create desktop shortcuts on Macs.  If you are a Mac user, or if you wish to start eXist manually on Linux or Windows, do the following:</para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Open the terminal or command prompt</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Change to the directory where you installed eXist (e.g. "<filename>/usr/local/lib/exist/</filename>", "<filename>/Applications/exist/</filename>" or "<filename
                        >C:\Program Files\eXist</filename>").</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>If you are a Linux or Mac user, enter the following:</para>
                    <synopsis format="linespecific">bin/startup.sh</synopsis>
                    <para>If you are a Windows user, enter the following:</para>
                    <synopsis format="linespecific">bin\startup.bat</synopsis>
                </step>
            </procedure>
            <para>If these scripts do not launch eXist, you can launch it by changing to the directory where you installed eXist and entering the following into the console:</para>
            <synopsis>java -Xmx128M -Djava.endorsed.dirs=lib/endorsed -jar start.jar jetty</synopsis>
                <!--Question: why does this connect to www.terracotta.org? I have an app that intercepts all requests like this and it says that Terminal wants to connect on port 80 o www.terracotta.org. If I deny the connection, eXist still starts up. Jens Petersen-->
                <para>If you have problems running the shell/batch scripts, read
                        <ulink url="#appendix">Running Executable Files</ulink> below.</para>
            <para>
                While eXist starts up, log output appears in the console. If eXist 
                launched properly, you will find output similar to the following (this example output is taken from Mac OS X):
            </para>
            <example>
                <title>Console Output</title>
                <screen><![CDATA[
Using locale: en_US.UTF-8
04 Nov 2009 18:45:58,346 [main] INFO  (JettyStart.java [run]:90) - Configuring eXist from /Applications/eXist/conf.xml 
04 Nov 2009 18:45:58,346 [main] INFO  (JettyStart.java [run]:91) -  
04 Nov 2009 18:45:58,347 [main] INFO  (JettyStart.java [run]:92) - Running with Java 1.6.0_15 [Apple Inc. (Java HotSpot(TM) 64-Bit Server VM) in /System/Library/Frameworks/JavaVM.framework/Versions/1.6.0/Home] 
04 Nov 2009 18:45:58,347 [main] INFO  (JettyStart.java [run]:97) -  
04 Nov 2009 18:45:58,347 [main] INFO  (JettyStart.java [run]:101) - [eXist Version : 1.4.0] 
04 Nov 2009 18:45:58,347 [main] INFO  (JettyStart.java [run]:103) - [eXist Build : 20091104] 
04 Nov 2009 18:45:58,348 [main] INFO  (JettyStart.java [run]:105) - [eXist Home : /Applications/eXist] 
04 Nov 2009 18:45:58,348 [main] INFO  (JettyStart.java [run]:107) - [SVN Revision : 10364] 
04 Nov 2009 18:45:58,348 [main] INFO  (JettyStart.java [run]:115) - [Operating System : Mac OS X 10.6.1 x86_64] 
04 Nov 2009 18:45:58,349 [main] INFO  (JettyStart.java [run]:118) - [jetty.home : /Applications/eXist/tools/jetty] 
04 Nov 2009 18:45:58,349 [main] INFO  (JettyStart.java [run]:120) - [log4j.configuration : file:/Applications/eXist/log4j.xml] 
04 Nov 2009 18:45:59,871 [main] INFO  (FileResource.java [<clinit>]:60) - Checking Resource aliases 
04 Nov 2009 18:45:59,989 [main] INFO  (HttpServer.java [setStatsOn]:1130) - Statistics on = false for org.mortbay.jetty.Server@4cc72243 
04 Nov 2009 18:45:59,994 [main] INFO  (HttpServer.java [doStart]:684) - Version Jetty/5.1.12 
04 Nov 2009 18:46:00,336 [main] INFO  (Container.java [start]:74) - Started org.mortbay.jetty.servlet.WebApplicationHandler@1f758cd1 
Logging already initialized. Skipping...
04 Nov 2009 18:46:01,214 [main] INFO  (Container.java [start]:74) - Started WebApplicationContext[/exist,eXist XML Database] 
04 Nov 2009 18:46:01,231 [main] INFO  (SocketListener.java [start]:205) - Started SocketListener on 0.0.0.0:8080 
04 Nov 2009 18:46:01,232 [main] INFO  (Container.java [start]:74) - Started org.mortbay.jetty.Server@4cc72243 
04 Nov 2009 18:46:01,232 [main] INFO  (JettyStart.java [run]:174) - ---------------------------------------------------------------- 
04 Nov 2009 18:46:01,232 [main] INFO  (JettyStart.java [run]:175) - eXist-db has started on port 8080. Configured contexts: 
04 Nov 2009 18:46:01,233 [main] INFO  (JettyStart.java [run]:177) - http://localhost:8080/exist 
04 Nov 2009 18:46:01,233 [main] INFO  (JettyStart.java [run]:179) - ---------------------------------------------------------------- 
]]></screen>
            </example>
            <para>
                When you see the "eXist-db has started" message, you know that your eXist installation works.
            </para>
            <note>
                <para>If the above start-up fails, ensure the <envar>JAVA_HOME</envar> and <envar>EXIST_HOME</envar> 
                    environment variables - the eXist and Java JDK root
                    directory paths - point to the correct locations. Both variables are used in the
                    <filename>startup.bat</filename> and <filename>startup.sh</filename>
                    scripts and have to be set correctly before the scripts are run (you can also insert the lines required in the beginning of the scripts themselves).</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><envar>JAVA_HOME</envar> should point to the directory where the Java
                            JDK is installed. A common problem is that the path added by the
                            installer points to the JRE, not the JDK. 
                            For instructions about how to set JAVA_HOME on Windows, 
                            follow the instructions in this <ulink url="http://confluence.atlassian.com/display/DOC/Setting+the+JAVA_HOME+Variable+in+Windows">guide</ulink>; 
                            on Linux, follow this <ulink url="http://www.cyberciti.biz/faq/linux-unix-set-java_home-path-variable/"
                                >guide</ulink>, and
                            on Mac OS X, follow this <ulink url="http://www.mehtanirav.com/2008/09/02/setting-java_home-on-mac-os-x-105"
                                >guide</ulink>. 
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <envar>EXIST_HOME</envar> should point to the directory that contains the
                            configuration file <filename moreinfo="none">conf.xml</filename>, so
                            that the server uses the path <filename>EXIST_HOME/conf.xml</filename>.
                            For example, if the <envar>EXIST_HOME</envar> path is <filename
                                >C:\Program Files\eXist</filename>, the server will look for
                            <filename>C:\Program Files\eXist\conf.xml</filename>. You can set EXIST_HOME in the same way that you set JAVA_HOME; thus, on Mac OS X, you would enter "export EXIST_HOME=/Applications/eXist" in the Terminal. 
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>You should also ensure that you have "write" permissions set for the <filename
                    moreinfo="none">data</filename> directory located in <filename
                        moreinfo="none">webapp/WEB-INF/</filename>.</para>
            </note>        </section>
        <section id="acccessing">
            <title>Accessing the Server</title>
            <para>In the default setup, eXist runs inside a web application served by a
                pre-configured <ulink url="http://jetty.codehaus.org/jetty/">Jetty</ulink> webserver. All
                interfaces are provided as servlets. To test that the server is running, enter the
                following URL in a web browser:</para>
            <para>
                <ulink url="http://localhost:8080/exist/index.xml"
                    >http://localhost:8080/exist/index.xml</ulink>
            </para>
            <para>(If you have changed the port used by eXist, you have to change the port value in the URL. In the console output upon start-up, the correct URL is given towards the end.)</para>
            <para>You should now see the following web page: </para>
            <screenshot>
                <graphic fileref="resources/index1.png"/>
            </screenshot>
            <para>Note that this web page is not the eXist-db.org homepage, but rather a local copy of this homepage
                included with the eXist installation. This local copy includes the eXist documentation,
                function libraries, resources, and a collection of XQuery examples that can be installed through the Admin webpage.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id="sample-apps">
            <title>Installing Sample Applications using the Admin Webpage</title>
            <para>To begin using the database system, you must first create document collections and
                import files into eXist. To help you in learning these and other basic database
                operations, a number of simple XQuery web applications have been included with the
                eXist distribution. These applications are designed to allow users to experiment and
                query sample XML documents using the eXist database system. </para>
            <informaltable>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td>
                                <para>To start using these sample applications, you must log in to
                                    the eXist database administration page. To log in, go to the
                                    <ulink url="http://localhost:8080/exist/admin/admin.xql"
                                        >Administration &#187; Admin</ulink> link
                                        
                                        located on the sidebar menu on the <ulink
                                            url="http://localhost:8080/exist/"
                                            >local eXist homepage</ulink>.</para>
                                <para>You should now see the login screen as shown on the
                                    right.</para>
                                <para>Enter the username "admin" and the password you set during installation (or
                                    which you have set by other means). </para>
                            </td>
                            <td>
                                <screenshot>
                                    <graphic fileref="resources/admin1.png"/>
                                </screenshot>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>
                                <para>Once you have logged in, select Examples Setup from the menu on the left. Most of the example data is shipped with eXist, but some files need to be downloaded. Check the "The XML Acronym Demystifier" and "The Mondial Database (Europe)" in order to download these files. Click on the "Import Files" button to import the example data into eXist.</para>
                                <para>After you have imported the files, you can access the collections they are imported into by clicking on "Browse Collections". Here you can upload and delete individual files, as well as view the contents of them.</para>
                            </td>
                            <td>
                                <screenshot>
                                    <graphic fileref="resources/admin2.png"/>
                                </screenshot>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>
                                <para>After the example data has been imported, you can go back to the <ulink
                                    url="http://localhost:8080/exist/"
                                    >Home</ulink> page and you will now be able to query the imported files through a number of small web applications listed in <ulink
                                        url="http://localhost:8080/exist/examples.xml"
                                        >All Examples</ulink> in the "Examples" tab.</para>     
                                    <!--"All Examples" should be moved up to the top in the Examples tab. "Bibliographic" should read "Bibliography". Jens Petersen-->
                                <para>The simplest of these applications is the <ulink
                                    url="http://localhost:8080/exist/sandbox/"
                                    >XQuery Sandbox</ulink> shown on the right which allows
                                    users to submit queries to the XML files imported into the database. The XQuery Sandbox
                                    provides the easiest way to start experimenting with
                                    eXist and XQuery.</para>
                                <para>A number of sample queries are furnished through the dropdown menu. 
                                    After modifying the queries, you can store them in the slots on the left. 
                                    Click on an empty slot to store the query in the  main query field. 
                                    If you click on a slot with a stored query, the contents of the stored query and the main query field will be swapped.
                                <!-- Users have complained that they do not understand this mechanism. Perhaps it would be an idea to have separate store and display buttons. Jens Petersen -->
                                </para>
                            </td>
                            <td>
                                <screenshot>
                                    <graphic fileref="resources/sandbox.png"/>
                                </screenshot>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </informaltable>
        </section>
        <section id="administering">
            <title>Administering eXist with the Java Admin Client</title>
            <para>In addition to the Admin webpage, eXist provides a Java-based Admin
                Client. This application enables users to perform more complex administrative tasks,
                such as user management, security settings, batch import of whole directories, and backup/restore of the database. </para>
            <para><!-- This GUI client can be used either as a graphical interface, or through a DOS or
                Unix command-line - which uses parameter options for specific tasks. If no action is
                specified on the command-line, the client will enter "interactive mode" and display
                a graphical login interface. -->
                Additional information on using the Admin Client from
                the command line is available in the section on <ulink url="client.xml">Using the Java Client on the Command Line</ulink>.</para>
            
            <para>You can launch the client by doing one of the
                following:</para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Windows and Linux users can double-click on the desktop shortcut icon (if
                        created) or select the shortcut icon from the start menu (if
                        created)</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>or launch using Java WebStart:</para>
                    <para>
                        <ulink url="webstart/exist.jnlp">
                            <graphic fileref="resources/webstart.small.jpg"/>
                        </ulink>
                    </para>
                    <para>You can also find the Java WebStart launch icon in the Administration menu in the left sidebar of all
                        documentation pages. <!--NOTE: Java WebStart needs to be found by the web
                        browser and the eXist jars need to be signed (if you compiled them
                        yourself)!-->
                    </para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>or enter the following in a Unix shell or DOS/Windows command
                        prompt (with JAVA_HOME set correctly):</para>
                    <synopsis format="linespecific">bin\client.bat (DOS/Windows)</synopsis>
                    <synopsis format="linespecific">bin/client.sh (Unix)</synopsis>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>or you can
                        enter the following on the command-line:</para>
                    <synopsis>java -jar start.jar client</synopsis>
                </step>
            </procedure>
            <informaltable>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td>
                                <para>A screenshot of the client login interface is shown on the
                                    right. In the login window, you can provide your username and
                                    password, and select a server. The client can either connect to
                                    a Remote server, or launch an Embedded database (i.e. a database embedded
                                    in an application which runs in the same process as the
                                    client). 
                                    <!--I don't quite understand this. -Jens Petersen-->
                                    For now, you should run the client remotely (running eXist on localhost is also running it remotely). 
                                    <!--The "embedded" option is useful for backup/restore or mass uploads
                                    of data (writing to an embedded instance avoids the network
                                    overhead).--></para>
                                <para>If you connect to a remote database, the URL field specifies
                                    the location of the database server. For the standard database setup used here, use the
                                    displayed default URI
                                    (xmldb:exist://localhost:8080/exist/xmlrpc). More
                                    information on server URIs and their function can be found in
                                    the guide to <ulink url="deployment.xml">Database Deployment</ulink>.</para>
                                <!-- <para>To log in to eXist's default administrator account, use the
                                    "admin" username. if you have not yet changed the admin password
                                    (e.g. if this is your first log in), leave the password field empty. After
                                    clicking "OK", the main client window will open (see the next
                                    screenshot).</para>
                                -->
                            </td>
                            <td>
                                <screenshot>
                                    <graphic fileref="resources/client1.png"/>
                                </screenshot>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>
                                <para>Once you have logged in, a client window will open. This
                                    window is split into two panels, and has a top menu and
                                    a toolbar. The top panel lists the database collections; the
                                    bottom panel is the "shell" and has a command prompt. This
                                    shell allows you to manually enter database commands. Most
                                    commands, however, can be entered using the menu. All of the
                                    menu and toolbar items have tooltips that explain
                                    their functions.</para>
                            </td>
                            <td>
                                <screenshot>
                                    <graphic fileref="resources/client2.png"/>
                                </screenshot>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>
                                <para>If eXist is online, you expose it to exploitation if you use an empty admin password. If you did not specify an admin password during installation, you are strongly advised to set an admin password as soon as possible. 
                                    You can do this in the Java Admin Client by following these steps:</para>
                                <orderedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Open the "Edit Users" window by selecting the "Manage
                                            Users" icon (image of a pair of keys) in the
                                            toolbar</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>At the top, select the "admin" user in the table of
                                            users</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Type in the new password into the password
                                            fields</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Click the "Modify User" button to apply the
                                            changes</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </orderedlist>
                            </td>
                            <td>
                                <screenshot>
                                    <graphic fileref="resources/client3.png"/>
                                </screenshot>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </informaltable>
        </section>
        <section id="shutting-down">
            <title>Shutting Down the Database</title>
            <para>It is recommended you properly shut down the database before killing the server
                process. If you do not do this, data files may become corrupted. There are several ways
                to trigger a database shutdown:</para>
            <!-- is hitting "^C" harmful? Jens Petersen-->
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Java Admin Client: select Connection &#187; Shutdown
                        from the menu.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Admin Webpage: select the Shutdown link
                            (<ulink url="http://localhost:8080/exist/admin/admin.xql"
                            >http://localhost:8080/admin.xql</ulink>)</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Run the <filename>bin/shutdown.sh</filename> (Unix) or <filename
                            >shutdown.bat</filename> (DOS/Windows) scripts.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Manually enter on the command-line:</para>
                    <synopsis>java -jar start.jar shutdown</synopsis>
                    <para>To specify the username and password, pass the <parameter>-u</parameter>
                        and <parameter>-p</parameter> parameters on the command-line. By default,
                        the command attempts to shut down the database running at the default URI:
                        xmldb:exist://localhost:8080/exist/xmlrpc/db. To shutdown a different
                        database, use the corresponding URI and the <parameter>-l</parameter>
                        parameter. For example: </para>
                    <synopsis>java -jar start.jar shutdown -u admin -p adminpass -l xmldb:exist://localhost:8080/exist/xmlrpc/db</synopsis>
                </step>
            </procedure>
            <!-- <note>
                <para>If eXist has been deployed as a web application in a web server other than the
                    supplied Jetty server, calling shutdown will close the database instance, but
                    not the server process of the web server. Since eXist does not know in which
                    environment it is running, it can only close itself. Regardless, closing the
                    database explicitly is always a good idea.</para>
            </note>
            -->
        </section>
        <!-- One could consider moving all of section 9 somehwere else, since it really does not belong in the Quick Start
            <section id="sect9">
            <title>Starting eXist as a Service</title>
            
            <para>Instead of manually running the eXist server in a shell window, you may prefer to
                run it as a background service which is automatically launched during system
                startup. eXist comes with pre-configured scripts that use Tanuki Software's <ulink
                    url="http://wrapper.tanukisoftware.org">Java Service Wrapper</ulink> to handle
                the setup procedure. The required scripts are contained in the directory <filename
                    >tools/wrapper</filename>. On Windows, you can simply choose the option to
                    <emphasis>Install eXist as Service</emphasis> from the eXist menu created in the
                start menu. You can also call <filename>tools/wrapper/bin/install.bat</filename>
                instead. This will install eXist and Jetty as a Windows service.</para>
            <note>
                <para>Installing eXist as a service on Windows Vista requires full administrator
                    rights. Right click on the start menu item and select "Run as administrator".
                    You may need to do this even if you are already logged in as an
                    administrator.</para>
            </note>
            <para>After executing the install.bat script, you should find eXist listed in the list
                of services currently registered with Windows:</para>
            <screenshot>
                <graphic fileref="resources/services.png"/>
            </screenshot>
            <para>Once the service is registered, you can launch it via the service manager as shown
                in the screenshot or from the command line:</para>
            <synopsis>
                cd tools\wrapper\bin
                wrapper.exe &#x002d;&#x002d;start ..\conf\wrapper.conf
            </synopsis>
            <para>For Linux, all of the start/shutdown scripts can be found in <filename
                    >tools/wrapper/bin/exist.sh</filename>. You can create a link to this file from
                the <filename>init.d</filename> directory of your distribution (where all of the
                start/shutdown scripts reside). Normally, the directory will be <filename
                    >/etc/init.d</filename>. For example:</para>
            <synopsis>ln -s $EXIST_HOME/tools/wrapper/bin/exist.sh /etc/init.d/exist</synopsis>
            <para>You can then add the service to the correct system runlevel. Check with your Linux
                distribution for instructions.</para>
        </section>
        -->
        
        <section id="troubleshooting">
            <title>If Something Goes Wrong ...</title>
            <para>If you experience any problems while installing eXist, your first step should be
                to check the log files to get additional information about the source of the
                problem. eXist uses the <emphasis>log4j-package</emphasis> to write output logs to
                files. By default, this output is written to the directory <filename moreinfo="none"
                    >webapp/WEB-INF/logs</filename>. <!--Or, if you are running eXist as a Windows or
                Unix service, check the directory <filename>tools/wrapper/logs</filename>. -->The main
                log files for eXist itself are <filename>exist.log</filename> and <filename
                    >xmldb.log</filename>. <!-- The other log files show output from Cocoon.  --></para>
            <para>If you encounter a problem you are unable to fix, check the <ulink
                url="index.xml#mailinglists">mailing list</ulink> archives for postings on similar
                errors. If you cannot find a posting, or you are still unsure about the problem, 
                consider posting your problem on the list for feedback. If you do decide to
                post a message, please include any exception message you find, both in the logs and
                the console<!--, and ensure you post the server-side, and not the client-side messages
                (client-side messages such as browser errors are not useful for
                troubleshooting)-->.</para>
        </section>
        <section id="bin-executables">
            <title>Running Executable Files</title>
            <para>Included in the distribution are a number of useful <filename>.sh</filename> (Unix
                Shell) and <filename>.bat</filename> (DOS batch) programs located in the <filename
                    >bin</filename> directory. If you installed the source distribution or used the
                installer, you can find this directory in the root directory of the distribution. <!-- If
                you installed the <filename>exist.war</filename> file (Web Application Archive), you
                will find the <filename>bin</filename> directory in the location the <filename
                >.war</filename> file was unpacked. </para>
            <para>These shell and batch scripts are simply wrappers (interfaces between the
                executable Java programs) around the bootstrap loader contained in the jar file
                <filename>start.jar</filename>.--></para>
            <para>If you find the programs do not launch, you can also manually launch these files
                on the command-line, and specify which application you would like to start.</para>
            <para>To manually launch these scripts:</para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>startup.sh (Unix) / startup.bat (Windows)</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Enter on the command-line:</para>
                        <synopsis>java -jar start.jar jetty</synopsis>
                        <para>Description: Starts the included Jetty web server at port 8080. eXist
                            <!--and Cocoon (a web development framework) are --> is installed as a web
                            application, located at <ulink url="http://localhost:8080/exist/"
                                >http://localhost:8080/exist/</ulink>. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>shutdown.sh (Unix) / shutdown.bat (Windows)</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Enter on the command-line:</para>
                        <synopsis>java -jar start.jar shutdown</synopsis>
                        <para>Description: Closes the running instance of eXist. If eXist has been
                            started with <filename>startup.sh</filename>, calling <filename
                                >shutdown.sh</filename> will also stop the Jetty web server.
                            Otherwise, only the database is stopped by this call, since eXist has no
                            control over the environment in which it is running. You should
                                <emphasis>always</emphasis> call <filename>shutdown</filename>
                            before killing the server process. <!--This issue is discussed in detail in
                            the succeeding section <emphasis>Shutting Down the
                            Database</emphasis>.-->
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>server.sh (Unix) / server.bat (Windows)</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Enter on the command-line:</para>
                        <synopsis>java -jar start.jar server</synopsis>
                        <para>Description: Launches eXist as a stand-alone server process. In this
                            setup, eXist is only accessible through the XMLRPC and the simple,
                            built-in HTTP interface.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>client.sh (Unix) / client.bat (Windows)</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Enter on the command-line:</para>
                        <synopsis>java -jar start.jar client</synopsis>
                        <para>Description: Launches the Java Administration Client - a graphical
                            database interface. By default, this application is also launched if no
                            application is selected on the command-line:</para>
                        <synopsis>java -jar start.jar</synopsis>
                        <!-- <para>The Java Admin Client is discussed in detail the succeeding section
                            <emphasis>Java Admin Client</emphasis></para> -->
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
