<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "docbookx.dtd">-->
<book xmlns:ci="http://apache.org/cocoon/include/1.0">
    <bookinfo>
        <graphic fileref="logo.jpg"/>
        <title>Open Source Native XML Database</title>
        <author>
            <firstname>Wolfgang M.</firstname>
            <surname>Meier</surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address format="linespecific">
					<email>wolfgang@exist-db.org</email>
                </address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </bookinfo>
    <ci:include src="sidebar.xml"/>
    <chapter>
        <title>User Authentication and Access Control</title>
        <section>
            <title>Overview</title>
            <para>Beginning with version 0.9, the database engine supports basic
                user authentication and access control. Access control loosely
                resembles Unix conventions, so Unix users should be familiar
                with this.</para>
            <para>Access control is disabled unless you set a password for the
                superuser (see below). Write access is granted to everyone, so please
                be careful about exposing your server to the world.</para>
            <para>eXist organizes users in groups. It has different permission
                sets for the user, the group and the rest of the world. Every
                user may be a member of several groups. The &quot;dba&quot;
                group is a special group reserved to database
                administrators. Only &quot;dba&quot; users are allowed to create
                or remove users or change permissions for other users.</para>
            <para>Information on users is stored in database collection
                <filename>/db/system</filename> in the special XML file
                <filename>/db/system/users.xml</filename>, which is created on
                database startup. By default, the
                <filename>/db/system</filename> collection is only readable for
                &quot;dba&quot; users, but you may choose to change this.</para>
            <para>Passwords are stored as MD5 digests. Whenever a user enters
                his password, the database generates an MD5 for it and compares
                it to the digest stored in <filename>users.xml</filename>. It is
                rather difficult to guess the original password from the MD5
                string, so passwords should be sufficiently secure.</para>
            <para>Every resource in the database is owned by a user and by a
                group. By default, the owner is set to the user creating the
                resource and his primary group. eXist manages different
                permissions for the owner, the owner group and others. Only the
                owner of the resource or dba users are allowed to change these permissions.</para>
            <para>eXist provides an XML:DB service interface to manipulate
                permissions and manage users. The interactive client uses this
                interface to implement a set of commands which we will use in
                the next sections.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Change the Superuser Password</title>
            <para>When the database is started for the first time, two default
                users are created: &quot;admin&quot; and &quot;guest&quot;.
                &quot;admin&quot; is a member of the dba group and thus has
                superuser rights.</para>
            <para>At database creation time, the &quot;admin&quot; password is
                null. This means that access to eXist is granted to everyone. To
                enable access control you have to set a password for the
                &quot;admin&quot; user. You may use the interactive client or
                the <ulink href="admin/admin.xql">administrative web
                interface</ulink> to do so. The client's graphical user interface
                has a dialog for user management. It is shown below:</para>
                
            <screenshot>
                <graphic fileref="client-5.png"/>
            </screenshot>
            
            <para>If you prefer the shell mode, use the
                <command>passwd</command> command to set a new password for
                the superuser:</para>
            <example>
                <title>Set a password for the superuser</title>
                <screen><![CDATA[type help or ? for help.
exist:/db>passwd admin
password: somepass
re-enter password: somepass
exist:/db>quit
]]></screen>
            </example>
            <para>Once a password has been set for the superuser, access control
                is enabled. To start the shell-mode client as superuser you
                will now have to specify the <option>-u</option> option, e.g.:</para>
            <synopsis>bin/client.sh -u admin</synopsis>
            <para>The other default user, &quot;guest&quot;, has password
                &quot;guest&quot;. The guest identity is internally assigned to
                all clients which have not authenticated themselves. For
                example, the Xincon WebDAV interface does not support
                authentication, so &quot;guest&quot; is assumed by default. This
                is certainly a source of confusion and you have to be careful
                about read/write permissions if you intend to use WebDAV.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Creating Users</title>
			<para>The <command>adduser</command> shell-command allows you 
				to create additional
                users. The command asks for a password and a list of groups to
                which the user should belong. An example is shown below:</para>
            <example>
                <title>Creating a New User</title>
                <screen><![CDATA[
exist:/db/shakespeare>adduser wolf
password: xxxxxxxx
re-enter password: xxxxxxxx
enter groups: users]]></screen>
            </example>
            
            <para>The command <command>users</command> displays a list of all known
            database users.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Resource Permissions</title>
            <para>The interactive client displays the permissions
                assigned to each resource (if you have set the
                <option>permissions=true</option> property in the
                <filename>client.properties</filename> file). An example is
                shown below:</para>
            <example>
                <title>Permissions</title>
                <screen><![CDATA[
exist:/db/shakespeare/plays>ls
-rwur-ur--      admin   dba     hamlet.xml
-rwur-ur--      admin   dba     macbeth.xml
-rwur-ur--      wolf    users   r_and_j.xml
-rwur-ur--      admin   dba     shakes.xsl
exist:/db/shakespeare/plays>]]></screen>
            </example>
            <para>In this example listing, all files except
                <filename>r_and_j.xml</filename> are owned by user
                &quot;admin&quot; and group &quot;dba&quot;. Currently, there
                are three different permissions: read, write and update.</para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>read</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>permission to read or query a file or list the
                            contents of a collection. If the read permission is
                            not set on a collection, you will not be able to see
                            the collection contents. The files in the collection
                            will also not be evaluated during XPath processing.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>write</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>permission to remove or update a file or add a new
                            file or subcollection to a collection.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>update</term>
                    <listitem>
						<para>permission to update an existing file, either by
							using XUpdate or by replacing the entire document. 
							Removing the file is not allowed unless the write 
							permission
                            is granted. Also, if a user has only update permissions
                            for a collection, he will not be allowed to create new
                            files in it.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>Permissions for collections are <emphasis>not</emphasis> inherited by sub-collections, i.e.
                you may have write permissions for some collections though you don't have
                them for the parent collection.</para>
            <para>The interactive client displays permissions similar to the
                Unix <command>ls -l</command>. In case you are not familiar with
                this: The first char in, for example,
                <option>-rwur-ur--</option> shows the type of the resource: it
                is set to minus (-) for documents and &quot;d&quot; for
                collections. The next three chars show the permissions for the
                user: you will see a minus here if a permission is denied, r, w
                or u if the permission is granted. This pattern is repeated for
                group and world, i.e. the next three chars represent group
                permissions, the last three chars show permissions granted to others.</para>
            <para>
                <option>-rwur-ur--</option> is the default setting for every
                newly created resource, i.e. group has read/update permissions,
                but not write permissions; others are only allowed to read.</para>
            <para>The database root collection <filename>/db</filename> by default
            has permissions set to <option>-rwurwurwu</option>, i.e. full access is
            granted to everyone.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Changing Permissions</title>
            <para>Permissions can be changed either through the <emphasis>Edit Properties</emphasis>
            dialog in the client GUI or with the <command>chmod</command> command in the shell 
            window. The <emphasis>Edit Properties</emphasis> dialog is shown below:</para>
            
            <screenshot>
                <graphic fileref="client-6.png"/>
            </screenshot>
            
            <para>Please note that only the owner of a resource or members of dba are allowed to change
                permissions. All other users will see an error message.</para>
                
            <para>On the shell, the <command>chmod</command> command expects two parameters: the first
                specifies the name of a resource or collection, the second defines the permissions 
                to set or remove. Permissions are defined using a syntax
                as shown below:</para>
            <synopsis>[user|group|other]=[+|-][read|write|update][, ...]</synopsis>
            <para>For example, to grant the write permission to the group and
                deny all to others, you may use:</para>
            <synopsis>chmod hamlet.xml group=+write,other=-read,-update,-write</synopsis>
            <para>If you don't specify a resource as first argument to <command>chmod</command>,
            the permission string will be applied to the current collection. This is an
            important feature if you want to change permissions for the <filename>/db</filename>
            root collection, which would otherwise not be possible. For example, to deny
            write permissions to world, cd into the root collection and enter:</para>
            
            <synopsis>chmod other=-write</synopsis>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Changing Resource Ownership</title>
            <para>Only the owner has full control over a resource. It is thus sometimes
				important to be able to change the ownership. The client provides the
                <command>chown</command> command to do this. The command expects three
                arguments:</para>
            <synopsis>chown user group [resource]</synopsis>
            <para>As for <command>chmod</command>, the resource argument is optional: if skipped, chown will be applied to the
                current collection. To change the owner of the file <filename>r_and_j.xml</filename>
                you may do:</para>
            <example>
                <title>Changing Ownership</title>
                <screen><![CDATA[
exist:/db/shakespeare/plays>chown wolf users r_and_j.xml
exist:/db/shakespeare/plays>ls
-rwur-ur--      admin   dba     hamlet.xml
-rwur-ur--      admin   dba     macbeth.xml
-rwur-ur--      wolf    users   r_and_j.xml
-rwur-ur--      admin   dba     shakes.xsl
exist:/db/shakespeare/plays>]]></screen>
            </example>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Authentication and Cocoon</title>
            <para>Cocoon uses the XML:DB API to access eXist. Cocoon thus has to authenticate
                the user like any other XML:DB based application. To make this easier, eXist
                contains a Cocoon action for the login task: <classname>XMLDBSessionLoginAction</classname>.
                The action presents a login form, checks the entered user and password against
                the database and stores them to a newly created HTTP session. As long as the session
                remains valid, no further login will be required. You should probably read the
                document about actions in Cocoon's documentation to fully understand how actions
                work. The following snippet shows a small example from Cocoon's <filename>sitemap.xmap</filename>
                configuration:</para>
            <example>
                <title><filename>sitemap.xmap</filename> snippet</title>
                <screen><![CDATA[
<!-- this is a protected resource: it uses the xmldb-login action
to authenticate a user against the database -->
<map:match pattern="xadmin.xsp">
    <map:act src="xmldb:exist:///db" type="xmldb-login">
         <map:generate src="xadmin.xsp" type="serverpages"/>
         <map:transform type="cinclude">
              <map:parameter name="use-request-parameters" value="true"/>
         </map:transform>
         <map:transform src="stylesheets/doc2html-2.xsl">
              <map:parameter name="use-request-parameters" value="true"/>
         </map:transform>
         <map:serialize encoding="UTF-8" type="xhtml"/>
     </map:act>
     <!-- no session found: display login form -->
     <map:generate src="login.xml"/>
     <map:transform type="cinclude"/>
     <map:transform src="stylesheets/doc2html-2.xsl"/>
     <map:serialize type="xhtml"/>
</map:match>]]></screen>
            </example>
        </section>
		  <section>
			  <title>XQuery Access Control</title>
			  <para>Please see the separate documentation on <ulink href="xacml.xml">XACML in eXist</ulink>.</para>
		  </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
