<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<book>
    <bookinfo>
        <graphic fileref="logo.jpg"/>
        <productname>Open Source Native XML Database</productname>
        <title>eXist - Tuning</title>
        <date>July 2011</date>
        <author>
            <firstname>Wolfgang M.</firstname>
            <surname>Meier</surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address format="linespecific"><email>wolfgang at exist-db.org</email></address>
            </affiliation></author>
        <author>
            <firstname>Leif-Jöran</firstname>
            <surname>Olsson</surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address format="linespecific"><email>ljo at exist-db.org</email></address>
            </affiliation></author>
    </bookinfo>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="sidebar.xml"/>
    <chapter>
        <title>Tuning the Database</title>
        <section>
            <title>Memory settings</title>
            <para>Java always limits the maximum amount of memory available to a process. eXist will
                thus not automatically use all of the memory available on your machine. The default
                setting is limited to 512MB.</para>
            <para>The maximum amount of memory Java will allocate is determined by the
                    <option>-Xmx</option> parameter passed to Java on the command line. If you
                launch eXist via one of the shell or batch scripts, you need to change
                    <option>-Xmx</option> in there.</para>
            <para>On a <emphasis>Unix</emphasis> system, edit <filename
                    >EXIST_HOME/bin/functions.d/eXist-settings.sh</filename>. Search for the
                    <option>JAVA_OPTIONS</option> variable, which sets <option>-Xmx</option> for the
                server. The <option>CLIENT_JAVA_OPTIONS</option> variable does the same for the Java
                admin client. Instead of directly editing <filename>eXist-settings.sh</filename>,
                you may also override those variables globally in your own shell.</para>
            <para>On <emphasis>Windows</emphasis>, the <option>-Xmx</option> settings is done in the
                main .bat files, .e.g. <filename>EXIST_HOME\bin\startup.bat</filename>.</para>
            <para>If you launch <emphasis>eXist as a service</emphasis>, all Java settings will be
                controlled by the service wrapper. In this case, the file to edit is by default<filename
                    >EXIST_HOME/tools/wrapper/conf/wrapper.conf</filename>. Search for the following
                lines:</para>
            <synopsis># Maximum Java Heap Size (in MB)
wrapper.java.maxmemory=128</synopsis>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Cache settings</title>
            <para>Each of the core database files and indexes has a page cache. The main purpose of
                this cache is to make sure that the most frequently used pages of the db files are
                kept in memory. If a file's cache becomes too small, eXist-db may start to unload pages
                just to reload them a few moment later. This "trashing effect" results in an
                immediate performance drop, in particular while indexing documents.</para>
            <para>All caches share a single memory pool, whose size is determined by the attribute
                    <option>cacheSize</option> in the <sgmltag>db-connection</sgmltag> section of
                    <filename>conf.xml</filename>. The global cache manager will dynamically grant
                more memory to caches while they are under load and free the memory used by idle
                caches.</para>
            <example>
                <title>cacheSize parameter in conf.xml</title>
                <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<db-connection cacheSize="48M" collectionCache="24M" database="native"
        files="webapp/WEB-INF/data" pageSize="4096" nodesBuffer="-1">]]></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>The default <ulink url="http://www.exist-db.org/configuration.html#N101B8"
                    >setting</ulink> of 48MB for <option>cacheSize</option> is <emphasis>very</emphasis> conservative. It
                will be ok for smaller databases, but you may soon experience a performance drop
                when indexing more than a few 100MB of XML data. Consider increasing
                    <option>cacheSize</option> up to approximately 1/3 of the main memory available to
                Java (determined by the <option>-Xmx</option> parameter passed to the Java command
                line). If you are forced to run eXist-db with other web applications in the same servlet
                engine, not recommended, you may need to choose a smaller setting (running out of memory will with high certainty crash
                the database, so please be careful).</para>
            <para>The <option>cacheSize</option> is mainly relevant when storing/updating data. The
                effect on query speed should not be that big, unless some of the index caches are
                really much too small.</para>
            <para>If you continue to experience performance issues while storing data, you may need
                to revisit your index configuration. Removing unused indexes will give more room to
                the other indexes. Only do full text indexing on the lowest possible level.</para>
            <para>The <option>nodesBuffer</option> attribute can be used to set eXist-db's temporary
                internal buffer to a fixed size. The buffer is used during indexing to cache nodes
                before they are flushed to disk. The default setting (nodesBuffer="-1") is to use as
                much memory as is available, but this can be problematic if you have to store large
                documents in a multi-user environment. For a production server, a good
                recommendation would be to set nodesBuffer to 1000 or less if there are many
                concurrent write operations.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Index configuration</title>
            <section>
                <title>Don't rely on the default behaviour</title>
                <para>eXist-db does <emphasis>NOT</emphasis> index any element or attribute values <emphasis>at all</emphasis> by
                    default. Always add appropriate indexing fitting your needs. It may create a full text index (see below), but this won't help with
                    standard comparison operators or functions. Thus, when evaluating an expression
                    like</para>
                <synopsis>//SPEECH[SPEAKER = "HAMLET"]</synopsis>
                <para>the query engine will fall back to a full scan over all
                        <sgmltag>SPEAKER</sgmltag> elements in the database. This is very slow and limits
                    concurrency. You should at least create a global index definition (in <filename>/db/system/config/db/collection.xconf</filename> inside the database) and add range indexes for
                    the most frequently used comparisons.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Disable any default indexes (pre 1.4)</title>
                <para>If no other <ulink url="indexing.xml">index configuration</ulink> is
                    found for a database collection, eXist-db will use the default settings specified
                    in <filename>conf.xml</filename>. For pre-1.4 eXist-db versions, the default is to
                    create a legacy full text index on <emphasis>ALL</emphasis> elements and attributes in
                    the database. The problem with this is that</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>maintaining the default index costs performance and memory, which
                            could be better used for other more specific indexes. The index may grow very fast,
                            which can be a destabilizing factor.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>the index is unspecific. The query engine cannot use it as efficiently
                            as a dedicated index on a set of named elements or attributes (<ulink
                                url="#idxdefs">see below</ulink>).</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <para>If you experience memory issues or observe constantly decreasing performance
                    while loading documents, tuning your indexes should be one of the first
                    steps:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>disable the legacy full text index in your index <ulink
                                url="indexing.xml#N10422">definitions</ulink>:</para>
                        <programlisting language="xquery"><![CDATA[
<collection xmlns="http://exist-db.org/collection-config/1.0">
    <index>
        <fulltext default="none" attributes="false">
        </fulltext>
    </index>
    ...
</collection>]]></programlisting>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>recreate full text or other indexes only on those elements and
                            attributes you want to query. Prefer index definitions by qname over a
                            configuration by path.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>if you are using eXist 1.4 or newer, we strongly asks you to consider <emphasis>switching to the new
                                    <ulink url="lucene.xml">Lucene-based index</ulink></emphasis>.
                            It provides better performance and stability.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </section>
            <section id="idxdefs">
                <title>Prefer simple index definitions</title>
                <para>Keeping your <ulink url="indexing.xml#N10422">index definitions</ulink> simple
                    makes it easier for the query optimizer to resolve dependencies. In particular,
                    avoid context-dependant index definitions unless you really have a reason to use
                    them. A context-dependant index is defined on a path like
                        <code>/book/chapter/title</code>, while general indexes are defined on a
                    simple element or attribute qname:</para>
                <programlisting language="xquery"><![CDATA[
<collection xmlns="http://exist-db.org/collection-config/1.0">
    <index>
        <!-- Range indexes by qname -->
        <create qname="title" type="xs:string"/>
        <create qname="@ID" type="xs:string"/>

        <!-- context-dependant configuration using the path attribute: -->
        <create path="/book/title" type="xs:string"/>
    </index>
</collection>
]]></programlisting>
                <para>Defining indexes on qnames may result in a larger index, but it also allows
                    the query engine to apply all available optimization techniques, which can
                    improve query times by an order of magnitude. Replacing a context-dependant
                    index by a simple index on qname can thus result in a performance boost, thanks
                    to eXist's new <ulink url="http://atomic.exist-db.org/blogs/eXist/NewIndexing"
                        >query-rewriting optimizer</ulink>. eXist-db versions released before June 2007 do not offer
                    these possibilities.</para>
            </section>
            <!-- Extend and move to the index configuration guide? -->
            <!--section>
                <title>Check if your index is used by the optimizer</title>
                
                <para>As said above, simple index definitions allow eXist's query rewriting
                    optimizer to exploit the available indexes in the best possible way. However,
                    there are cases for which an index can not be used at all or only in a limited
                    way. First, a typed range index will not be used if some of the element
                    or attribute values cannot be cast to valid instances of that type. If you
                    declare an index on element <sgmltag>year</sgmltag> to be of type 
                    <option>xs:integer</option>, then all year tags need to contain a valid
                    integer value. If one or more year elements in the input node set for the query 
                    contains a string, e.g. "unknown", instead of an integer, the index becomes 
                    useless. Because relying on the index alone would yield an incorrect result,
                    eXist has to fall back to a full scan.
                </para>
                
            </section-->
            <section>
                <title>Use range indexes on strongly typed data or short strings</title>
                <para>Range indexes work with the standard XQuery operators and string functions.
                    Querying for something like</para>
                <synopsis language="xquery"><![CDATA[//book[year = 2000]]]></synopsis>
                <para>will always be slow without an index. As long as no index is defined, eXist
                    has to scan over every year element in the db, casting its string value to an
                    integer.</para>
                <para>For queries on string content, range indexes work well for exact comparisons
                        (<code>author = 'Joe Doe'</code>) or regular expressions
                        (<code>matches(author, "^Joe.*")</code>), though you may also consider using
                    a full text index in the latter case. However, please note that range indexes on
                    strings are <emphasis>case-sensitive</emphasis> or rather, to use the correct
                    formulation, sensitive to the default <ulink
                        url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Collation">collation</ulink>. If you need
                    case-insensitive queries, consider a n-gram index.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Consider a n-gram index for exact substring queries on longer text
                    sequences</title>
                <para>While range indexes tend to become slow for substring queries (like
                        <code>contains(title, "XSLT 2.0")</code>), a n-gram index is nearly as fast
                    as a full text index, but it also indexes whitespace and punctuation.
                        <code>ngram:contains(title, "XSLT 2.0")</code> will only match titles
                    containing the exact phrase "XSLT 2.0". n-gram indexes are <emphasis>case
                        insensitive</emphasis>.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Choose a full text index for tokenizable text where whitespace/punctuation is
                    mostly irrelevant</title>
                <para>The full text index is fast and should be used whenever you need to query for
                    a sequence of separate words or tokens in a longer text. It can sometimes even
                    be faster to post-process the returned node set and filter out wrong matches
                    than using a much slower regular expression.</para>
                <para>eXist-db version 1.4 and newer offers a <ulink url="lucene.xml">new full text index</ulink> which
                    is based on Apache Lucene. It provides better performance and overall stability
                    than the legacy full text index.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Writing Queries</title>
            <section>
                <title>Prefer short paths</title>
                <para>eXist-db uses indexes to directly locate an element or attribute by its name. It
                    doesn't need to <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tree_traversal"
                        >traverse</ulink> the entire document tree. This means that the direct
                    selection of a node through a single descendant step is
                        <emphasis>faster</emphasis> than walking down the child axis. For
                    example:</para>
                <synopsis language="xquery">a/b/c/d/e/f</synopsis>
                <para>will be <emphasis>slower</emphasis> than</para>
                <synopsis language="xquery">a//f</synopsis>
                <para>The first expression requires 6 (!) index lookups while the second just needs
                    two. The same rules apply to the ancestor axis, e.g. f/ancestor::a.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Always process the most selective filter/expression first</title>
                <para>If you need multiple steps to select certain nodes from a larger node set, try
                    to process the most selective steps first. The earlier you can reduce the node
                    set to be processed, the faster your query will run. For example, assume we have
                    to find publications written by "Bjarne Stroustrup" after the year 2000:</para>
                <synopsis language="xquery"><![CDATA[/dblp/*[year > 2000][author = 'Bjarne Stroustrup']]]></synopsis>
                <para>The database has 568824 records matching <code>year &gt; 2000</code>, but only
                    41 of them were written by Stroustrup. Moving the filter on the author to the
                    front of the expression should thus result in better performance:</para>
                <synopsis language="xquery"><![CDATA[/dblp/*[author = 'Bjarne Stroustrup'][year > 2000]]]></synopsis>
                <para>It would certainly be nice if eXist could do this kind of optimization
                    automatically. We are working on it. eXist recognizes more and more cases for
                    intelligent query rewritings. For example, it already transforms the boolean
                    expression</para>
                <synopsis language="xquery"><![CDATA[/dblp/*[author = 'Bjarne Stroustrup' and year > 2000]]]></synopsis>
                <para>into a multi filter step as shown above.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Allow eXist-db to process large node sets in one step</title>
                <para>The query engine is optimized to process a path expression in one, single
                    operation. For instance, the XPath:</para>
                <synopsis language="xquery">//A/*[B = 'C']</synopsis>
                <para>is evaluated in a single operation for all context items. It doesn't make a
                    difference if the input set comes from a single large document, includes all the
                    documents in a specific collection or even the entire database. The logic of the
                    operation remains the same.</para>
                <para>However, "bad" queries can force the query engine to partition the input
                    sequence and process it in an item-by-item mode. Several examples for bad uses
                    of FLWOR expressions will be given below. Those should be easy to understand.
                    Other cases are not so obvious. For example, most function calls will also force
                    the query engine into item-by-item mode:</para>
                <synopsis language="xquery">//A/*[f:process(B) = 'C']</synopsis>
                <para>The function has to be called once for every instance of B. Normally, eXist
                    would try to evaluate the general comparison in a single step (assuming there's
                    a usable index on B). However, it now needs to call a (non-optimized) function
                    for each B and will thus need to process the entire comparison once for every
                    context item.</para>
                <para>There are functions to which the above does not apply. This includes most
                    functions which operate on indexes, e.g. <code>contains</code>,
                        <code>matches</code>, <code>starts-with</code>, <code>ngram:contains</code>,
                    and the like. They are optimized so eXist-db only needs to call them once to
                    process the entire context set. For example, using <code>ngram:contains</code>
                    as below is perfectly ok:</para>
                <synopsis language="xquery">//A/*[ngram:contains(B, 'C')]</synopsis>
                <para>while</para>
                <synopsis language="xquery">//A/*[ngram:contains(f:process(B), 'C')]</synopsis>
                <para>will again force eXist-db into step-by-step evaluation.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Prefer XPath Predicates Over Where Expressions</title>
                <para>This is a variation of the problems discussed above. Many users tend to
                    formulate SQL-style queries using an explicit "where" clause:</para>
                <example>
                    <title/>
                    <programlisting language="xquery"><![CDATA[
for $e in //entry 
where $e/@type = 'subject'
return $e
]]></programlisting>
                </example>
                <para>could be rewritten as:</para>
                <example>
                    <title>Equivalent query using XPath predicate</title>
                    <programlisting language="xquery"><![CDATA[
for $e in //entry[@type = 'subject'] 
return $e
]]></programlisting>
                </example>
                <para>The "for"..."where" expression forces the query engine into a step-by-step
                    iteration over the input sequence, testing each instance of $e against the where
                    expression. Possible optimizations are lost.</para>
                <para>Contrary to this, the XPath predicate expression can be processed in one
                    single step, making best use of any available indexes. Sure, there are use cases
                    which cannot be handled without using "where", e.g. joins between multiple
                    documents. That's ok. However, you shouldn't use "where" if you can replace it
                    by a simple XPath.</para>
                <para>Internally, the query engine will always try to process a "where" clause like
                    an equivalent XPath with predicate. However, it only detects the simple
                    cases.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Use general comparisons to compare an item to a list of alternatives</title>
                <para>General comparisons are very handy if you need to compare a given item to
                    several alternative values. For example, you could use an "or" to find all
                        <sgmltag>b</sgmltag> children whose string value is either "c" or
                    "d".</para>
                <synopsis language="xquery">//a[b eq 'c' or b eq 'd']</synopsis>
                <para>A shorter way to express this is:</para>
                <synopsis language="xquery">//a[b = ('c', 'd')]</synopsis>
                <para>The comparison will be true if b's string value matches one of the strings in
                    the right hand sequence. If an index is defined on <sgmltag>b</sgmltag>, eXist
                    will need only one index lookup to find all b's matching the comparison. The
                    equivalent "or" expression needs 2 separate index lookups.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Querying Multiple Collections</title>
                <para>If you need to query multiple collections which are on the same level of the
                    collection hierarchy, you could use a for loop to iterate over the collection
                    paths. However, this forces the query engine to process the remaining expression
                    once for each collection. It is thus better to construct the initial node set
                    once and use it as input for the main expression. For example:</para>
                <example>
                    <title>Nested for loop</title>
                    <programlisting language="xquery"><![CDATA[
for $path in ('/db/a', '/db/b')
for $result in collection($path)//test[...]
return
    ...
]]></programlisting>
                </example>
                <para>will be less efficient than:</para>
                <example>
                    <title>Single loop over initial node set</title>
                    <programlisting language="xquery"><![CDATA[
let $docs :=
    for $path in ('/db/a', '/db/b') return $collection($path)
for $result in $docs//test[...]
return
    ...
]]></programlisting>
                </example>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Use the ancestor or parent axis instead of a top-down approach</title>
                <para>eXist-db can navigate the ancestor axis as fast as the descendant axis. It can
                    thus be more efficient to build a query bottom-up instead of top-down. Here's a
                    top-down example:</para>
                <example>
                    <title>Top-down query using nested for</title>
                    <programlisting language="xquery"><![CDATA[
for $section in collection("/db/articles")//section
for $match in $section//p[contains(., "XML")]
return
    <match>
        <section>{$section/title/text()}</section>
        {$match}
    </match>
]]></programlisting>
                </example>
                <para>This query walks through a set of sections and queries each of them for
                    paragraphs containing the string "XML". It then outputs the title of the
                    section, followed by the matching paragraphs. Note that it will also return the
                    title of all sections which do not have any matches.</para>
                <para>The nested for loop again forces the query engine into a step-by-step
                    iteration over the section elements. We can avoid this by using a bottom-up
                    approach:</para>
                <example>
                    <title>Bottom-up query using ancestor axis</title>
                    <programlisting language="xquery"><![CDATA[
for $match in collection("/db/articles")//section//p[contains(., "XML")]
return
    <match>
        <section>{$match/ancestor::title/text()}</section>
        {$match}
    </match>
]]></programlisting>
                </example>
                <para>The second query should be several times faster than the first one.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Match regular expressions against the start of a string</title>
                <para>Function fn:matches returns true if any substring of its argument string
                    matches the regular expression. The query engine thus needs to scan all index
                    entries as the match could be at any position of an entry.</para>
                <para>You can reduce the range of entries to be scanned by anchoring your pattern at
                    the start of a string (where applicable):</para>
                <synopsis language="xquery"><![CDATA[fn:matches($str, "^XQuery")]]></synopsis>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Use fn:id to lookup xml:id attributes</title>
                <para>eXist automatically indexes all xml:id attributes and other attributes with
                    type ID as declared in a DTD (only if validation is enabled). This automatic
                    index is used by the standard id functions and provides a fast way to look up an
                    element. For example,</para>
                <synopsis language="xquery">id("sect1")/head</synopsis>
                <para>locates the element with id "sect1" and returns its <sgmltag>head</sgmltag>
                    child. This is done through a fast index lookup. However, please note that the
                    equivalent expression</para>
                <synopsis language="xquery">//section[@xml:id = 'sect1']/head</synopsis>
                <para>will <emphasis>NOT</emphasis> use the id index (you will need to declare an
                    extra range index for that).</para>
                <para>Please be also aware that larger xml:id attribute values cost performance as has been
                    reported by some users working with large databases.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Defer output generation until really needed</title>
                <para>When working with large result sets within a query, it is important to
                    understand the <emphasis>differences between stored nodes and in-memory
                        XML</emphasis>: if a node set consists of nodes which are stored in the
                    database, eXist will usually never load those nodes into memory. Instead, it
                    uses lightweight references for most processing steps. This way, even large node
                    sets do not consume too much memory.</para>
                <para>However, all new XML nodes created within an XQuery will reside in memory and
                    you should be aware that the constructed XML fragments need to fit into the
                    memory available to the Java VM. If a query generates too many nodes, the XQuery
                    watchdog (if enabled) may step in and kill it.</para>
                <para>A typical scenario: a query selects a large number of documents from the
                    database and then iterates through each to generate some HTML output for
                    display. However, only the first 10 results are really returned to the user, the
                    rest is stored into an HTTP session for later viewing.</para>
                <para>In this case it is important to limit the HTML generation to those items which
                    are actually returned. Though the source XML documents may be large, eXist will
                    not load them into memory, but just keep references to them. Storing those
                    references into a session does not consume much memory.</para>
                <example>
                    <title>Limiting output generation</title>
                    <programlisting language="xquery"><![CDATA[let $nodes := (: select some nodes in the db :)
let $session := session:set-attribute("result", $nodes) (: store result into session :)
(: only return the first 10 nodes :)
for $node in subsequence($nodes, 1, 10)
return
    (: Generate HTML for output :)
    <div>(: Create complex HTML markup using $node :)</div>]]></programlisting>
                </example>
                <para>Please note also that eXist-db uses <emphasis>lazy evaluation</emphasis> when
                    constructing new XML fragments. For example:</para>
                <synopsis language="xquery"><![CDATA[<book>{$node/title}</book>]]></synopsis>
                <para>Assuming that $node references a node in the database, the query engine will
                    not copy $node/title into the constructed <sgmltag>book</sgmltag> element.
                    Instead, only a reference is inserted. The reference will not be expanded until
                    the fragment is serialized or queried. So if you only need to wrap selected
                    parts of an element into a new fragment, memory consumption will not be too
                    high.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Known Issues in the 1.2.x Series</title>
            <section>
                <title>Queries on constructed XML fragments</title>
                <para>The 1.2.x series has a limitation with respect to queries on constructed,
                    in-memory XML fragments: before evaluating a path expression on an in-memory
                    node, the query engine stores the node into a persistent document created in a
                    temporary collection of the db. A very simple example is the query:</para>
                <synopsis language="xquery"><![CDATA[(<root><node/></root>)//node]]></synopsis>
                <para>Executing this expression should leave a log message similar to the following
                    in your server logs (if you didn't disable debug messages):</para>
                <screen>06 Mar 2009 16:46:07,786 [main] DEBUG (XQueryContext.java 
                    [storeTemporaryDoc]:2242) - Stored: 3: /db/system/temp/534d7dd16f9b97e6cb47054140e544a1.xml</screen>
                <para>The problem with those temporary fragments is that they need to be cleaned up
                    sometimes. This has a negative influence on performance and the cleanup process
                    can even block the db for a while. Also, experience shows that the overall
                    stability of the db suffers if too many temporary fragments have to be
                    stored/cleaned up in short time.</para>
                <para>eXist-db version 1.4 or newer fixes those issues completely. It has a redesigned query engine,
                    which is able to directly operate on in-memory nodes without transforming them
                    into persistent nodes. No temporary documents need to be stored. As a
                    consequence, queries on in-memory fragments will be much faster with 1.4.0 and
                    have no effect on stability.</para>
                <para>If you experience performance or stability issues with the 1.2.x series, we
                    recommend to check your log files for messages similar to the one given above.
                    If you see lots of them, there are two possibilities:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>upgrade to 1.4.1 </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>find the XQuery expressions which generate the temporary fragments. In
                            many cases, it is easily possible to rewrite them. At least try to
                            reduce the amount of temp documents.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
