<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: security.xml 10003 2009-09-05 08:43:51Z wolfgang_m $ -->
<book>
    <bookinfo>
        <graphic fileref="logo.jpg"/>
        <productname>Open Source Native XML Database</productname>
        <title>Upgrade Guide</title>
        <date>September 2009</date>
        <author>
            <firstname>Wolfgang M.</firstname>
            <surname>Meier</surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address format="linespecific"><email>wolfgang at exist-db.org</email></address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </bookinfo>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="sidebar.xml"/>
    <chapter>
        <title>Upgrade Guide</title>
        
        <section>
            <title>General Information</title>
            
            <para>Never install a new version of eXist into the same directory
                as an older version:</para>
            
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Create a <ulink url="backup.xml">backup</ulink> of your data. If the new version is
                    <emphasis>binary compatible</emphasis> with the old version,
                    keep the data directory (by default in <filename>webapp/WEB-INF/data</filename>)
                    of the old version. Note: eXist needs to be stopped before copying files from the data dir.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Install the new version into a different location.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>If the new version is <emphasis>binary compatible</emphasis>, replace the
                    data directory of the new install with the one from the old one.</para>
                    <para>Otherwise you need to do a full <ulink url="backup.xml#restore">restore</ulink> of the data.</para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Upgrading to 1.4rc</title>
            
            <para>The 1.4 release is not binary compatible with the 1.2.x series. You need to 
                backup/restore.</para>
            
            <section>
                <title>Special Notes</title>
                
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Indexing</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>eXist 1.2.x used to create a default full text index on all 
                                elements in the db. This has been <emphasis>disabled</emphasis>. The
                                main reasons for this are:</para>
                            
                            <orderedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>maintaining the default index costs performance and memory, which
                                        could be better used for other indexes. The index may grow very fast,
                                        which can be a destabilizing factor.</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>the index is unspecific. The query engine cannot use it as efficiently
                                        as a dedicated index on a set of named elements or attributes. Carefully creating 
                                        your indexes by hand will result in much better performance.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </orderedlist>
                            <para>Please consider using the new Lucene-based full text index. However, if you need
                                to switch back to the old behaviour to ensure backwards compatibility, just edit
                                the system-wide defaults in conf.xml:</para>
                            
                            <programlisting>
                                <markup><![CDATA[<index>
    <fulltext attributes="false" default="none">
        <exclude path="/auth"/>
    </fulltext>
</index>]]></markup></programlisting>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Document Validation</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Validation of XML documents during storage is now <emphasis>turned off by default</emphasis>
                                in <filename>conf.xml</filename>:</para>
                            
                            <synopsis language="xml"><![CDATA[<validation mode="no">]]></synopsis>
                            
                            <para>The previous <option>auto</option> setting was apparently too confusing
                                for new users who did not know what to do if eXist refused to store a document
                                due to failing validation. If you are familiar with 
                                <ulink url="validation.xml">validation</ulink>, the use of catalog files and the like,
                                feel free to set the default back to <option>auto</option> or <option>yes</option>.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Cocoon</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>eXist does no longer require Cocoon for viewing documentation
                                and samples. Cocoon has been largely replaced by eXist's own
                                <ulink url="urlrewrite.xml">URL rewriting and MVC 
                                framework</ulink>.</para>
                            <para>Consequently, we now limit Cocoon to one directory of the
                                web application (<filename>webapp/cocoon</filename>) and moved
                                all the Cocoon samples in there. For the 1.4 final, we plan
                                to completely remove Cocoon from the standard distribution, though
                                we would like to continue to provide a separate <emphasis>eXist-as-Cocoon-block</emphasis>
                                distribution.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </section>
            
        </section>
        
    </chapter>
</book>