<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<book>
    <bookinfo>
        <graphic fileref="logo.jpg"/>
        <productname>Open Source Native XML Database</productname>
        <title>XQuery Documentation</title>
        <date>July 2011</date>
        <orgname>The eXist Project</orgname>
        <author>
            <firstname>Wolfgang M.</firstname>
            <surname>Meier</surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address format="linespecific"><email>wolfgang at exist-db.org</email></address>
            </affiliation></author>
        <author>
            <firstname>Leif-Jöran</firstname>
            <surname>Olsson</surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address format="linespecific"><email>ljo at exist-db.org</email></address>
            </affiliation></author>
    </bookinfo>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="sidebar.xml"/>
    <chapter>
        <title>XQuery</title>
        <section>
            <title>Overview (Current Status of XQuery Support)</title>
            <para>eXist-db implements core XQuery syntax (with the exception of XML Schema-related
                features) as specified in the <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/xquery/">W3C
                    recommendation</ulink>. Functions in the standard function library should also
                follow the <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/xpath-functions/">"XQuery 1.0 and XPath
                    2.0 Functions and Operators" recommendation</ulink>. Please check the local
                function library <ulink url="xquery/functions.xql">documentation</ulink>.</para>
            <para>The XQuery implementation is tested against the official XQuery Test Suite (XQTS
                version 1.0.2). This suite contains more than 14,000 tests. As of November 2007,
                eXist-db passes more than 99% of the test suite, but we are continuously trying to
                improve these results. Current test results are reported on the <ulink
                    url="http://xqts.exist-db.org/">web site</ulink>. A good part of the remaining
                failures is caused by smaller problems in the XQuery parser, computed constructors
                and the missing schema support in the eXist-db XQuery engine, though we do have schema support in an extension module.</para>
            <note>
                <para>eXist-db implements ALL features described in the XQuery specification with the
                    EXCEPTION of the following unsupported features:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Schema-related Features: <command>validate</command>, <command>import
                                schema</command>.</para>
                        <para>eXist-db's XQuery processor does currently not support the schema import
                            and schema validation features defined as optional in the XQuery
                            specification. The database does not store type information along with
                            the nodes. It therefore cannot know the typed value of a node and has to
                            assume <option>xs:untypedAtomic</option>. This is the behaviour defined
                            by the XQuery specification.</para>
                        <para>Also, you currently can't specify a data type in an element or
                            attribute test. The node test <command>element(test-node)</command> is
                            supported, but the test <command>element(test-node,
                                xs:integer)</command> will result in a syntax error.</para>
                        <important>
                            <para>To avoid misunderstandings: eXist-db does nevertheless support strong
                                typing whenever the expected type of an expression, a function
                                argument or function return value is explicitely specified or can be
                                known otherwise. Don't expect eXist-db to be laxist about type
                                checks!</para>
                        </important>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </note>
            <para>In addition to the standard features, eXist-db provides extended support for
                    <emphasis>modules</emphasis> and implements the <emphasis>full axis</emphasis>
                feature, which means you can use the <emphasis>optional axes</emphasis>: <command
                    >ancestor</command>, <command>ancestor-or-self</command>, <command
                    >following</command>, <command>following-sibling</command>, <command
                    >preceding</command>, and <command>preceding-sibling</command>.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Function Library</title>
            <para>A complete list of eXist-db-supported XQuery functions can be viewed on the <ulink
                    url="xquery/functions.xql">XQuery Function Documentation</ulink> page or the new
                    <ulink url="functions">XQuery Function Documentation Browser</ulink>. Each function description is taken directly from the signature
                provided by the class implementing the <classname>Function</classname> interface.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>The Module System</title>
            <para>Using eXist-db, you can write entire web applications in XQuery. This may result in
                rather complex XQuery scripts, consisting of several thousand lines of code. Being
                able to package related functions into modules is thus an important feature. eXist-db
                allows modules to be imported from a variety of sources:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>an URI</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>a collection in the database</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>a jar file, i.e. a Java archive</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>a Java class, if the module is itself implemented in Java</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>For example, a typical import statement in an XQuery will look like this:</para>
            <synopsis language="xquery">import module namespace status="http://exist-db.org/xquery/admin-interface/status" 
at "http://exist-db.org/modules/test.xqm";</synopsis>
            <para>Provided that the module namespace does not point to one of the preloaded standard
                modules (see below), the query engine will try to locate the module source by
                looking at the URI given after the <command>at</command> keyword. In the example
                above, the module was specified using a full URI and the query engine will attempt
                to load the module source from the given URI. However, the module could also be
                stored in a database collection:</para>
            <synopsis language="xquery">import module namespace status="http://exist-db.org/xquery/admin-interface/status" 
at "xmldb:exist:///db/modules/test.xqm";</synopsis>
            <para>The query engine recognizes that the module should be stored in the local database
                instance and tries to directly compile it from there.</para>
            <para>If the XQuery module is part of a Java application, it might also be an option, to
                pack the module into a Java archive (.jar file) along with the Java classes and use
                the following import to load the module from a Java package:</para>
            <synopsis language="xquery">import module namespace status="http://exist-db.org/xquery/admin-interface/status" 
at "resource:org/exist/xquery/lib/test.xqm";</synopsis>
            <para>Finally, XQuery modules can also be implemented in Java (see <ulink
                    url="#javamods">below</ulink>), in which case you can import them by specifying
                the class path of the Module class:</para>
            <synopsis language="xquery">import module namespace xdiff="http://exist-db.org/xquery/xmldiff"
at "java:org.exist.xquery.modules.xmldiff.XmlDiffModule";</synopsis>
            <para>The <filename>extensions/modules</filename> directory in the eXist-db distribution
                contains a number of useful modules, which could also serve as examples for
                implementing your own.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Using Relative URIs</title>
                <para>If the location specified in an import statement is a relative URI, the query
                    engine will try to load the module relatively to the current module load path.
                    The module load path is determined as follows:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>if the main XQuery was retrieved from the file system, the module load
                            path points to that directory. This applies to queries executed through
                            the XQueryServlet, XQueryGenerator or the Java admin client.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>if the main XQuery was loaded from a database collection, the module
                            load path is the URI of that collection.</para>
                        <para>For example, if you access an XQuery via the REST server:</para>
                        <synopsis>http://localhost:8080/exist/servlet/db/modules/test.xq</synopsis>
                        <para>All relative module paths will be resolved relative to the <filename
                                >/db/modules</filename> collection.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Builtin Modules</title>
                <para>eXist-db comes with a set of utility modules, which are all implemented in Java.
                    You can also write your own modules as described <ulink url="#javamods"
                        >below</ulink>. Some of these utility modules are frequently used in
                    queries, so they are automatically imported into every query by default.</para>
                <para>The query engine allows you to configure which modules will be auto-loaded.
                    The <sgmltag>builtin-modules</sgmltag> element in <filename>conf.xml</filename>
                    lists the namespaces and implementing classes of all modules to be preloaded
                    into queries:</para>
                <example>
                    <title>Auto-loaded Modules</title>
                    <programlisting>
<markup><![CDATA[<xquery enable-java-binding="no">
    <builtin-modules>
        <module uri="http://exist-db.org/xquery/util"
            class="org.exist.xquery.functions.util.UtilModule"/>
        <module uri="http://exist-db.org/xquery/transform"
            class="org.exist.xquery.functions.transform.TransformModule"/>
    </builtin-modules>
</xquery>]]></markup>
                    </programlisting>
                </example>
                <para>You never need to specify a location when importing a preloaded module. The
                    namespace of the module is already known and eXist-db knows how to load it. Also,
                    auto-loaded modules don't need to be explicitely imported into the main XQuery,
                    though you still need to import them if you want to use them from within another
                    XQuery module. </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>XQuery Caching</title>
            <para>XQuery modules executed via the REST interface, the XQueryServlet or
                XQueryGenerator are <emphasis>automatically</emphasis> cached: the compiled
                expression will be added to an internal pool of prepared queries. The next time a
                query or module is loaded from the same location, it will not be compiled again.
                Instead, the already compiled code is reused. The code will only be recompiled if
                eXist-db decides that the source was modified or it wasn't used for a longer period of
                time.</para>
            <para>If a query is accessed by more than one thread concurrently, each new thread will
                create a new copy of the compiled query. The copies will be added to the query pool
                until it reaches a pre-defined limit.</para>
            <para>Modules are cached along with the main query that imported them.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>eXist-db Extension Functions</title>
            <para>eXist-db offers a number of additional functions and operators, which are discussed
                in some detail in the following subsections.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Specifying the Input Document Set</title>
                <para>A database can contain a virtually unlimited set of collections and documents.
                    By default, database queries that use the XML:DB API will only process the
                    documents in the current XML:DB collection. However, four additional functions
                    are available to change this behavior: <command>doc()</command>, <command
                        moreinfo="none">xmldb:document()</command>, <command moreinfo="none"
                        >collection()</command> and <command>xmldb:xcollection()</command>. The
                        <command>collection()</command> and <command>doc()</command> functions are
                    standard XQuery/XPath functions; whereas, <command>xmldb:xcollection()</command>
                    and <command>xmldb:document()</command> are eXist-db-specific extensions.</para>
                <para>Without an URI scheme, eXist-db interprets the arguments to <command
                        >collection()</command> and <command>doc()</command> as absolute or relative
                    paths, leading to some collection or document within the database. For
                    example:</para>
                <synopsis>doc("/db/collection1/collection2/resource.xml")</synopsis>
                <para>refers to a resource stored in <filename
                        >/db/collection1/collection2</filename>.</para>
                <synopsis>doc("resource.xml")</synopsis>
                <para>references a resource relative to the base URI property defined in the static
                    XQuery context. The base URI contains an XML:DB URI pointing to the base
                    collection for the current query context, e.g. <filename
                        >xmldb:exist:///db</filename>.</para>
                <para>The base collection depends on how the query context was initialized. If you
                    call a query via the XML:DB API, the base collection is the collection from
                    which the query service was obtained. All relative URLs will be resolved
                    relative to that collection. If a stored query is executed via REST, the base
                    collection is the collection in which the XQuery source resides. In most other
                    cases, the base collection will point to the database root /db. </para>
                <note>
                    <para>As it might not always be clear what the base collection is, we recommend
                        to use an explicit path to access a document. This makes it easier to use a
                        query via different interfaces.</para>
                </note>
                <para>You can also pass a full URI to the <command>doc()</command> function:</para>
                <synopsis>doc("http://localhost:8080/exist/servlet/db/test.xml")</synopsis>
                <para>in this case, the URI will be retrieved and the data stored into a temporary
                    document in the database.</para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>doc() / xmldb:document()</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>While <command>doc()</command> is restricted to a single
                                document-URI argument, <command>xmldb:document()</command> accepts
                                multiple document paths to be included into the input node set.
                                Second, calling <command>xmldb:document()</command> without an
                                argument includes <emphasis>EVERY</emphasis> document node in the
                                current database instance. Some examples:</para>
                            <synopsis format="linespecific">doc("/db/shakespeare/plays/hamlet.xml")//SPEAKER</synopsis>
                            <synopsis format="linespecific">xmldb:document('/db/test/abc.xml', '/db/test/def.xml')//title</synopsis>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>collection() / xmldb:xcollection()</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The <command moreinfo="none">collection()</command> function
                                specifies the collection of documents to be included in the query
                                evaluation. By default, documents found in subcollections of the
                                specified collection are also included. For example, suppose we have
                                a collection <filename moreinfo="none">/db/test</filename> that
                                includes two subcollections <filename moreinfo="none"
                                    >/db/test/abc</filename> and <filename moreinfo="none"
                                    >/db/test/def</filename>. In this case, the function call
                                    <command moreinfo="none">collection('/db/test')</command> will
                                include all of the resources found in <filename moreinfo="none"
                                    >/db/test</filename>, <filename moreinfo="none"
                                    >/db/test/abc</filename> and <filename moreinfo="none"
                                    >/db/test/def</filename>.</para>
                            <para>The function <command moreinfo="none"
                                    >xmldb:xcollection()</command> can be used to change the
                                behavior of <command moreinfo="none">collection()</command>. For
                                instance, the function call </para>
                            <synopsis format="linespecific">xmldb:xcollection('/db/test')//title</synopsis>
                            <para>will ONLY include resources found in <filename moreinfo="none"
                                    >/db/test</filename>, but NOT in <filename moreinfo="none"
                                    >/db/test/abc</filename> or <filename moreinfo="none"
                                    >/db/test/def</filename>.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Manipulating Database Contents</title>
                <para>The XML:DB extension functions can be used to create new database collections,
                    or to store query output into the database. To illustrate, suppose we have a
                    large file containing several RDF metadata records, but we do not want to store
                    the metadata records in a single file, since our application expects each record
                    to have its own document. In this case, we must divide the document into smaller
                    units. Using an XSLT stylesheet would be one way to accomplish this - however,
                    it is also a memory-intensive approach. A preferable option is to use XQuery to
                    do the job. </para>
                <para>The XQuery script below shows how to split a large RDF file into a series of
                    smaller documents:</para>
                <example>
                    <title>Splitting a Document</title>
                    <programlisting language="xquery">
<![CDATA[
xquery version "1.0";

declare namespace  xdb="http://exist-db.org/xquery/xmldb";
declare namespace util="http://exist-db.org/xquery/util";

xdb:register-database("org.exist.xmldb.DatabaseImpl", true()),
let $isLoggedIn := xdb:login("xmldb:exist:///db", "admin, ""),
$out := xdb:create-collection("xmldb:exist:///db", "output")
for $rec in /rdf:RDF/* return
    xdb:store($out, concat(util:hash($rec/@rdf:about, "MD5"), ".xml"),
        <rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
            {$rec}
        </rdf:RDF>
    )
]]>
                    </programlisting>
                </example>
                <para>Let's look at this script in some detail. First, since the extension functions
                    are based on the XML:DB API, we have to register a database driver with <command
                        >xdb:register-database</command>. Then we can create a new sub-collection,
                    called "output" using <command>xdb:create-collection</command>, for which we
                    need to be logged in appropriately using <command>xmldb:login</command>.</para>
                <para>Next, the <command>for</command>-loop iterates through all child elements of
                    the top RDF element. In each iteration, we use <command>xdb:store</command> to
                    write out the current child node to a new document. Since a unique document name
                    is required for each new document, we need a way to generate unique names. In
                    this case, the URI contained in the <command>rdf:about</command> attribute is
                    unique, so we simply compute an MD5 key from it, append the ".xml" extension,
                    and use it as the document's name.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Utility Functions</title>
                <para>The function namespace <uri>http://exist-db.org/xquery/util</uri> contains a
                    number of common utility functions. The <command>util:hash</command> function,
                    used in the above example, is one such function. In this subsection, we discuss
                    a few of the important available utility functions. For a complete list, please
                    go to the <ulink url="functions/util">Built-in Functions</ulink>
                    section.</para>
                <para>However, one important function, <command>util:eval</command>, requires
                    further explanation.</para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>util:eval()</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>This function is used to dynamically execute a constructed XQuery
                                expression inside a running XQuery script. This can be very handy in
                                some cases - for example, web-based applications that dynamically
                                generate queries based on HTTP request parameters the user has
                                passed.</para>
                            <para>By default, the dynamically executed query inherits most of the
                                current context, including local variables:</para>
                            <synopsis language="xquery">
let $a := "Hello"
return util:eval("$a")
                            </synopsis>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
                <para>Consider the following simple example script in which any two numbers
                    submitted by a user are added or subtracted: </para>
                <example>
                    <title>Adding/Subtracting Two Numbers</title>
                    <programlisting language="xquery">
<![CDATA[xquery version "1.0";

declare namespace request="http://exist-db.org/xquery/request";
declare namespace util="http://exist-db.org/xquery/util";

declare function local:do-query() as element()
{
    let $n1 := request:get-parameter("n1", ""),
		$n2 := request:get-parameter("n2", ""),
		$op := request:get-parameter("op", "")
	return
		if($n1 = "" or $n2 = "") then
			<p>Please enter two operands.</p>
		else
			let $query := concat($n1, " ", $op, " ", $n2)
			return
				<p>{$query} = {util:eval($query)}</p>
};

<html>
	<body>
		<h1>Enter two numbers</h1>

		<form action="{request:get-uri()}" method="get">
			<table border="0" cellpadding="5">
			<tr>
				<td>First number:</td>
				<td><input name="n1" size="4"/></td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Operator:</td>
				<td>
					<select name="op">
						<option name="+">+</option>
						<option name="-">-</option>
					</select>
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>Second number:</td>
				<td><input name="n2" size="4"/></td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td colspan="2"><input type="submit"/></td>
			</tr>
			</table>
		</form>

		{ local:do-query() }
	</body>
</html>]]>
                                </programlisting>
                </example>
                <para>In this example, there is one XQuery script responsible for evaluating the
                    user-supplied parameters, which uses the parameters from the HTTP request to
                    construct another XQuery expression, which it then passes to <command
                        >util:eval</command> for evaluation. The application would then post-process
                    the returned results, and display them to the user. (For more information on how
                    to write web applications using XQuery, go to our <ulink url="devguide.xml"
                        >Developer's Guide</ulink>.)</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>XSL Transformations</title>
                <para>eXist-db has a function for directly applying an XSL stylesheet to an XML
                    fragment within the XQuery script. This can be very convenient, for example, if
                    your application requirements are basic, and you do not want to install Cocoon
                    to run the XSLT.</para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>transform:transform()</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>This XSL transformation function has the following
                                signature:</para>
                            <synopsis>transform:transform($input as node()?, $stylesheet as
                                item(), $parameters as node()?) as node()?</synopsis>
                            <para>
                                <command>transform:transform</command> expects the node to be
                                transformed in the first argument <option>$input</option>. If
                                    <option>$input</option> is an empty sequence, the function
                                returns immediately.</para>
                            <para>The XSL stylesheet will be read from the location specified in
                                    <option>$stylesheet</option>, which should be either an URI or a
                                node. If $stylesheet is of type xs:anyURI, the function will attempt
                                to load the stylesheet from the specified location. A relative URI
                                is interpreted as a file path. The function then tries to locate the
                                stylesheet in the same way as imported XQuery modules, i.e. relative
                                to the module load directory determined by the static XQuery
                                context.</para>
                            <para>Some examples for referencing the stylesheet:</para>
                            <synopsis>transform:transform($root, doc("/db/styles/style.xsl"), ())</synopsis>
                            <para>Creates the stylesheet from a document node.</para>
                            <synopsis>transform:transform($root, xs:anyURI("style.xsl"), ())</synopsis>
                            <para>Loads the stylesheet from the file <filename>style.xsl</filename>.
                                The function usually expects the file to reside in the same
                                directory as the main query.</para>
                            <synopsis>transform:transform($root, xs:anyURI("http:exist-db.org/style.xsl"), ())</synopsis>
                            <synopsis>transform:transform($root, xs:anyURI("xmldb:exist:///db/styles/style.xsl"), ())</synopsis>
                            <para>The last two examples try to load the stylesheet from an URI.
                                However, the "xmldb:" URI points to a resource stored in the
                                database.</para>
                            <para>The stylesheet will be compiled into a template using the standard
                                Java APIs (<classname>javax.xml.transform</classname>). The template
                                is shared between all instances of the function and will only be
                                reloaded if modified since its last invocation.</para>
                            <para>The <option>$options</option> parameter can be used to pass
                                stylesheet parameters to the XSL processor as an XML fragment - for
                                example:</para>
                            <synopsis><![CDATA[<parameters>
    <param name="param1" value="value1"/>
    <param name="param2" value="value2"/>
</parameters>]]></synopsis>
                            <para>This will set the stylesheet parameter <option>param1</option> to
                                the string value <option>value1</option>, and in the XSL stylesheet,
                                the parameter can then be referenced as follows:</para>
                            <synopsis><![CDATA[<xsl:param name="param1"/>]]></synopsis>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>transform:stream-transform()</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Identical to the <command>transform:transform</command> function,
                                but it directly streams the transformation result to the HTTP
                                request output stream and doesn't return anything. The function is
                                thus only usable in a web context. Note that the servlet output
                                stream will be closed afterwards.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>HTTP-Related Functions</title>
                <para>eXist-db offers functions for handling HTTP request parameters and session
                    variables that use the <uri>http://exist-db.org/xquery/request</uri> namespace.
                    Functions in this namespace are only usable if the query is executed through the
                    XQueryGenerator or the XQueryServlet (for more information consult eXist's
                        <ulink url="devguide.xml">Developer's Guide</ulink> ).</para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>request:get-parameter(<emphasis>name</emphasis>, <emphasis>default
                                value</emphasis>)</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>This HTTP function expects two arguments: the first denotes the
                                name of the parameter, the second specifies a default value, which
                                is returned if the parameter is not set. This function returns a
                                sequence containing the values for the parameter. The above script
                                (Adding/Subtracting Two Numbers) offers an example of how <command
                                    >request:get-parameter</command> can be used to read HTTP
                                request parameters.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>request:get-uri()</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>This function returns the URI of the current request. To encode
                                this URI using the current session identifier, use the following
                                function:</para>
                            <synopsis>session:encode-url(request:get-uri())</synopsis>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>session:create()</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>This function creates a new HTTP session if none exists.</para>
                            <para>Other session functions read and set session attributes, among
                                other operations. For example, an XQuery or Java object value can be
                                stored in a session attribute, to cache query results. For more
                                example scripts, please look at our <ulink url="examples.xml"
                                    >Examples</ulink> page, under the XQuery Examples
                                section.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section id="javamods">
            <title>Java Binding</title>
            <para>eXist-db supports calls to arbitrary Java methods from within XQuery. The binding
                mechanism follows the short-cut technique introduced by <ulink
                    url="http://saxon.sf.net"> Saxon</ulink> (a collection of tools for processing
                XML documents). The class where the external function will be found is identified by
                the namespace URI of the function call. The namespace URI should start with the
                prefix <option>java:</option> followed by the fully qualified class name of the
                class. For example, the following code snippet calls the static method
                    <methodname>sqrt</methodname> (square-root function) of class
                    <classname>java.lang.Math</classname>:</para>
            <example>
                <title>Calling a Static Method</title>
                <programlisting language="xquery"><![CDATA[
declare namespace math="java:java.lang.Math";
math:sqrt(2)
				]]></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>Note that if the function name contains a hyphen, the letter following the hyphen
                is converted to upper-case and the hyphen is removed (i.e. it applies the CamelCase
                naming convention), and so, <code>to-string()</code> will call the Java method
                    <code>toString()</code>.</para>
            <para>If more than one method in the class matches the given name and parameter count,
                eXist-db tries to select the method that best fits the passed parameter types at
                runtime. The result of the method call can be assigned to an XQuery variable. If
                possible, it will be mapped to the corresponding XML schema type. Otherwise, it's
                type is the built-in type <option>object</option>.</para>
            <para>
                <emphasis>Java constructors</emphasis> are called using the function
                    <option>new</option>. Again, a matching constructor is selected by looking at
                the parameter count and types. The returned value is a new Java object with the
                built-in type <option>object</option>.</para>
            <para>
                <emphasis>Instance methods</emphasis> are called by supplying a valid Java object as
                first parameter. The Java object has to be an instance of the given class. For
                example, the following snippet lists all files and directories in the current
                directory:</para>
            <example>
                <title>List Contents of the Current Directory</title>
                <programlisting language="xquery"><![CDATA[
declare namespace file="java:java.io.File";

<files>
    {
        for $f in file:list-files( file:new(".") )
        let $n := file:get-name($f)
        order by $n
        return
            if (file:is-directory($f)) then
                <directory name="{ $n }"/>
            else
                <file name="{ $n }" size="{ file:length($f) }"/>
    }
</files>       			
        		]]></programlisting>
            </example>
            <note>
                <para>For security reasons, the Java binding is disabled by default. To enable it,
                    the attribute <option>enable-java-binding</option> in the central configuration
                    file has to be set to <option>yes</option>: </para>
                <synopsis>&lt;xquery enable-java-binding="yes"&gt;</synopsis>
                <para>Enabling the Java binding bears some risks: if you allow users to directly
                    pass XQuery code to the database, e.g. through the sandbox application, they
                    might use Java methods to inspect your system or execute potentially destructive
                    code on the server.</para>
                <para>The <ulink url="xacml.xml">XACML</ulink> package therefore allows for
                    fine-grained control of the Java binding feature, e.g. restricting access to
                    certain Java classes. Please make sure you have properly set up XACML if you are
                    planning to access Java code via XQuery on a production system. </para>
            </note>
        </section>
        <section id="extension-modules">
            <title>Creating XQuery Modules</title>
            <para>eXist-db supports XQuery-based library modules. These modules are simply collections
                of function definitions and global variable declarations, of which eXist-db knows two
                types: <emphasis>External Modules</emphasis>, which are themselves written in
                XQuery, and <emphasis>Internal Modules</emphasis>, which are implemented in Java.
                The standard XPath/XQuery functions and all extension functions described in the
                above sections are defined through internal modules.</para>
            <para>You can declare an XQuery file as a module and import it using the <command>import
                    module</command> directive. The XQuery engine imports each module only once
                during compilation. The compiled module is then made available through the static
                XQuery context.</para>
            <para>Users can also provide additional Java modules. With the current release, it is
                relatively simple to add these modules, although the current API may change in the
                future. To register a module, eXist-db requires a namespace URI by which the module is
                identified, and the list of functions it supplies. For this, you need only to pass a
                driver class to the XQuery engine, and this class should implement the interface
                    <classname>org.exist.xpath.InternalModule</classname>.</para>
            <para>Moreover, the class <classname>org.exist.xpath.AbstractInternalModule</classname>
                already provides an implementation skeleton. The class constructor expects an array
                of function definitions for all functions that should be registered. A function
                definition (class <classname>FunctionDef</classname>) has two properties: the static
                signature of the function (as an instance of
                    <classname>FunctionSignature</classname>), and the Java Class that implements
                the function.</para>
            <para>A function is a class extending <classname>org.exist.xquery.Function</classname>
                or <classname>org.exist.xquery.BasicFunction</classname>. Functions without special
                requirements (e.g. overloading) should subclass BasicFunction. To illustrate, the
                following is a simple function definition:</para>
            <example>
                <title>A Basic Java Function</title>
                <programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[
public class EchoFunction extends BasicFunction {

public final static FunctionSignature signature =
new FunctionSignature(
	new QName("echo", ExampleModule.NAMESPACE_URI, ExampleModule.PREFIX),
	"A useless example function. It just echoes the input parameters.",
	new SequenceType[] { 
	    new FunctionParameterSequenceType("text", Type.STRING, Cardinality.ZERO_OR_MORE, "The text to echo")
    },
	new FunctionReturnSequenceType(Type.STRING, Cardinality.ZERO_OR_MORE, "the echoed text"));

public EchoFunction(XQueryContext context) {
	super(context, signature);
}

public Sequence eval(Sequence[] args, Sequence contextSequence)
throws XPathException {
	// is argument the empty sequence?
	if (args[0].getLength() == 0)
		return Sequence.EMPTY_SEQUENCE;
	// iterate through the argument sequence and echo each item
	ValueSequence result = new ValueSequence();
	for (SequenceIterator i = args[0].iterate(); i.hasNext();) {
		String str = i.nextItem().getStringValue();
		result.add(new StringValue("echo: " + str));
	}
	return result;
}

}]]></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>In looking at this sample, first note that every function class has to provide a
                function <emphasis>signature</emphasis>. The function signature defines the
                    <emphasis>QName</emphasis> by which the function is identified, a documentation
                string, the sequence types of all arguments, and the sequence type of the returned
                value. In the example above, we accept a single argument named "text" of type
                    <option>xs:string</option> and a cardinality of <option>ZERO_OR_MORE</option>
                with the description "The text to echo". In other words, we accept any sequence of
                strings containing zero or more items. The return value is of type
                    <option>xs:string</option> and a cardinality of <option>ZERO_OR_MORE</option>
                with the description "the echoed text". <emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> The
                parameter description should be normal sentence starting with a capital letter. The
                return value description is always prepended with "Returns ", so have the text to
                match. </para>
            <para>Next, the subclass overwrites the <command>eval</command> method, which has two
                arguments: the first contains the values of all arguments passed to the function,
                the second passes the current context sequence (which might be null). Note that the
                argument values in the array <option>args</option> have already been checked to
                match the sequence types defined in the function signature. We therefore do not have
                to recheck the length of the array: if more or less than one argument were passed to
                the function, an exception would have been thrown before eval gets called.</para>
            <para>In XQuery, all values are passed as sequences. A sequence consists of one or more
                items, and every item is either an atomic value or a node. Furthermore, a single
                item is also a sequence. The function signature specifies that any sequence
                containing zero or more strings is acceptable for our method. We therefore have to
                check if the empty sequence has been passed. In this case, the function call returns
                immediately. Otherwise, we iterate through each item in the sequence, prepend
                    <option>echo:</option>" to its string value, and add it to the result
                sequence.</para>
            <para>In the next step, we want to add the function to a new module, and therefore
                provide a driver class. The driver class defines a namespace URI and a default
                prefix for the module. Functions are registered by passing an array of
                    <option>FunctionDef</option> to the constructor. The following is an example
                driver class definition:</para>
            <example>
                <title>Creating a Driver Class</title>
                <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public class ExampleModule extends AbstractInternalModule {

public final static String NAMESPACE_URI = 
    "http://exist-db.org/xquery/examples";
	
public final static String PREFIX = "example";
	
private final static FunctionDef[] functions = {
	new FunctionDef(EchoFunction.signature, EchoFunction.class)
};
	
public ExampleModule() {
	super(functions);
}

public String getNamespaceURI() {
	return NAMESPACE_URI;
}

public String getDefaultPrefix() {
	return PREFIX;
}

}]]></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>Finally, we are able to use this newly created module in an XQuery script:</para>
            <example>
                <title>Importing a Module</title>
                <programlisting language="xquery">
<![CDATA[xquery version "1.0";

import module namespace example="http://exist-db.org/xquery/examples"
at "java:org.exist.examples.xquery.ExampleModule";

example:echo(("Hello", "World!"))
]]></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>The query engine recognizes the <option>java:</option> prefix in the location URI,
                and treats the remaining part (in this case,
                    <option>org.exist.examples.xquery.ExampleModule</option>) as a fully qualified
                class name leading to the driver class of the module.</para>
        </section>
        <section id="collations">
            <title>Using Collations</title>
            <para>Collations are used to compare strings in a <emphasis>locale-sensitive</emphasis>
                fashion. XQuery allows one to specify collations at several places by means of a
                collation URI. For example, a collation can be specified in the <command>order
                    by</command> clause of a XQuery FLWOR expression, as well as any string-related
                functions. However, the concrete form of the URI is defined by the eXist-db
                implementation. Specifically, eXist-db recognizes the following URIs:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <synopsis>http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions/collation/codepoint</synopsis>
                    <para>This URI selects the unicode codepoint collation. This is the default if
                        no collation is specified. Basically, it means that only the standard Java
                        implementations of the comparison and string search functions are
                        used.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <synopsis>http://exist-db.org/collation?lang=xxx&amp;strength=xxx&amp;decomposition=xxx</synopsis>
                    <para>or, in a simpler form:</para>
                    <synopsis>?lang=xxx&amp;strength=xxx&amp;decomposition=xxx</synopsis>
                    <para>The <option>lang</option> parameter selects a locale, and should have the
                        same form as in <option>xml:lang</option>. For example, we may specify "de"
                        or "de-DE" to select a german locale.</para>
                    <para>The <option>strength</option> parameter (optional) value should be one of
                        "primary", "secondary", "tertiary" or "identical".</para>
                    <para>The decomposition parameter (optional) has the value of "none", "full" or
                        "standard".</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>The following example selects a german locale for sorting:</para>
            <synopsis language="xquery">for $w in ("das", "daß", "Buch", "Bücher", "Bauer", "Bäuerin", "Jagen", "Jäger") 
order by $w collation "?lang=de-DE" 
return $w</synopsis>
            <para>And returns the following:</para>
            <synopsis>Bauer, Bäuerin, Buch, Bücher, das, daß, Jagen, Jäger</synopsis>
            <para>You can also change the default collation:</para>
            <synopsis language="xquery">declare default collation "?lang=de-DE"; 
"Bäuerin" &lt; "Bier"</synopsis>
            <para>Which returns <option>true</option>. Note that if you use the default codepoint
                collation instead, the comparison would evaluate to <option>false</option>.</para>
            <note>
                <para>eXist-db's range index is currently only usable with the default codepoint
                    collation. This means that comparisons using a different collation will not be
                    index-assisted and will thus be slow. We plan to support collation-aware indexes
                    in the 1.3 release.</para>
            </note>
        </section>
        <section id="serialization">
            <title>Serialization Options</title>
            <para>The serialization of query results into a binary stream is influenced by a number
                of parameters. These parameters can be set within the query itself, however the
                interpretation of the parameters depends on the context in which the query is
                called. Most output parameters are applicable only if the query is executed using
                the XQueryGenerator or XQueryServlet servlets, or the REST server.</para>
            <para>Serialization parameters can be set by <option>declare option</option> statement
                in the query prolog. In <option>declare option</option>, the serialization
                parameters can be specified as follows:</para>
            <synopsis>declare option exist:serialize "method=xhtml media-type=application/xhtml+html";</synopsis>
            <para>Here, single options are specified within the string literal, separated by a
                whitespace. Note also that the option QName must be
                <option>exist:serialize</option>, where the <option>exist</option> prefix is bound
                to the namespace <uri>http://exist.sourceforge.net/NS/exist</uri>, which is declared
                by default and need not be specified explicitly.</para>
            <para/>
            <para>Note that these same options can be passed using the
                    <methodname>XPathQueryService.setProperty()</methodname> and
                    <methodname>XQueryService.setProperty()</methodname> methods in Java. These
                methods are defined in <classname>javax.xml.transform.OutputKeys</classname> and
                    <ulink url="api/org/exist/storage/serializers/EXistOutputKeys.html"
                    >EXistOutputKeys</ulink>. The latter eXist-db-specific options include the
                following:</para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>
                        <option>expand-xincludes= yes | no</option>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>should the serializer expand XInclude elements?</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>
                        <option>highlight-matches= both | elements | attributes | none</option>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>when querying text with the full text or n-gram extensions, the query
                            engine tracks the exact position of all matches inside text content. The
                            serializer can later use this information to mark those matches by
                            wrapping them into an element <sgmltag>exist:match</sgmltag>.</para>
                        <para>Setting <option>highlight-matches=both</option> will enable this
                            feature for every kind of indexable node.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>
                        <option>process-xsl-pi= yes | no</option>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>if a document is serialized and it has an XSL processing instruction,
                            eXist-db can try to load the referenced stylesheet and apply it to the
                            document.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>
                        <option>add-exist-id= element | all | none</option>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>shows the internal node ids of an element by adding an attribute
                                <option>exist:id="internal-node-id"</option>. Setting add-exist-id
                            to "element" will only show the node id of the top-level element, "all"
                            will show the ids of all elements.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>The general options include the following:</para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>
                        <option>method= xml | xhtml | text</option>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>determines the serialization method. Should be one of "xml", "xhtml"
                            or "text". The "xhtml" method makes sure that XHTML elements with an
                            empty content model are serialized in the minimized form, i.e. <literal
                                >img</literal> will be output as <sgmltag>img/</sgmltag>. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>
                        <option>media-type</option>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The MIME content type of the output. It will mainly be used to set the
                            HTTP Content-Type header (if the query is running in an HTTP
                            context).</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>
                        <option>encoding</option>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>specifies the character encoding to be used for outputting the
                            instance of the data model</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>
                        <option>doctype-public</option>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>a doctype declaration will be output if doctype-public and/or
                            doctype-system are set. The corresponding identifier is taken from the
                            value of the parameter.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>
                        <option>doctype-system</option>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>a doctype declaration will be output if doctype-public and/or
                            doctype-system are set. The corresponding identifier is taken from the
                            value of the parameter.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>
                        <option>indent= yes | no</option>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>indent the document to make it easier to read. Indenting adds
                            whitespace characters to element nodes, restricted by the rules given in
                            the XQuery serialization spec.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>
                        <option>omit-xml-declaration= yes | no</option>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>output an XML declaration if the parameter is set to "no"</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>For example, to disable XInclude expansion, and indent the output, you can use the
                following syntax:</para>
            <synopsis>declare option exist:serialize "expand-xincludes=no";</synopsis>
            <para>For the output method parameter, eXist-db currently recognizes three methods:
                    <option>xml</option>, <option>xhtml</option> and <option>text</option>. Note
                that unlike the xml method, the xhtml setting uses only the short form for elements
                that are declared empty in the xhtml DTD. For example, the <option>br</option> tag
                is always returned as &lt;br/&gt;. On the other hand, the text method only returns
                the contents of elements - for instance, &lt;A&gt;Content&lt;/A&gt; is returned as
                    <option>Content</option>. However, attribute values, processing instructions,
                comments, etc. are all ignored.</para>
        </section>
        <section id="xqopts">
            <title>Other Options</title>
            <para>To avoid that the server is blocked by a badly formulated query, eXist-db watches all
                query threads. A blocking query can be killed if it takes longer than a specified
                amount of time or consumes too many memory resources on the server. There are two
                options to control this behaviour:</para>
            <synopsis>declare option exist:timeout "time-in-ms";</synopsis>
            <para>Specifies the maximum amount of query processing time (in ms) before it is
                cancelled by the XQuery engine.</para>
            <synopsis>declare option exist:output-size-limit "size-hint";</synopsis>
            <para>Defines a limit for the max. size of a document fragment created within an XQuery.
                The limit is just an estimation, specified in terms of the accumulated number of
                nodes contained in all generated fragments. This can be used to prevent users from
                consuming too much memory if they are allowed to pass in their own XQueries.</para>
            <synopsis>declare option exist:implicit-timezone "duration";</synopsis>
            <para>Specifies the <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/xquery/#dt-timezone">implicit
                    timezone</ulink> for the XQuery context.</para>
            <synopsis>declare option exist:current-dateTime "dateTime";</synopsis>
            <para>Specifies the <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/xquery/#GLdt-date-time">current
                    dateTime</ulink> for the XQuery context.</para>
            <synopsis>declare option exist:optimize "enable=yes|no";</synopsis>
            <para>Temporarily disables the query rewriting optimizer for the current query. Use for
                testing/debugging.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Pragmas</title>
            <para>XQuery pragmas are a way to pass implementation-specific information to the query
                engine from within a XQuery. The syntax for pragmas has changed between the
                different drafts of the XQuery specification. In earlier eXist-db releases, pragmas
                were used similar to what is now the "declare option" prolog expression. The new
                syntax is quite different: pragmas can now be wrapped around an arbitrary XQuery
                expression (see the <ulink
                    url="http://www.w3.org/TR/xquery/#id-extension-expressions"
                    >specification</ulink>). </para>
            <para>Currently, eXist-db recognizes the following pragmas:</para>
            <section>
                <title>exist:timer</title>
                <para>Provides a simple way to measure the time for executing a given expression.
                    For example:</para>
                <synopsis>(# exist:timer #) { //some/path/expression }</synopsis>
                <para>creates a timer for the expression enclosed in curly braces and prints timing
                    information to the trace logger. Please note that trace needs to be enabled in
                        <filename>log4j.xml</filename>:</para>
                <example>
                    <title>Configure log4j to Display Trace Output</title>
                    <programlisting>
	                    <markup><![CDATA[<root>
	    <priority value="trace"/>
	    <appender-ref ref="console"/>
	</root>]]></markup>
	                </programlisting>
                </example>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>exist:batch-transaction</title>
                <para><emphasis>Currently only for XQuery Update Extensions.</emphasis> Provides a
                    method for batching updates on the database into a single Transaction, allowing
                    a set of updates to be atomically guaranteed. Also for each affected document or
                    collection, any configured Triggers will only be called once, the
                        <method>prepare()</method> method will be fired before the first update to
                    the configured resource and the <method>finish()</method> method fired after the
                    last update to the configured resource.</para>
                <synopsis>(# exist:batch-transaction #) {
	            	update value //some/path/expressionA width "valueA",
            		update value //some/path/expressionB width "valueB"
	             }</synopsis>
                <para>Uses a single Transaction and Trigger events for the expressions enclosed in
                    curly braces.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>exist:force-index-use</title>
                <para><emphasis>For debugging purposes</emphasis>. An expression that can be
                    assisted by indexes: comparisons, <function>fn:matches()</function>... Will
                    raise an error if, for any reason, this assistance can not be performed.</para>
                <para>This can help to check whether the indexes are correctly defined or
                    not.</para>
                <synopsis>(# exist:force-index-use #) {
	            	//group[. = "dba"]
	             }</synopsis>
                <para>Raises an error (currently <emphasis>err:XPDYxxxx</emphasis> since this kind of
                    dynamic error is not yet defined by the XQuery specifications) if the general
                    comparison doesn't use a range or a QName index.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>exist:no-index</title>
                <para>This prevents the query engine to use the index in expressions that can be
                    assisted by indexes: comparisons, <function>fn:matches()</function>... Useful if
                    the searched value isn't very selective or if it is cheaper to traverse the
                    previous step of a path expression than querying the index.</para>
                <synopsis>(# exist:no-index #) {
                    //group[. = "dba"]
                 }</synopsis>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>exist:optimize</title>
                <para>For testing only. This pragma is normally inserted automatically by the query
                    rewriter (if enabled) to optimize an expression that implements the
                        <classname>org.exist.xquery.Optimizable</classname> interface.</para>
                <synopsis>//((#exist:optimize#) { item[stock = 10] })</synopsis>
            </section>
            <para>We will certainly add more pragma expressions in the near future. Among other
                things, pragmas are a good way to pass optimization hints to the query
                engine.</para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
